<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>Three sermons tvvo of them appointed for the Spittle, preached in St. Pauls Church, by John Squier, vicar of St. Leonards Shoredich in Middlesex: and John Lynch, parson of Herietsham in Kent.</title>
            <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1637</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 208 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 57 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-04">2011-04 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A12814</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 23120</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S117834</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853044</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853044</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18407</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A12814)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18407)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1220:11)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>Three sermons tvvo of them appointed for the Spittle, preached in St. Pauls Church, by John Squier, vicar of St. Leonards Shoredich in Middlesex: and John Lynch, parson of Herietsham in Kent.</title>
                  <author>Squire, John, ca. 1588-1653.</author>
                  <author>Lynch, John, 1590 or 91-1680. aut</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[4], 108 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Robert Young for Humfrey Blunden, neere the Castle Taverne in Corne-hill,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1637.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>"Pascha Christianum .. By John Lynch" and "A sermon, preached in S. Pauls Church in London, by John Squier priest" each have separate dated title page; register and pagination are continuous.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2009-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-04</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18407:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18407:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>THREE SERMONS: TWO OF THEM APPOINTED FOR The SPITTLE, preached in St. Pauls Church,</p>
            <p>
               <hi>BY</hi> JOHN SQUIER, Vicar of St. <hi>Leonards</hi> Shoredich in <hi>Middleſex:</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>AND</hi> JOHN LYNCH, Parſon of <hi>Herietſham</hi> in KENT.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by <hi>Robert Young</hi> for <hi>Humfrey Blunden,</hi> neere the Caſtle Taverne in Corne-Hill. 1637.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18407:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18407:2"/>
            <head>To the Right Honourable, Sir <hi>Ed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Bromefield</hi> KNIGHT, Lord Maior of <hi>London.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>SIR,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Ee are <hi>Brethren</hi> both by <hi>nature</hi> and <hi>affection;</hi> but (in this) to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards your <hi>Lordſhip</hi> eſpecial<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly. Wee deſire to ſet out theſe <hi>Sermons,</hi> as ſome ſmall ſigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication thereof. Your <hi>Call</hi> did cauſe the <hi>Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> of them, we crave that your <hi>Countenance</hi> may further the <hi>Printing</hi> of them. The <hi>Defects</hi> in either of them, ſhall bee acknowledged by either of us, to be our owne. But if there bee in them ought worth the owning, by the approbation of the charitable Reader; that ſhall be readily aſcribed to our Incourager, by</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your affectionately devoted in all humble and hearty ſervice, JOHN SQUIER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <group>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="introduction">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18407:3"/>
                  <pb n="1" facs="tcp:18407:3"/>
                  <head>For the Spittle, 1637.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>
                        <seg rend="decorInit">E</seg>Ccleſiaſtes</hi> 12.10. doth ſhew the direction of <hi>The Preacher</hi> to all <hi>Preachers:</hi> he did, we ſhould <hi>ſeek out acceptable words.</hi> But <hi>Quis ido<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neus ad haec?</hi> what <hi>Preacher</hi> can preach in this maner? Peradventure no <hi>Preacher, This Preacher</hi> cannot performe it without all per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>adventure. I hope (by Gods gracious aſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance) to prepare for my <hi>Honorable</hi> &amp; <hi>Hono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red</hi> gueſts, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, food which ſhall be <hi>whole<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome;</hi> but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that it ſhall be <hi>Toothſome,</hi> I doe not ſay it, I dare not ſay it. No Chriſtian <hi>Sermon</hi> can be like the Jewiſh <hi>Manna</hi> (accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to that Jewiſh Legend,<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Aug. Retract.</hi> 2.24.</note> to ſavour unto all men according to their ſeverall appetites. Your <hi>Preacher</hi> is far from that faculty of St. <hi>Peter</hi> in his Sermon upon <hi>The Whiteſunday,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Acts</hi> 2.6.</note> to ſpeake to every hearer <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in his <hi>own Idiome</hi> &amp; proper language, <hi>Acceptable words.</hi> If my words be <hi>Accepted,</hi> nay if they be not <hi>Excepted</hi> againſt, it ſhall bee both a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove my deſerts, &amp; beyond my expectation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="2" facs="tcp:18407:4"/>If I pitch upon a point of <hi>Poperie,</hi> I know learned men who would have all <hi>Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> confined to the <hi>Chaire,</hi> not once to ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peare in the <hi>Pulpit: ne Sutor ultra crepidam,</hi> that rurall Miniſters ſhould not climbe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the <hi>Spheare</hi> of their <hi>Activity,</hi> but keep themſelves within the compaſſe of the <hi>Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme,</hi> or of <hi>Caſes</hi> of <hi>Conſcience</hi> at the high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt. If I preach for <hi>Peace</hi> in the Church, and <hi>Conformitie</hi> to the <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of the Church, this diſcourſe, doubtleſſe, will diſpleaſe the <hi>Diſciplinarians.</hi> If I call upon you <hi>to render unto Caeſar what belongeth to Caeſar,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <hi>Luc.</hi> 20.25.</note> to ſubmit your ſelves to the ſupreme <hi>Authoritie,</hi> ſome will whiſper, this is <hi>ambitious Flattery:</hi> and if I exhort the <hi>Countrie</hi> to write after that <hi>Copie</hi> which is ſet them by this <hi>Citie,</hi> and to <hi>imitate</hi> the workes of charity and piety per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed by many worthy <hi>Londoners,</hi> others would condemne me for as pernicious <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pularitie.</hi> If my Text ſhould lead mee to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vouch the dignity and authority of the <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>periours</hi> in our <hi>Clergie,</hi> I ſhould not eſcape that brand, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold a <hi>Time-ſervant,</hi> and a <hi>Man-pleaſer:</hi> and if I plead for the <hi>Liberty</hi> of the <hi>Inferiour Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry,</hi> I may ſinke under the cenſure of that
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:18407:4"/>(which my ſoule abhorreth) favouring or ſavouring of <hi>Schiſme</hi> and <hi>Diſobedience.</hi> If I perſwade the <hi>Duty Of Miniſters,</hi> ſome will ſay, <hi>I lay a burden on my Brethren, which neither they nor their Fore-fathers were ever able to bear:</hi> and if I plead for the <hi>Duty To Miniſters,</hi> I know the aſperſion, that I am an <hi>excellent Advocate in mine owne cauſe,</hi> and that we <hi>take too much upon us we Sonnes of Levi.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If I ſhould pray you (with Saint <hi>Peter</hi>) that you would become a choſen people, Zealous of <hi>good workes,</hi> the <hi>Antinomians</hi> would be <hi>Antagoniſts,</hi> my Adverſaries; ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, that all ſound preachers edifie the hearers by preaching points of <hi>Faith,</hi> and doe not dwell upon the <hi>Workes</hi> of the <hi>Law,</hi> which are not pertinent to <hi>Good Chriſtians,</hi> and to <hi>Men</hi> grown in Religion. If I ſhould ſhew what ſort of <hi>Good workes</hi> I would per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwade you principally to practiſe, namely <hi>all,</hi> but <hi>eſpecially</hi> thoſe of <hi>Piety to the Church,</hi> I ſuppoſe ſome expert Linguiſts would tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate that Greeke ſentence, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in the words of their Apoſtle, <hi>Ad quid perditio haec?</hi> all <hi>Cost is Loſt</hi> which fooliſh Prodigals caſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way on workes of that nature. Or finally, if I ſhould inſtance in an <hi>Individuum,</hi> in a
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:18407:5"/>
                     <hi>Particular</hi> object, which my perſwaſion did propoſe unto your <hi>Piety,</hi> as that <hi>Church</hi> which is conſecrated to the <hi>Service</hi> of <hi>God</hi> by the memoriall of St. <hi>Paul;</hi> there want not Auditors who will avouch, that this ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hortation is ſuperfluous, where a <hi>Pleropho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry</hi> of practice is already precedent; that the <hi>bagges</hi> for that <hi>Building</hi> are like to the <hi>Pitch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers</hi> at the <hi>Marriage</hi> of <hi>Cana,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Full to the Brim;</hi> that there is no room for the <hi>Rich to caſt in their gifts,</hi> no not for the <hi>poore wid<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow to thruſt her Mite</hi> into the treaſurie for the building of the Temple. <hi>O, ſit Veritas in ore Prophetae!</hi> O, may my Exhortations bee al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>waies anſwered by ſuch a <hi>True Anticipati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on!</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now, ſince the <hi>words</hi> of your <hi>Preacher</hi> are but <hi>wind,</hi> and that out of what <hi>Corner</hi> of his mouth ſoever they ſhall blow, ſome hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rers cannot, or will not ſaile according un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to them, how ſhall I ſteere betwixt <hi>Scylla</hi> and <hi>Charybdis,</hi> without ſtriking upon the <hi>Sand</hi> or the <hi>Rocke?</hi> I have a <hi>Cynoſura,</hi> a <hi>Star</hi> to lead me, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Eccleſiastes,</hi> the <hi>grand Preacher</hi> doth point to, to all Preachers, <hi>Luk.</hi> 4.23. <hi>Phyſician heale thy ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Certainly there is no <hi>Patient</hi> but will bee
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:18407:5"/>patient, when hee ſhall ſee his <hi>Phyſitian</hi> ſup up that bitter potion, which he was afraid had beene prepared for his queaſie and relu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctant ſtomacke. I will therefore <hi>lay my fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger upon mine owne ſore,</hi> your infirmities ſhall be a <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> I will not touch them. I will preach <hi>To you,</hi> but <hi>Of my ſelfe,</hi> This way, if any way, I ſhall not offend. And if this way any benefit ſhall ariſe from you to me by the action, or from me to you by the reflection, then for you and me, I ſhall bleſſe my God and your God, with unfained thankſgiving from the bottome of mine heart. Heare therefore (right Honourable, right Worſhipfull, and right dearly beloved in the Lord) the word of the Lord with re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verence and attention.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>LUKE 18.13.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Y <hi>Text</hi> is a <hi>Prayer:</hi> a <hi>Publicans Prayer,</hi> ſo it was; a <hi>publike Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> ſo it is, ſo (I am ſure) it ſhould be: a <hi>Catholike Prayer,</hi> every par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Chriſtian ſhould have a perſonall ſhare therein, every one ſhould alſo <hi>pray, God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For <hi>God</hi> is the <hi>Father</hi> of <hi>All, Sin</hi> is the <hi>Qualitie</hi>
                     <pb n="6" facs="tcp:18407:6"/>of <hi>All, Mercie</hi> is the <hi>Deſire</hi> of <hi>All,</hi> and <hi>Me</hi> ſhould be the <hi>Application</hi> of <hi>All.</hi> Therefore, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, let <hi>All men</hi> pray as <hi>One man,</hi> as <hi>This man, God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Againe, here we have the univerſall <hi>Object</hi> of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, <hi>God:</hi> the univerſall <hi>Subject</hi> of prayer (all men im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed in one man) <hi>Me:</hi> the univerſall <hi>Neceſsitie</hi> to pray, <hi>Sin:</hi> and the univerſall <hi>Motive</hi> to pray, <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie.</hi> Therefore <hi>Hujus ad exemplum totus componitor orbis,</hi> let this <hi>One</hi> man be a Tutour to the <hi>whole World;</hi> all ſhould pray as here he doth pray, <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This is a <hi>Generall Prayer,</hi> and a <hi>Speciall Prayer.</hi> It is <hi>Generall</hi> for <hi>all Times,</hi> and for <hi>all Actions;</hi> but it is moſt <hi>Speciall</hi> for <hi>This Time,</hi> and for <hi>This Action</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove <hi>all</hi> other. Becauſe of our concurrence and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fluence in this holy action of <hi>Speaking</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> Gods holy word, now <hi>Specially</hi> are we bound to uſe this <hi>Prayer, God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I preſume that you will permit the <hi>Speaker</hi> to <hi>Speake</hi> this phraſe; conſidering that I am a man of polluted lips, and an unpoliſhed tongue; of a ſhal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low judgement, and a ſhort memorie: yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I feele that <hi>within me</hi> which may juſtly diſmay me from delivering this <hi>Embaſſage,</hi> from <hi>Speaking For God,</hi> and <hi>Before God.</hi> Therefore <hi>Vae mihi ſi non Evangelizavero, vae mihi ſi non Oravero:</hi> Woe be to that <hi>Preacher</hi> which maketh not <hi>This Prayer</hi> a <hi>Preface</hi> to his <hi>Sermon, God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God be mercifull to MEE;</hi> yea, <hi>God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to YOU Sinners alſo.</hi> I conceive this tranſition
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:18407:6"/>to be no tranſgreſſion: for, <hi>Hom<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> ſum, &amp; nihil Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manum à me alienum eſſe puto:</hi> yee are <hi>Men,</hi> and therefore alſo <hi>Subject to Humane Frailties.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Notwithſtanding this godly goodly appearance, may not ſome appeare in this place with <hi>Partialitie</hi> to the <hi>Cauſe,</hi> or <hi>Prejudice</hi> to the <hi>Perſon?</hi> May not ſome <hi>Zelotes</hi> be <hi>Prodigall</hi> in <hi>Hearing,</hi> and but <hi>Spa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring</hi> in <hi>Practiſing?</hi> Nay, <hi>Ille alter ego Soſia qui ſum domi:</hi> Is it impoſſible for an <hi>Hearer</hi> to have his <hi>Eare</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> and his <hi>Heart</hi> at his <hi>Houſe,</hi> or in a worſe place, in the ſame ſeaſon, and at the ſame Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon? <hi>Jam ſumus ergo pares.</hi> Well may we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore all concurre to elect this <hi>Prayer</hi> of the <hi>Publicane</hi> to be our <hi>Prolocutor</hi> to that <hi>High Houſe.</hi> Here we are in the Sight of God to <hi>Speake</hi> and <hi>Heare</hi> the <hi>Word</hi> of God; in the <hi>Speaking</hi> and <hi>Hearing</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, <hi>God be mercifull to Me, God be mercifull to You,</hi> yea, <hi>God be mercifull to us All</hi> miſerable <hi>Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Object</hi> of our <hi>Prayer</hi> muſt be the <hi>Subject</hi> of my <hi>Sermon,</hi> I meane of the firſt part thereof. <hi>Prayer</hi> is <hi>Peculiar</hi> unto <hi>God.</hi> We may conceive this truth, if we conſider theſe three <hi>Properties,</hi> which are <hi>Pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar</hi> both to <hi>God,</hi> and to the <hi>Proper Object</hi> of <hi>Prayer.</hi> He is <hi>Enter, Potenter, Praeſenter: God</hi> is <hi>Omniſcient, Omnipotent, Omnipraeſent. God Knoweth all Things, Rules all Men,</hi> and <hi>Filleth all Places. God is All in All; per eſſentiam,</hi> becauſe in him <hi>We live, and move, and have our being; per potentiam,</hi> becauſe whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ever God <hi>Will,</hi> that he <hi>Doth</hi> in <hi>Heaven</hi> and in <hi>Earth; &amp; per praeſentiam,</hi> becauſe <hi>there is no creature which is not manifeſt in his ſight: but all things are naked, and opened to the eyes of him with whom we have to doe.</hi> In
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:18407:7"/>a word, <hi>God is in all places, with all perſons, at all ſeaſons,</hi> and therefore the <hi>Abſolute</hi> and <hi>Onely Object</hi> of our <hi>Prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If you would have it yet more plainly, No <hi>Man</hi> can ſay more in his <hi>Sermon,</hi> than every <hi>Child</hi> doth ſpeak in his <hi>Catechiſm. God</hi> is <hi>Pater Coeleſtis,</hi> our <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venly Father:</hi> a <hi>Father</hi> which <hi>Will,</hi> and an <hi>Heavenly</hi> Father which <hi>Can</hi> heare and help us. This is his <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pertie, Soli ac Semper, Proper</hi> to him <hi>alone,</hi> and to <hi>None</hi> but him. God therefore <hi>muſt</hi> be <hi>adaequatum Objectum Orationis: Invocation</hi> is his <hi>Roialtie,</hi> and whoſoever doth trench into this <hi>Prerogative,</hi> he is guiltie of <hi>High Treaſon</hi> againſt the <hi>Heavenly Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>narch. Give</hi> therefore <hi>unto Caeſar that which belon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geth to Caeſar.</hi> Let our <hi>Prayers</hi> be directed to the right <hi>Object: God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>We muſt <hi>Pray to God,</hi> but not as the Athenians did, <hi>Sacrifice to God,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to the <hi>Unknowne God.</hi> Wee muſt not be <hi>Samaritans</hi> to <hi>worſhip wee know not what,</hi> but we muſt be <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> we ſhould <hi>Know what we worſhip.</hi> For the attaining of this <hi>Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge,</hi> as the <hi>Eye</hi> of our <hi>Bodie</hi> is to the <hi>Sun,</hi> ſo is our <hi>Underſtanding</hi> the <hi>Eye</hi> of our <hi>Soule</hi> to <hi>God.</hi> If the <hi>Eye</hi> of a man ſhall <hi>Directly</hi> looke upon the <hi>Sun,</hi> the <hi>Sun</hi> will dazle it, and blind it: but caſt downe your <hi>Eye</hi> into the <hi>Water,</hi> and therein you may ſee the <hi>Shape</hi> of the <hi>Sun.</hi> So <hi>God</hi> doth inhabit, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>Light</hi> man cannot <hi>looke upon:</hi> but reflect our cogi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations to the <hi>Waters,</hi> to his <hi>Creatures,</hi> to that <hi>Sea</hi> of <hi>Glaſſe,</hi> to his <hi>Scriptures,</hi> in theſe we ſhall <hi>See our God Shadowed</hi> unto us, in theſe ſhall we <hi>See</hi> that which will be <hi>Sufficient for,</hi> and <hi>Efficient of</hi> our <hi>Happineſſe</hi>
                     <pb n="9" facs="tcp:18407:7"/>in generall, and our <hi>Holineſſe</hi> in this particular, in the performance of this worke of pietie; when we goe to <hi>Speake Of and before God,</hi> by <hi>Preaching:</hi> and <hi>To and with God,</hi> by our <hi>Prayer</hi> and <hi>Invocation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I ſhall not take <hi>Gods Name in Vaine,</hi> if I uſe it to this purpoſe, by it to ſhaddow out <hi>Gods</hi> majeſtie to our apprehenſion.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gods Name,</hi> according to the Hebrew, hath two roots, ſignifying one, but implying three things; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Jehovah</hi> is derived of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> both ſignify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to <hi>Bee:</hi> becauſe <hi>God is,</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>The Being,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>Giveth Our Being,</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. Maketh his <hi>Promiſes</hi> to <hi>Bee</hi> infallibly; <hi>without any Variableneſſe or Shadow of Turning.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. The <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>God Jehovah,</hi> ſignifying <hi>Being,</hi> by the change of three letters, doth imply <hi>God</hi> to <hi>Bee the Being,</hi> according to the threefold diſtinction, of time, or <hi>Being.</hi> From his <hi>Name Jehovah,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>draw the letter <hi>Jod;</hi> and it ſignifieth the time <hi>Paſt, Fuit, he hath been:</hi> Change in the ſame <hi>Name,</hi> ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther letter, <hi>Camets</hi> into <hi>Cholem,</hi> and it ſignifieth the time <hi>Preſent, Ens</hi> or <hi>Exiſtens,</hi> he that is now <hi>Being:</hi> and <hi>Jod,</hi> and it is the <hi>Future,</hi> the <hi>Time</hi> to <hi>Come, Erit Hee</hi> that <hi>Will Be.</hi> Hence <hi>God</hi> himſelfe ſaid that his <hi>Name</hi> was <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Ero,</hi> which the <hi>Septuagints</hi> tran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſlate <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <hi>Plato</hi> doth terme <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>Perſon</hi> or <hi>Thing</hi> which hath a <hi>Perpetuall Being.</hi> St. <hi>John</hi> more cleerely, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>He who Was, Is, and is to Come.</hi> To which that inſcription of the <hi>Egyptians</hi> in their <hi>Temples,</hi> to their <hi>God,</hi> is anſwerable, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>I am</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>He that ever Was,</hi> that <hi>Is, and Ever Shall be.</hi> By <hi>Name Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hovah: The God of Eternall and everlaſting Being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:18407:8"/>2. From <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>Bee,</hi> God is called <hi>Jehovah;</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe he <hi>Giveth Being to All,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>The Lord made all Things, and formed Thee from the Wombe.</hi> The <hi>Egyptians</hi> emblematically expreſſe him by an <hi>Egge:</hi> that as <hi>all Fowles</hi> are <hi>bred</hi> of it, ſo all <hi>Things</hi> are <hi>made</hi> by <hi>Him. Hee</hi> is our <hi>Father, Hee</hi> is our <hi>Jehovah,</hi> in him we <hi>live, and move, and have our Being.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. From <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>Bee, God</hi> is called <hi>Jehovah,</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe hee doth give a <hi>Being to All his Promiſes,</hi> and maketh them <hi>All Yea and Amen.</hi> He is known to us, not onely by the Name <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> of <hi>God Almightie,</hi> but alſo by the <hi>Name Jehovah,</hi> that is, he who <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſeth</hi> us <hi>Deliverance</hi> from <hi>Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Pharaoh;</hi> from the <hi>Spirituall Egypt,</hi> and <hi>Eternall Pharaoh;</hi> both from the <hi>Sinne</hi> of <hi>Man,</hi> and from <hi>That Man</hi> of <hi>Sin.</hi> And his <hi>Promiſes</hi> are like the <hi>Capitol,</hi> built upon <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mobile Saxum,</hi> a ſtone that will never ſhrink: like the <hi>Center,</hi> they are <hi>immovable:</hi> like the <hi>Lawes of the Medes and Perſians,</hi> they can <hi>Never be Altered:</hi> like the <hi>Angel</hi> to <hi>Sarah,</hi> at the <hi>Time appointed they will come:</hi> and like the <hi>Law,</hi> not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> nor <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <hi>one Jote</hi> or <hi>Title</hi> of them ſhall <hi>fall. In thee O God (Jehovah) doe wee put our truſt: O Lord (Jehovah) let us never be put to confuſion.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here in the <hi>Greek,</hi> he is called <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>God;</hi> of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to <hi>Run,</hi> or of <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Feare<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> becauſe <hi>in our Feare,</hi> wee muſt <hi>run to Him;</hi> He will be our <hi>Aſylum,</hi> our <hi>San<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuarie;</hi> none can pluck us out of his hand. <hi>If God be on our Side, we will not feare what man can doe unto us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Latins</hi> terme him <hi>Deus,</hi> of <hi>Dedit</hi> hee <hi>Gave,</hi>
                     <pb n="11" facs="tcp:18407:8"/>becauſe hee <hi>Gave all</hi> things to <hi>all men. Man</hi> is made by <hi>God;</hi> like that <hi>Woman Pandora;</hi> all indowments are his Gifts. From the <hi>Haire</hi> on our <hi>Heads,</hi> to the <hi>Bloud</hi> in our <hi>Hearts;</hi> from the <hi>latches</hi> of our <hi>ſhooe,</hi> to the <hi>Inheritance</hi> of our <hi>Anceſtors;</hi> from the <hi>Labour</hi> of of your <hi>Hands,</hi> to the <hi>Studie</hi> of our <hi>Minds;</hi> from the <hi>Policie</hi> of Statſemen, to the <hi>Simplicitie</hi> of Chriſtians: both the <hi>Spirit</hi> of <hi>Wiſedome,</hi> and the <hi>Wiſdome</hi> of the <hi>Spirit;</hi> of <hi>All,</hi> we muſt ſay, what that <hi>Prophet</hi> did of his <hi>Hatchet, Alas it is but Borrowed: Deus Dedit, God</hi> is the <hi>Fountaine</hi> of <hi>all our Abilities.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In our owne language, his <hi>name</hi> is <hi>God,</hi> becauſe he is the <hi>Efficient of all Good. God</hi> doth feed us with his <hi>Good Creatures,</hi> guard us with his <hi>Good Angels,</hi> inſtruct us with his <hi>Good Word,</hi> comfort us by his <hi>Good Spirit,</hi> and preſerve, prevent, ſanctifie, and ſave us by his <hi>Good Grace.</hi> This is our <hi>Good,</hi> this is our <hi>God.</hi> O my ſoule reſt and rejoyce in him.</p>
                  <p>Since then, <hi>God</hi> is <hi>Jehovah;</hi> hee who is <hi>all. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Originally</hi> in <hi>Himſelfe,</hi> and <hi>Derivatively</hi> to all <hi>Perſons,</hi> by his <hi>Promiſes:</hi> Hee is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to whom we muſt <hi>run,</hi> in all our <hi>feares,</hi> and afflictions: He is <hi>Deus,</hi> the <hi>Giver</hi> of all we <hi>have,</hi> and <hi>Are:</hi> And fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nally, hee is our <hi>Good;</hi> all the <hi>Good</hi> our head can looke after, or our heart can long after: oxternall, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall, eternall: Certainely we ſhould <hi>Pray,</hi> and <hi>Pray</hi> perpetually, to that <hi>Perſon,</hi> propoſed here in our text; <hi>God,</hi> yea <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now this <hi>God,</hi> this <hi>Jehovah</hi> is <hi>One,</hi> or rather very <hi>Oneneſſe,</hi> and meere <hi>Unitie,</hi> having nothing <hi>but is ſelfe, in it ſelfe,</hi> and not conſiſting (as things doe beſides God) of many things. Howbeit this <hi>One,</hi> is <hi>Three:
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:18407:9"/>One Subſtance, Three Perſons:</hi> The <hi>Father,</hi> the <hi>Son,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt; Co-equall,</hi> and <hi>Co-eternall;</hi> the <hi>Unitie</hi> in the <hi>Trinitie,</hi> and the <hi>Trinitie</hi> in the <hi>Unitie,</hi> to be worſhipped and glorified.</p>
                  <p>If any would <hi>know</hi> more; <hi>know</hi> moreover, that <hi>God</hi> being a <hi>Pure Act,</hi> is <hi>moſt knowable</hi> in <hi>Himſelfe;</hi> yet leaſt <hi>knowable to us:</hi> becauſe he muſt be <hi>known</hi> to us, by our <hi>Intellect</hi> or <hi>Underſtanding;</hi> but the <hi>Object,</hi> to be <hi>Underſtood,</hi> by its <hi>excellence,</hi> doth <hi>exceed</hi> our <hi>Facultie</hi> of <hi>Underſtanding.</hi> As the <hi>Sunne</hi> is <hi>Viſible</hi> in it ſelfe, yet it maketh it <hi>Selfe</hi> to bee <hi>inviſible,</hi> and not to be <hi>ſeene</hi> or looked upon by <hi>Bats,</hi> and <hi>Owles,</hi> by the luſtre and <hi>excellent Light</hi> thereof: So, both becauſe of the <hi>Abſtruſeneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Object,</hi> and <hi>Obtuſeneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Subject;</hi> it is impoſsible that there ſhould bee a perfect <hi>knowledge</hi> of <hi>God</hi> in <hi>Man.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I remember, I have read that <hi>Hiero</hi> the King, de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded of <hi>Simonides,</hi> the <hi>Philoſopher Quid eſt Deus, what is God?</hi> That learned man <hi>Petebat Diem,</hi> craved a <hi>Day</hi> for to ſhape him anſwer. The ſecond day hee demands the ſecond time; <hi>Quid eſt Deus, what is God?</hi> He begg'd <hi>Biduum,</hi> two dayes to anſwer him. The third <hi>Day, Three Daies:</hi> till in the concluſion he in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>genuouſly confeſſed, that the <hi>More hee ſtudied, the Leſſe he was inabled to declare, What God it.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>And indeed, according to the <hi>Viſion</hi> of that <hi>Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> it is eaſier for a <hi>Child</hi> to take up the <hi>Ocean</hi> in a <hi>Shell;</hi> than for any man to comprehend in his <hi>Scull, What God is.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Tu es interior intimo meo, &amp; ſuperior ſummo meo,</hi> ſaid the holieſt of the Fathers. <hi>God</hi> is more inward than our moſt inward <hi>Cogitations: God</hi> is more high
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:18407:9"/>than our moſt high <hi>Speculations.</hi> The <hi>God of Peace,</hi> is like the <hi>Peace of God; Hee paſſeth all Underſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wherefore our ſafeſt eloquence concerning <hi>God</hi> is ſilence, when we confeſſe without confeſſion, that his goodneſſe is inexplicable, his greatneſſe above our capacitie and reach. He is above, we upon earth: there fore it behoveth our words to bee warie and few.</p>
                  <p>I ſoare too high, I will be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I will ſtoope to the <hi>Ground;</hi> and build the concluſion of this point upon the <hi>Grounds</hi> of Religion, upon the <hi>Principles</hi> in our Engliſh <hi>Catechiſme. Quid Deus, what is God? God is our Father,</hi> which is in <hi>Heaven: God is the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mightie maker of heaven and earth. O Father in hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, O Maker of heaven, O God</hi> (yea) <hi>God be merci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full to mee a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here we may caſt both our eies, on two notes: yet neither ſhall bee able to diſcerne, whether is moſt noteable. Our incomparable <hi>Neceſsitie To Pray,</hi> and our incomparable <hi>Commoditie,</hi> if we <hi>Doe Pray.</hi> Both theſe are inferred from this; <hi>that God</hi> is the <hi>Object of Prayer,</hi> or the <hi>Perſon</hi> which is <hi>onely</hi> to be <hi>Prayed</hi> unto. But let this <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Thame,</hi> fall into one <hi>Thamiſis:</hi> let this <hi>Jor</hi> and <hi>Dan,</hi> fall into <hi>one Jor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dan.</hi> Let both theſe notes bee handled in one: that their confluence may make the fuller fountaine, ſtrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming out the more plentifull inſtructions.</p>
                  <p>The ground worke whereof I ſuppoſe bee, and ſo propoſe this propoſition; <hi>Jovis omnia Plena, our God is in everie Place:</hi> and therefore our <hi>Prayer</hi> ſhould be ſo alſo.</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <pb n="14" facs="tcp:18407:10"/>1 Our <hi>Prayer</hi> ſhould bee as our <hi>God</hi> is, <hi>in temple Cordis, &amp; in corde Temple,</hi> both in the <hi>Temple of our Heart,</hi> and in the <hi>Heart of our Temple.</hi> In our <hi>Heart</hi> God is inthroned, <hi>tanquam Rex in Throno,</hi> like a King in his Tribunall, where each oppreſſed Subject ought to exhibite his <hi>Petition,</hi> with all ſubmiſſure ſupplication. This place the Church is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> here it t<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>chiefeſt</hi> part of Gods <hi>People,</hi> and the <hi>chie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt</hi> part of Gods <hi>Temple:</hi> here then we ſhould eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially indeavour to make our <hi>Prayers aſcend like in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cenſe, and the lifting up of our hands to be as the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning ſacrifice.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 In your <hi>Journies</hi> from the Church to your hou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes, or to any place from your houſes, he who is <hi>Via,</hi> the <hi>Way,</hi> cannot be out of your company: your duty therefore is to crave <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to bee <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to <hi>Pray God</hi> to be your <hi>Guide,</hi> and to <hi>Bleſſe</hi> you in all your underta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kings.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 If your <hi>Callings</hi> call you into the <hi>Market,</hi> con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive that he who is <hi>Veritas,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> cannot be ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded out of <hi>your preſence,</hi> although he may bee abu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed in his <hi>owne preſence.</hi> Let <hi>Prayer</hi> therefore <hi>open thy heart,</hi> that <hi>God may open thy mouth,</hi> that thou maiſt nor <hi>Lye</hi> nor <hi>Sweare</hi> in thy buying and ſelling.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 If you glance an eye into a <hi>Shep</hi> (as you pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed) it is not impoſſible to ſuppoſe that you ſee our inviſible <hi>God,</hi> even there alſo. Hee that is <hi>Vita, Life</hi> it ſelfe, muſt give <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Maintenance</hi> to their life, if any <hi>Thrift grow in that Garden.</hi> Their pain there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore would not be much more, nor their gaine much leſſe, if <hi>Tradeſmen</hi> ſhould bleſſe their labour with a ſhort ejaculation, <hi>Proſper thou the works of our hands
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:18407:10"/>upon <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>, O Lord; O Lord proſper Thou our handy worker.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 When you arrive at your owne <hi>Houſe,</hi> know that <hi>Domus Tua</hi> is <hi>Domus Dei: that if God had not built thy houſe, their labour had beene but in vaine that built it.</hi> Know moreover, that if he be not everie moment the <hi>grouncell, beame,</hi> and <hi>buttrice</hi> to ſupport it, the next minute ſhould not ſee <hi>one ſtone upon another.</hi> If therefore <hi>Thine Houſe</hi> bee <hi>Gods Houſe,</hi> uſe <hi>Gods phraſe, Domus men domus Oration is vocabitur, My Houſe ſhall bee called an Houſe of Prayer. Prayer</hi> ſhould be <hi>Seranoctis;</hi> hee who ſhutteth up the Eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning without ſaying <hi>Prayers,</hi> hee doth <hi>Bolt out God,</hi> and <hi>let in</hi> the <hi>Devill;</hi> a fearefull <hi>Sojounar. Prayer</hi> ſhould be <hi>Clavis diei,</hi> he who <hi>ſpeaketh to God</hi> by <hi>Prai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er</hi> in the <hi>Morning,</hi> is ſure of <hi>
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap> good morrow.</hi> At <hi>Meals,</hi> have <hi>Grace</hi> before <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap> grace after meat: and let gracious diſcourſes be the ſalet, ſauce, and ſalt to ſeaſon your banquet; that <hi>Cibus mentis</hi> may ſeem more ſavourie to thy <hi>Soule,</hi> than <hi>Cibus ventris</hi> to thy appetite. Happy is that <hi>Feaſt</hi> where <hi>God</hi> is a <hi>Gueſt,</hi> there cannot but be a bleſſing at ſuch a meeting. Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceeding from your repaſt to your <hi>Reſt:</hi> thy <hi>Chamber</hi> ſhould be to thee as <hi>Bethel</hi> was to <hi>Jacob; Surely God is in that place, though ſome men doe not know it.</hi> O, may <hi>Prayer</hi> then (be your <hi>Caduceus</hi>) cloſe your eies! happy is that man who ſo goeth to <hi>Bed,</hi> that <hi>God</hi> is in his <hi>Bed-chamber,</hi> and <hi>Prayer his Bed-fellow.</hi> Final<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, honeſt <hi>Alipius,</hi> powred out his holy <hi>Prayers,</hi> in a more homely <hi>Place:</hi> knowing that the <hi>Sunne</hi> can <hi>ſhine</hi> on a <hi>Dungbill,</hi> without contracting any thing that is unſavoury to the <hi>impaſsible Beames</hi> thereof.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:18407:11"/>Thus the firſt word of my text doth ſhew what muſt be the firſt word in our <hi>Prayers:</hi> Wee have the <hi>Publican</hi> for our <hi>Precedent,</hi> and he <hi>Prayed</hi> thus, <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 To returne and review all theſe <hi>Places</hi> and <hi>Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, ordine retrogrado;</hi> firſt of the laſt. Some need not be daintie of their devotion, no not in that place, as though the <hi>Place</hi> did <hi>pollute</hi> their <hi>Prayers,</hi> when it may be feared that their <hi>Prayers pollute</hi> the <hi>Place.</hi> If not the <hi>Prayers,</hi> yet the <hi>Thoughts</hi> of ſome men are more <hi>foule</hi> than the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the very <hi>Draught</hi> into which they disburden the <hi>Filth</hi> of nature. But <hi>aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cend</hi> we to the <hi>Chamber,</hi> there peradventure we ſhall meet with <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſome foot-print of <hi>Prayer.</hi> Alas it is ſuſpected, that even when they go to <hi>Sleepe,</hi> the <hi>Husband</hi> is like <hi>Tyrannous Lamech,</hi> and the <hi>Wife</hi> like <hi>querulous Zipperah: Hos Deus conjun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>xit?</hi> Can ſuch <hi>Dreame</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> when the <hi>Divell</hi> cau<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeth them to <hi>Sleepe</hi> in ſuch unſeemly contention? From the <hi>Bed</hi> deſcend unto the <hi>Bord:</hi> there indeed we ſhall heare <hi>formall Prayers,</hi> both before and after meat; but the <hi>Interim</hi> is oftentimes interlarded with ſuch <hi>diſcourſes</hi> and <hi>diſgraces,</hi> with ſuch <hi>cenſuring</hi> and <hi>judging,</hi> as if they indevoured that their <hi>Tongues</hi> ſhould <hi>teare</hi> the <hi>names</hi> of the abſent into ſmaller pie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, than their <hi>Teeth</hi> can their <hi>Meat</hi> in their mouths. Surely if <hi>God</hi> bee <hi>Charity, God</hi> cannot bee preſent at ſuch <hi>uncharitable</hi> eating.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 When they ariſe and walke, <hi>egredientem armat Oratio? regredienti occurrit Oratio?</hi> Doe ſome by their <hi>prayers</hi> ſay ſo much as <hi>God ſpeed</hi> to their <hi>Jour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney?</hi> If there be no <hi>invocation,</hi> how can there be any
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:18407:11"/>
                     <hi>expectation</hi> of <hi>Gods</hi> bleſſing upon their <hi>going</hi> out, or <hi>comming</hi> home againe.</p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Market,</hi> that <hi>Old lying Legend</hi> hath a true morall, <hi>of an old Devill lying on his elbow faſt aſleepe in the Market place,</hi> becauſe (ſaid he) temptations in this place are ſuperfluous. For ſuch <hi>Buyens</hi> and <hi>Sel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lers,</hi> ſuch <hi>Lyers</hi> and <hi>Stealers,</hi> will to <hi>Hell</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of their own good nature and prompt inclination, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out any externall or infernall provocation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> And ſome ſay the ſame of ſome <hi>Shep keepers,</hi> that they concurre in the ſame kinde alſo, by way of Retaliation. Becauſe <hi>Chriſt</hi> did once <hi>whip</hi> the <hi>Buyers</hi> and <hi>Sellers</hi> out of the <hi>Temple,</hi> therefore <hi>Buyers</hi> and <hi>Sellers</hi> doe now every day <hi>whip Chriſt out of their ſhops</hi> and <hi>markets.</hi> O unchriſtian dealing! <hi>what ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage will it bee for a man to gaine the whole world, and to loſe his owne ſoule?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 But our meditations being come hither, we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but conceive here, <hi>etiam faciem Dei vider, God to be preſent in a more illuſtrious manner.</hi> For if in any earthly place, where can we look to finde the <hi>Lord of the Temple, if not in the Temple of the Lord,</hi> in our congregations and Churches: But alas, <hi>poſteriora tantum,</hi> his glorious preſence is infinitely eclipſed by our infinite infirmities, admitted even in theſe holy meetings. <hi>God</hi> indeed is here <hi>ſpeaking</hi> in our <hi>Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mons, hearing</hi> in our <hi>Prayers, ſeeing</hi> in both: but our behaviour acknowledgeth his <hi>preſence</hi> in neither, we have ſo little <hi>baring of the Head</hi> at the one, and <hi>ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding of the Knee</hi> at the other. I have ſeene as <hi>much Reverence</hi> (and more) performed by <hi>ſervants</hi> to their <hi>Maſtar,</hi> at his <hi>Table,</hi> and in his <hi>Kitchin,</hi> than by, <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſors</hi>
                     <pb n="18" facs="tcp:18407:12"/>to their <hi>God,</hi> in his <hi>Temple.</hi> Now I perſwade my ſelfe, that if we were perſwaded that <hi>God were in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed preſent amongſt us at our meetings in our Churches,</hi> we would ſignifie it by a more <hi>reverent geſture.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, Gods reſidence is in the <hi>Sanctum ſancto<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rum,</hi> in our <hi>Heart</hi> no qu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſtion. Bleſſed is the <hi>Heart</hi> which knoweth it ſo. Bleſſed is that man which can ſpeake that language, <hi>My Heart is prepared, my Heart is prepared: in utrumque paratum,</hi> both for <hi>Hearing</hi> and <hi>Praying.</hi> Then ſhould we not feare ſuch <hi>Detra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions for our Sermons,</hi> nor you feele ſuch <hi>Diſtracti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons in your Devotions.</hi> But I feare our <hi>Heart</hi> doth know that <hi>God</hi> is not, and <hi>God</hi> doth know that our <hi>Heart</hi> is not alwayes <hi>preſent in theſe holy places, at theſe holy exerciſes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To contract all our omiſſions into one compendi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um. Thus we ſee, that from our <hi>Bed</hi> to our <hi>Boord,</hi> from our <hi>Shops</hi> to our <hi>Markets,</hi> from our <hi>Houſes</hi> to our <hi>Churches,</hi> from the <hi>Action</hi> in this <hi>Place</hi> to the <hi>Affection</hi> of our <hi>Perſons, God</hi> and <hi>Prayer</hi> are too of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten <hi>Abſent</hi> from us.</p>
                  <p>Surely that in all theſe things <hi>we forget God,</hi> we are moſt miſerable: but if in all theſe <hi>God did forget us</hi> (to be <hi>Mercifull</hi>) we were more than moſt miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable. Let therefore our ſolid <hi>Hearts</hi> be like the hollow <hi>Mountaines, Echoing</hi> out <hi>One</hi> word, the firſt word of my <hi>Text, God, God,</hi> yea <hi>God be mercifull to us miſerable Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Here conceive me aright: I doe not <hi>prie</hi> to <hi>ſpie</hi> a <hi>Mote</hi> in your <hi>Eye,</hi> and <hi>winke</hi> at a <hi>Beame</hi> in mine own <hi>Soule.</hi> I ingenuouſly confeſſe I doe but <hi>ſee</hi> but the <hi>Shadow</hi> of theſe Sinnes in you by my <hi>Contemplation,</hi>
                     <pb n="19" facs="tcp:18407:12"/>but I <hi>feele</hi> the ſame, or ſome ſuch, in my ſelfe, the <hi>Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy</hi> of Sin, in my <hi>Converſation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Diogenes conculcabat Platonis faſtum, at fastu majori:</hi> I trample (ſaid <hi>Diogenes</hi>) on the <hi>Pride</hi> of <hi>Plato;</hi> but (replied <hi>Plato</hi>) with a <hi>greater Pride.</hi> I acknowledge I would <hi>trample downe</hi> theſe your <hi>Sins, forgetting of God to be alwayes Preſent,</hi> and <hi>forgetting of Your Selves, that You are ſo Irreverent</hi> at your <hi>Prayers</hi> in his <hi>Preſence,</hi> but with a <hi>Greater Sin.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I confeſſe that I have not that awfull apprehenſion of Gods dreadfull <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, of his <hi>Perpetuall Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence</hi> in my <hi>Church,</hi> in my <hi>Chamber,</hi> in my <hi>Cloſet</hi> and cloſeſt <hi>Conclave,</hi> not in my <hi>Heart,</hi> which is due to our <hi>Great Jehovah.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I confeſſe <hi>Prayer</hi> doth <hi>dwell</hi> with me as St. <hi>Peter</hi> did with the <hi>Tanner,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, it doth but <hi>Sojourn</hi> with me, and God knoweth it is too often <hi>Abſent</hi> from me.</p>
                  <p>I am not to that holy <hi>Devotion</hi> as Saint <hi>Peter</hi> was to <hi>Tabor: bonum eſt nobis eſſe Hic:</hi> I doe not de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>light to <hi>Dwell</hi> there. I doe not ſay, alas, I cannot ſay, <hi>Faciamus tria Tabernacula, O let us build three Ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bernacles one for God, one for Prayer, and one for Thee, O my Soule,</hi> that we might <hi>Dwell perpetually together,</hi> as St. <hi>Paul</hi> once perſwaded the holy <hi>Theſſalonians.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Alas, from my <hi>Studie</hi> to my <hi>Church,</hi> from my <hi>Studies</hi> to my <hi>Employments,</hi> in my <hi>Vocations</hi> and <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creations, alone</hi> and in <hi>company,</hi> by <hi>Day,</hi> by <hi>Night,</hi> I have little acquaintance with thoſe holy and heavenly <hi>ſoliloquia &amp; colloquia, ſudden ſhort Ejaculations,</hi> and ſolemne <hi>Invocations,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>perſevering in Prayer,</hi> with <hi>Watching and Faſting,</hi> which were ſo familiar with the bleſſed
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:18407:13"/>Saints, now at reſt from their labours.</p>
                  <p>Here, here is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I indeed am that <hi>Phyſician</hi> who have preſcribed to you, but <hi>can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not heale my ſelfe;</hi> yet that I may yet ſearch out <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>Medicine</hi> to <hi>heale</hi> me in <hi>neglecting Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>Cordiall</hi> to <hi>ſtrengthen you in affe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cting Prayer,</hi> I will have recourſe to <hi>Luke</hi> that <hi>belo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Phyſician,</hi> who preſcribeth unto us a moſt ſove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne <hi>medicine</hi> by the mouth of this <hi>Publicane</hi> in my Text, the <hi>Balme of Gilead,</hi> the <hi>mercy of God, God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Abyſſus Abyſſum invocat,</hi> one <hi>Deep</hi> calleth upon another.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Object</hi> of Prayer, <hi>God,</hi> which is <hi>Infinite,</hi> doth direct my diſcourſe unto the <hi>Neceſsitie</hi> to Pray, which is <hi>Infinite</hi> in like manner: <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi> That <hi>Sin</hi> is <hi>Infinne,</hi> we may conceive, if we conſider the <hi>Denomination, Deſcription, Divi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, Object, Attribute,</hi> and <hi>End</hi> thereof.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>Sinner</hi> in the concrete, hath neere affinitie with the abſtract <hi>Sin,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. The <hi>Etymolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>giſts</hi> pronounce <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as it were <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>ſtray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> or <hi>wandring.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is to <hi>goe the right way,</hi> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> is to <hi>goethe wrong way.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This <hi>Denomination</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> declareth the <hi>Nature</hi> thereof. It maketh men <hi>Cains, Fugitives,</hi> and <hi>Vaga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bonds, Jewes, coeli ac ſoli ſui profugos, Stragglers</hi> which have no home nor houſe to put their heads in. <hi>Sodomites</hi> ſmote with <hi>blindneſſe,</hi> which cannot hit the <hi>Doore to Heaven,</hi> though they ſhould <hi>wearie</hi> themſelves to find it. And <hi>Gentiles, ſitting in dark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, and in the ſhadow of death.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="21" facs="tcp:18407:13"/>Now a ſolicarie perſon <hi>ſtraggling</hi> in the wide <hi>Wil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derneſſe,</hi> among the <hi>Wild Beaſts, in the darke,</hi> and <hi>out of the way,</hi> having neither <hi>Light</hi> nor <hi>Guide,</hi> how would ſuch a poore wight be perplexed? The ſame is the perplexitie of every <hi>Sinner.</hi> He doth <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Wander</hi> amongſt the <hi>Dangers of the World,</hi> indeed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt a <hi>World of Dangers.</hi> It ſtandeth him the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in hand to <hi>pray</hi> that <hi>God</hi> would ſend him a <hi>Guide</hi> in ſo deſperate a pilgrimage, that <hi>God would be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to him a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 Next, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,<hi>Sin is the tranſgreſsion of the Law:</hi> ſo that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>ſin,</hi> maketh a <hi>Sinner</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an <hi>Out law</hi> or <hi>Rebell.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sin</hi> maketh the <hi>Sinner</hi> to be to <hi>God</hi> like <hi>Abſalom</hi> to <hi>David,</hi> he may not dare to <hi>ſee the Kings face.</hi> And like <hi>David, Sheba,</hi> and <hi>Joab,</hi> not his owne <hi>Houſe;</hi> no <hi>Citie,</hi> nor <hi>Sanctuarie,</hi> may ſhield him from the <hi>ſword</hi> of the <hi>Executioner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thinke now how a guiltie <hi>Traitour,</hi> a <hi>Bandido,</hi> a proſcribed and proclaimed <hi>Rebell,</hi> how he fleeth from the <hi>Citie</hi> to the <hi>Countrey,</hi> from the <hi>Townes</hi> to the <hi>Fields,</hi> and from his <hi>Houſe</hi> to ſome <hi>Cave:</hi> if he <hi>remaineth,</hi> he <hi>ſtarveth;</hi> if he <hi>returneth,</hi> he <hi>dieth</hi> with <hi>torment and ignominie.</hi> And in that <hi>breathing time</hi> before <hi>Death he Dieth</hi> a thouſand times, he quaketh at every <hi>ſhadow,</hi> as if it were an <hi>Officer,</hi> and ſtar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth at every <hi>Wind,</hi> as if it were an <hi>Hue</hi> and <hi>Crie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thinke I ſay, on this <hi>amazed wretch,</hi> and withall thinke on the <hi>amazement</hi> of every <hi>wretched Sinner.</hi> No meane <hi>Neceſsitie</hi> to make men <hi>Pray, God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3. <hi>Sin</hi> is <hi>factum, dictum, cogitatum:</hi> either <hi>infuſed</hi>
                     <pb n="22" facs="tcp:18407:14"/>to our <hi>thoughts,</hi> or <hi>effuſed</hi> by our <hi>Words,</hi> or <hi>diffuſed</hi> in our <hi>Deeds.</hi> Our <hi>Hearts</hi> are <hi>Hives;</hi> if <hi>examined,</hi> they containe <hi>examen,</hi> a <hi>Swarme of ſinfull Cogitations:</hi> and withall a <hi>Maſter Bee,</hi> a <hi>Boſome Sinne,</hi> which trumpetteth out, <hi>We have no inheritance in the Son of Jeſſe.</hi> The <hi>Sinnes</hi> on the <hi>lip</hi> of a <hi>Man,</hi> are like the <hi>Sands</hi> on the <hi>lip</hi> of the <hi>Sea,</hi> (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>) infinite and innumerable: yet muſt every one of us give an account for every one of them. And all our <hi>Deeds</hi> alſo, which we have done, either like <hi>Abſolom</hi> in the <hi>ſight of the Sun,</hi> or like <hi>Sarah behind the Doore:</hi> all our actions <hi>Publike</hi> or <hi>Private,</hi> are regiſtred, and muſt be remembred. All theſe <hi>Sinnes</hi> therefore conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, our <hi>Thoughts,</hi> our <hi>Words,</hi> our <hi>Deeds:</hi> it may be concluded, that a <hi>Sinner</hi> ſhould be like <hi>Stentor,</hi> hee ſhould <hi>Have</hi> a <hi>Voice;</hi> or rather like the <hi>Night-Bird,</hi> that he ſhould <hi>Bee</hi> a <hi>Voice:</hi> that he ſhould <hi>Pray,</hi> nay <hi>Cry, God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 Moreover, which is yet more fearefull, all theſe <hi>Sinnes,</hi> all theſe <hi>Thoughts, Words,</hi> and <hi>Deeds,</hi> are <hi>acted, uttered,</hi> and <hi>effected</hi> againſt <hi>God,</hi> an <hi>infinite Majeſtie;</hi> which doth inferre an <hi>infinite Iniquitie:</hi> wee uſe it as a proverb, <hi>Peccatum Minimum, eſt Maximum, quia in Maximum.</hi> The <hi>leaſt Sinne</hi> may be termed an <hi>infinite Sin,</hi> becauſe an <hi>infinite Perſon</hi> is offended by it. But ſome <hi>Sins</hi> we may pronounce <hi>infinite</hi> both <hi>extenſivè,</hi> and <hi>intenſivè;</hi> both in regard of their <hi>Object,</hi> and <hi>Subject</hi> alſo. The <hi>Deſires</hi> of the <hi>Covetous,</hi> are as <hi>Broad</hi> as the <hi>World;</hi> of the <hi>Libidinous</hi> as <hi>Long</hi> as <hi>Eternitie;</hi> of the <hi>Ambitious,</hi> as <hi>High</hi> as <hi>Heaven;</hi> and of the <hi>Malitious,</hi> as <hi>Deep</hi> as <hi>Hell.</hi> The <hi>Heart</hi> of an habituated <hi>Sinner,</hi> is like the <hi>Mare Mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuum;</hi>
                     <pb n="23" facs="tcp:18407:14"/>though whole <hi>Rivers</hi> of <hi>profits, pleaſures, preferments,</hi> and <hi>paſsions</hi> fall into them, they are not one <hi>jot</hi> the <hi>fuller;</hi> but have a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an <hi>inſatiable</hi> appetite to ſwallow more, if either <hi>God,</hi> or the <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill</hi> would exhibit them. Therefore ſuch <hi>infinite ſinnes,</hi> againſt ſo <hi>infinite</hi> a <hi>God,</hi> cannot but cauſe an <hi>infinite neceſsitie,</hi> (if it were poſſible) even to an <hi>in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finite prayer:</hi> Who can now ſilence the <hi>Publicans petition? God be mercifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 Thus we ſee that <hi>ſinne</hi> is an <hi>heavie</hi> caſe: yet one <hi>attribute</hi> doth add to the <hi>weight</hi> thereof. It is ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med a <hi>Burthen.</hi> A <hi>burthen</hi> over the <hi>head,</hi> by holy <hi>David;</hi> and a <hi>burthen</hi> over the <hi>heart,</hi> by Saint <hi>Paul:</hi> The <hi>burthen</hi> of <hi>Dumah,</hi> the <hi>burthen</hi> of <hi>Ammon,</hi> the <hi>burthen</hi> of <hi>Moab:</hi> indeed every <hi>ſin,</hi> to every <hi>ſinner,</hi> is an <hi>heavie burthen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Three ſorts of waies is <hi>ſinne</hi> ſaid to be a <hi>burthen,</hi> to three ſorts of <hi>Perſons.</hi> It is a <hi>burthen</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> to <hi>Man,</hi> and to <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man: Sin</hi> is a <hi>burthen</hi> to <hi>God, onus diſplicentiae &amp; indignationis,</hi> a <hi>burthen</hi> of wrath and <hi>indignation.</hi> To <hi>Man</hi> it is a <hi>burthen, onus reatus &amp; miſeriae,</hi> a <hi>burthen</hi> of guilt and <hi>condemnation.</hi> And unto <hi>God</hi> and <hi>Man,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to <hi>Jeſus Chriſt</hi> our <hi>ſin</hi> is an <hi>heavie burthen, onus ſupplicii &amp; ſatisfactionis,</hi> of <hi>affliction</hi> and <hi>ſatisfaction.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Sinne</hi> being ſuch a <hi>burthen,</hi> let the phraſe put us in mind of thoſe miſerable Malefactours; who our of a ſudden obſtinateneſſe, in their apparent and impenitent wickedneſſe, refuſe to bee tried by the Countrey. Theſe <hi>Caitives,</hi> having a ſharp ſtone under them, and a great plugge over them; Their crying and roaring will tell us that they <hi>feele</hi> a <hi>burthen:</hi> and
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:18407:15"/>yet, as a <hi>Pound weight</hi> is to a <hi>Talent</hi> of <hi>Lead;</hi> ſuch is the <hi>burthen</hi> of their <hi>Bodies,</hi> compared to this <hi>burthen</hi> of our <hi>Soules.</hi> Al<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap> then, what will betide us under ſuch a <hi>Load?</hi> Certainely, <hi>Come unto me all yee that are laden,</hi> ſaith <hi>Chriſt.</hi> And let everie Chriſtian goe unto him, in the voice of this <hi>Publicane,</hi> ſaying: <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6. Finally, the <hi>end</hi> of <hi>ſin</hi> is <hi>paine without end:</hi> a double <hi>paine: Poena ſenſus, &amp; Damni:</hi> both a <hi>paine privative,</hi> and <hi>poſitive.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>privative,</hi> is <hi>(Solemè mundo)</hi> to loſe the <hi>ſight</hi> and <hi>light</hi> of him, who is a thouſand times more <hi>illuſtrious</hi> than the <hi>Sunne,</hi> when the beames thereof are a thouſand times multiplyed: <hi>Sinners ſhalbe caſt By God, and from God into outer Darkneſſe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>Poſitive</hi> is both of <hi>Body</hi> and <hi>Soule</hi> in <hi>Hell;</hi> and both of them ſuffering two ſtrange <hi>Extremities,</hi> and <hi>Contraries; extreame Heat, weeping: and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>treame Cold, gnaſhing of Teeth.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now, if the ſight of the <hi>Rack</hi> (to which <hi>Hell</hi> is like <hi>Nebuchadnezzars Furnace,</hi> compared to the ſtinging of a <hi>Gnat</hi>) will conſtraine <hi>Rebels</hi> to confeſſe and repent their <hi>Rebellion:</hi> certainely the very ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gination of thoſe <hi>infernall, eternall tortures,</hi> will ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tort a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: though we were <hi>Tongue-tied</hi> like the ſonne of <hi>Croeſus,</hi> or <hi>Tongue-leſſe</hi> like the <hi>Eaſterne Confeſſours,</hi> it will compell us to <hi>ſpeake,</hi> and in the <hi>language</hi> of this <hi>Publicane, God be mercifull to mee a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To run over all theſe particulars, with a generall review. Since <hi>ſin</hi> doth make us <hi>ſtraggling Vagabonds, Traiterous Rebels,</hi> in <hi>thought, word,</hi> and <hi>deed,</hi>
                     <pb n="25" facs="tcp:18407:15"/>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> perpetually <hi>fighting</hi> and <hi>ſmiting</hi> againſt <hi>God</hi> Almightie, as a <hi>Body</hi> and unſupportable <hi>Load,</hi> ſinking both bodies and ſoules to the bottome of <hi>Hell:</hi> Therefore wee may <hi>Pray, God bee mercifull to Us Sinners:</hi> Yea, <hi>God bee mercifull</hi> to us all <hi>Miſerable, Miſerable Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now! <hi>What aylest thee, O my Soule,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Appl.</note>
                     <hi>and why art thou So diſquieted within me?</hi> Nay, <hi>What ayleſt thou, O my Soule, that thou art no More diſquieted within mee? Shall Sheba</hi> bee in <hi>Abel,</hi> and ſhall not the inhabitants thereof bee in a confuſion? ſhall <hi>Sin</hi> dwell in thee, <hi>O my ſoule,</hi> and ſhall not thy <hi>thoughts</hi> be confounded? Doſt thou not <hi>feele</hi> theſe <hi>ſinnes? O quid miſerius eſt miſero non miſerante ſeipſum?</hi> What is <hi>more miſerable</hi> than a <hi>ſinner</hi> that is <hi>unſenſible?</hi> Can <hi>Aetna lye on thee,</hi> nay, <hi>fry in thee?</hi> Doſt thou <hi>ſinne,</hi> and yet <hi>feele</hi> neither the <hi>weight</hi> nor <hi>heat</hi> thereof? Do not the <hi>wounds</hi> vexe thee as a thing that is <hi>raw,</hi> which thou haſt ſo oft received from that old <hi>Serpent</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>Satanas,</hi> from that <hi>Amphisbaena ore triſulco,</hi> with a <hi>threeforked ſting?</hi> Art thou not <hi>inveighled by,</hi> if not <hi>intangled with Voluptuouſneſse, Covetouſneſſe, Ambi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiouſneſſe?</hi> Doth not thy hand reach after <hi>Pleaſure?</hi> Did not thy <hi>heart</hi> long after <hi>Profit,</hi> and thy head looke after <hi>Preferment?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1. As farre as thy <hi>Meanes</hi> will permit, doſt thou not tread that path, wherein <hi>Dives</hi> did travell be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore thee: <hi>Rurple</hi> to thy <hi>Backe,</hi> and for thy <hi>Belly, deliciouſneſſe? Exceſſe</hi> both in <hi>food</hi> and <hi>apparell,</hi> both in the <hi>quantitie</hi> and <hi>qualitie</hi> thereof? In <hi>rayment</hi> to rejoice in the <hi>excrements</hi> of dumb dead creatures: In <hi>diet</hi> to delight in that <hi>which periſheth with the Uſing,</hi>
                     <pb n="26" facs="tcp:18407:16"/>nay with the <hi>eating:</hi> A true <hi>Ad quid Perdi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>io h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="3 letters">
                           <desc>•••</desc>
                        </gap>? This might have been ſold, and given to the poore.</hi> Thy <hi>ſuperfluity</hi> might have ſupplied their <hi>neceſsity:</hi> but that thou dareſt not diſpleaſe <hi>Iſis</hi> and <hi>Oſyris,</hi> thoſe grand <hi>Egyptian</hi> (in truth, <hi>Engliſh</hi>) <hi>Idols,</hi> thy <hi>backe</hi> and thy <hi>belly.</hi> Yet all the carnall Indulgences are but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the <hi>pleaſure of ſin for a ſeaſon:</hi> and thou knoweſt not how ſoone the <hi>Worme will come,</hi> &amp; then thy <hi>Goodly gourd will w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ther</hi> in a moment: <hi>Galen, Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>racelſus,</hi> no, <hi>Aeſculapius</hi> himſelfe cannot prevent it.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 Moreover, haſt thou not taken care, not onely what thou ſhalt put <hi>on</hi> thy <hi>back,</hi> &amp; put <hi>in</hi> thy <hi>belly;</hi> but alſo what thou ſhalt put <hi>up</hi> for thy <hi>Poſterity,</hi> that thou mighteſt have <hi>much goods, laid up for many yeeres,</hi> for thy <hi>ſelfe,</hi> and for thy <hi>Children?</hi> For thy <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: for thy <hi>Children,</hi> yea for thy <hi>Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>drens Children</hi> after thee, <hi>to the third and fourth ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration? Vah parvum eſt: To thouſand thouſands</hi> in them thou wouldeſt provide for by a <hi>perpetuated in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taile</hi> of an uninterrupted inheritance, ſo <hi>long</hi> as <hi>the Sun</hi> and <hi>Moon</hi> ſhould <hi>have indured. Spurr'd</hi> on by the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes, if <hi>God</hi> had not put his <hi>bridling Grace</hi> into thy mouth, by this time thy deſires had <hi>galloped</hi> as farre as <hi>Ophir</hi> or <hi>India:</hi> where thou hadſt beene <hi>Bagging</hi> up <hi>Gold</hi> and <hi>Silver,</hi> and <hi>piling</hi> up one <hi>Bag</hi> upon ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, betwixt thee and thy ſalvation, till thou mad'ſt the <hi>Way</hi> to <hi>Heaven</hi> as <hi>narrow</hi> as the <hi>Eye of a Needle:</hi> And verily a <hi>Camel laden with Gold, cannot enter at that Port of the new Hieruſalem.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 Finally, did never the <hi>Prince</hi> of the <hi>Ayre</hi> prompt thee to <hi>build caſtles in the Ayre,</hi> to climbe after that <hi>peremptoriam altitudinem,</hi> that <hi>perillous promotion,</hi>
                     <pb n="27" facs="tcp:18407:16"/>which (not ſeldome) draweth the <hi>ambitious higher, to hurle him downe lower?</hi> But if thou hadſt been ſure to have had ſuch faſt footing and hand-graſping, that thou ſhouldſt never have ſlipped from the <hi>Ladder</hi> of <hi>preferment;</hi> yet ſo much as thou hadſt added to thy <hi>honours,</hi> thou hadſt added to thy <hi>Stewardſhip</hi> alſo: <hi>Et quicquid tihi impenſum eſt, exigetur à te qualiter expenſum eſt,</hi> every <hi>mite,</hi> every <hi>minute,</hi> every <hi>title,</hi> every <hi>tittle</hi> of <hi>dignitie</hi> muſt bee accounted for. Thy <hi>ambition</hi> would have added to thy <hi>accounts</hi> a <hi>thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand for one,</hi> when thou ſhouldſt not have been able to <hi>anſwer one for a thouſand. Good men</hi> do <hi>ſave them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves</hi> and thoſe that <hi>heare</hi> them; <hi>Great men</hi> doe <hi>ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count</hi> for <hi>themſelves,</hi> and for thoſe that <hi>ſerve</hi> them. <hi>Honours</hi> being atchieved, if <hi>Maximus</hi> and <hi>Optimus</hi> could meet in one <hi>man,</hi> yet even <hi>Hee</hi> ſhall bee glad, while he <hi>liveth,</hi> to <hi>uſe</hi> this <hi>prayer</hi> of this <hi>Publican, God be mercifull to me a ſinner:</hi> and when hee <hi>dyeth,</hi> to <hi>pray</hi> as a <hi>great and good man</hi> of this kingdome did <hi>pray dying, Lord forgive me Mine-Other-mens ſins.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now all theſe groundleſſe, boundleſſe, endleſſe, fruitleſſe, unlawfull, unlimited, <hi>ſinnefull</hi> deſires of <hi>pleaſure, profits,</hi> and <hi>preferment,</hi> whither did they, doe they, would they lead thee <hi>O my miſerable ſoule?</hi> to be a <hi>Cain, Homicida,</hi> a <hi>killer</hi> of a <hi>man?</hi> to bee an <hi>Abſalom, parricida,</hi> a <hi>ſupplanter</hi> of thy <hi>father?</hi> to be a <hi>Baanah, regicida,</hi> a <hi>rebell</hi> againſt thy <hi>King?</hi> yea yet more execrable, to be one of thoſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to <hi>fight</hi> againſt thy <hi>God.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For what is all this, but an <hi>averſion</hi> from the <hi>Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor,</hi> and a <hi>converſion</hi> to the <hi>creature?</hi> a trampling on the <hi>inſtruction</hi> of his <hi>precepts,</hi> a ſpurning at the <hi>dire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction</hi>
                     <pb n="28" facs="tcp:18407:17"/>of his <hi>providence?</hi> To <hi>reſiſt Jehova</hi> my <hi>Maker, Jeſus Chriſt</hi> my <hi>Redeemer,</hi> and the <hi>Holy Ghoſt</hi> my <hi>Paraclete,</hi> my <hi>Sanctifier,</hi> and bleſſed <hi>Comforter? Oh ure, ſeca in hoc ſaeculo, ut parcas in futuro:</hi> nay, <hi>Ure, ſeca in hoc ſaeculo, ne peccem de futuro; Lord wound, burne</hi> my <hi>body,</hi> ſo that my <hi>ſoule</hi> may not <hi>ſinne:</hi> lay upon me <hi>obſcurity, infamy, ignominy, poverty, weake<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe, ſickneſſe, death,</hi> any thing but <hi>ſinne</hi> and <hi>hell;</hi> but <hi>ſinne</hi> the <hi>cauſe</hi> of <hi>hell,</hi> and <hi>hell</hi> the <hi>effect</hi> of <hi>ſinne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If now that eternall Judge ſhould injoine me <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>an eternall ſilence</hi> for my <hi>eternall demerit,</hi> I would begge but <hi>one word,</hi> to be left to the liberty of mine utterance, which ſhould never be <hi>out of my mouth, nor out of his Eares.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>PECCAVI, I have ſinned: Peccavi, I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, againſt heaven and againſt thee, and am no more worthy to be called thy ſonne: Peccavi, I have ſinned, Lord I have ſinned, and theſe ſheepe what have they done? Peccavi, I have ſinned,</hi> but <hi>Propitius peccatori, God be mercifull to me The ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>By this ſecond point I have ſhewed <hi>ſinne</hi> to bee a <hi>burden,</hi> indeed <hi>Such a burden as neither wee nor our Forefathers were ever able to beare.</hi> Howbeit, hither<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to I have onely <hi>touched that Burden with my little fin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger.</hi> In the third point, following, I will ſet my <hi>ſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der</hi> to it, and then my <hi>heart</hi> ſhall tell you how I <hi>feele</hi> the <hi>weight</hi> of it.</p>
                  <p>Wee ſee thus, that <hi>ſinne</hi> is a <hi>burden,</hi> yet ordinary <hi>ſinners feele</hi> it not. For (where <hi>ſinne</hi> is growne into a <hi>cuſtome</hi>) <hi>Mulus mulum ſcabit,</hi> the <hi>ſinner reacheth a cuſhion to the divell,</hi> and (by a reciprocall courteſie) the <hi>divell reacheth a cuſhion to the ſinner.</hi> The <hi>ſinner</hi>
                     <pb n="29" facs="tcp:18407:17"/>biddeth the <hi>divell</hi> take his eaſe, and ſpare his <hi>tempta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion;</hi> the <hi>divell</hi> biddeth the <hi>ſinner</hi> take his eaſe, and feare no <hi>damnation:</hi> for <hi>ſinne</hi> muſt bee freely and ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>carely committed.</p>
                  <p>Your <hi>Urinatores,</hi> expert <hi>Swimmers,</hi> being <hi>under water,</hi> feele not the <hi>weight</hi> of a <hi>full fraighted ſhip,</hi> of a thouſand runnes, riding perpendicularly over the ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry head of them: But ſo ſoon as they put their heads <hi>above water,</hi> the leaſt touch of the leaſt part of the ſhip will ſtemme them, and tumble them headlong into the bottome of the Ocean. So whileſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble <hi>men ſwimme</hi> in the cuſtome of any pleaſing or profitable <hi>ſinne,</hi> they are <hi>inſenſible</hi> of the <hi>burden</hi> of a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny crime, though it be as <hi>bigge</hi> as a <hi>Carrick,</hi> or as one of thoſe vaſte <hi>Sea-carts</hi> at <hi>Lepanto:</hi> But ſo ſoone as they ſhall begin but to <hi>lift up their heads</hi> out of the <hi>Ocean</hi> of their habituall offences, but to looke to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards heaven, they will be ready to <hi>ſinke with feare to be drowned in deſpaire,</hi> at the very apprehenſion thereof.</p>
                  <p>This applicative phraſe, <hi>Mihi peccatori,</hi> to <hi>Me a ſinner,</hi> will inſtruct us to ponder this point. Here I propoſe <hi>My ſelfe Your looking-glaſſe.</hi> The ſight of my frailties may reflect to you your infirmities, either the very ſame or ſome very like, <hi>ſhadowed</hi> by this example. <hi>Irrideant me arrogantes, ego tamen confite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bor tibi dedecora mea, in laudem tuam:</hi> although <hi>confeſsion</hi> to God produce <hi>deriſion</hi> from man, yet will I ſay, <hi>Mihi peccatori, to Mee the ſinner;</hi> and let mee have the <hi>ſhame,</hi> God the <hi>glory,</hi> and you an <hi>Item</hi> for your <hi>converſation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>To looke backe to the very <hi>Aest</hi> of my <hi>Nativity,</hi>
                     <pb n="31" facs="tcp:18407:18"/>and lower alſo: <hi>I was a ſinner before I was,</hi> I was borne in <hi>ſinne,</hi> and my mother <hi>conceived</hi> mee in ini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quity.</p>
                  <p>In my ſwadling <hi>clouts,</hi> thoſe <hi>cradle-cryings,</hi> and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>articulate complainings, were the <hi>actuall froth</hi> pum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ped from the dregges of my <hi>originall pollution.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Afterwards, being but <hi>Infans, Mendaciis Paedago<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gum fallebam, &amp; pomorum furta faciebam:</hi> being not able to <hi>ſpeake plainely,</hi> nor to <hi>goe ſtrongly,</hi> yet then I had a <hi>tongue</hi> to tell a <hi>lye</hi> for feare of the <hi>rod,</hi> and an <hi>hand</hi> to plucke other mens <hi>fruit,</hi> for the <hi>love</hi> of my <hi>palate.</hi> Theſe little <hi>ſinnes</hi> ſhewed, that being but a <hi>little childe,</hi> I had too <hi>little regard</hi> (or knowledge at the leaſt) of our <hi>great God,</hi> and his holy commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments.</p>
                  <p>My carefull parents putting me to <hi>Schoole,</hi> how did <hi>I play away that price leſſe Treaſure, my Time,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, how often did my ſports add <hi>feathers</hi> to thoſe nim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble houres? and afterwards, how faine would I have <hi>clipped the wings of thoſe birds,</hi> which (God know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth) were then <hi>flowne away</hi> too farre from being <hi>caught againe?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>At the <hi>Univerſity,</hi> I had no <hi>lips</hi> to kiſſe thoſe <hi>hands</hi> which clothed and fed mee there. I did not onely want a <hi>purſe,</hi> but (which is worſe) an <hi>heart</hi> alſo to be ſufficiently <hi>thankfull</hi> to thoſe inſtruments (now with God) which <hi>gave me that bleſſed education.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Being choſen <hi>Fellow</hi> in our <hi>Colledge,</hi> and taking <hi>Pupils,</hi> I gave them <hi>too much libertie,</hi> and tooke my ſelfe <hi>too little paines:</hi> I was an <hi>Heli,</hi> when I ſhould have been a <hi>Gamaliel;</hi> I conſidered not that <hi>Univerſity Tutors</hi> ſhould bee like the <hi>Latine Tutores, Tuitores,
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:18407:18"/>Defenders</hi> of younglings againſt <hi>barbariſmes</hi> in their <hi>language,</hi> and <hi>barbarouſneſſe</hi> in their <hi>lives:</hi> I conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red not that the inde fatigable induſtry of vigilant, di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent <hi>Tutors,</hi> ſhould make every <hi>Colledge</hi> both like <hi>Athe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> which <hi>taught men to know well,</hi> and like <hi>La<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cedaemon,</hi> which <hi>taught men to doe well.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>When the <hi>Univerſity</hi> had fitted mee for the <hi>Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtry.</hi> I entred that <hi>Calling</hi> with <hi>joy</hi> and <hi>hope,</hi> faſtning my expectation on the <hi>Honos,</hi> rather than the <hi>Onus;</hi> on the <hi>honour</hi> of the <hi>Miniſters,</hi> rather than the <hi>labour</hi> in the <hi>Miniſtrie:</hi> but ſince I have found that the beſt man which breathed ſince the Apoſtles, did <hi>weepe</hi> when hee entred into <hi>Orders,</hi> as <hi>truely ſenſible of the truly inſupportable burden.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In that <hi>Calling,</hi> too long, too oft did I too much <hi>repine atomy maintenance, that I fed other mens ſoules plentifully, but they fed my body too ſparingly: that a little wages was an unjuſt proportion to my great la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour:</hi> A foule fault, perhaps <hi>overvalewing the one,</hi> and <hi>undervaleming the other;</hi> but without peradven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture forgetting the worke that <hi>God will doe,</hi> that hee will <hi>reward his labourers;</hi> and the work which Gods <hi>children ſhould doe, If they cannot have meanes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their mindes, then to frame their mindes accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to their meanes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But of all, in the diſcharge, and for the diſcharge of my Calling, when, becauſe of my induſtrious, inge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuous, and impartiall labours, I felt my ſelfe <hi>whipped on both ſides;</hi> by the <hi>Rapiſts</hi> with <hi>ſcourges,</hi> and by o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers (who profeſſe themſelves <hi>Profeſſours</hi>) with <hi>ſcorpions: Etiam tu fili!</hi> even <hi>Iſraelites</hi> to <hi>ſmite</hi> inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent <hi>Jeremy</hi> with the <hi>tongue!</hi> I want a <hi>tongue</hi> to tell
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:18407:19"/>you what a <hi>ſwarme</hi> of diſcontents did <hi>ſting</hi> my ſoule with impatient cogitations. O poore puſillanimity! and farre from the <hi>Heroicall</hi> patience of thoſe Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thies, <hi>who being whipped for ſpeaking in the name of Jeſus, departed from the Councell Rejoicing that they were counted worthy to ſuffer ſhame for his Name.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Beſides my <hi>publike,</hi> in my <hi>private Calling</hi> alſo, in my poore cottage, in my <hi>ſmall Family,</hi> what great <hi>rivers</hi> of <hi>omiſsions</hi> have paſſed unſeene by the <hi>eye</hi> of the poore man that is the <hi>Head</hi> thereof? At home in defect, nothing ſo <hi>carefull</hi> for the <hi>ſoules,</hi> as every <hi>Mamoniſt</hi> is for the <hi>bodies</hi> of their <hi>ſervants,</hi> of their <hi>children</hi> eſpecially: abroad in exceſſe, uſing my friends kindneſſe, and Gods creatures <hi>too plentifully,</hi> when as it may be others of Gods children, <hi>more du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifull than my ſelfe,</hi> wanted that ſurpluſage for their <hi>extreme neceſsity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay my <hi>ſplendid a peccata,</hi> my <hi>beſt actions,</hi> in my <hi>preaching</hi> and <hi>hearing,</hi> my <hi>praying</hi> and <hi>faſting,</hi> my <hi>giving</hi> and <hi>forgiving,</hi> yea in the <hi>compoſing</hi> of this ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry <hi>Sermon,</hi> I have beene ſenſible of my <hi>affections, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections, imperfections,</hi> yea <hi>interfections,</hi> that I need a <hi>Surſum corda,</hi> one to cry continually, <hi>Lift up thy heart</hi> in thy devotions.</p>
                  <p>And I profeſſe it, <hi>Verebor omnia opera mea,</hi> I am a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of <hi>All my actions,</hi> that either <hi>ſuperbia</hi> or <hi>deſidia,</hi> either <hi>pride of</hi> them, or <hi>ſloath in</hi> them, will bee a <hi>worme</hi> to make them <hi>rotten</hi> at the very <hi>core.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My life paſt I have ſomewhat ſpent in <hi>reading bookes;</hi> if the remnant of my mortality I ſhould em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ploy onely in <hi>writing books,</hi> I ought to compoſe them onely of two kindes, after the preſident of that great
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:18407:19"/>man of God, onely <hi>Confeſsions</hi> and <hi>Retractations;</hi> onely to <hi>repent</hi> all my <hi>doings,</hi> and to <hi>recant</hi> all my <hi>ſayings;</hi> I meane the infinite infirmities which doe twinne in the very birth of my beſt endeavours. <hi>Me me, adſum qui feci, I have ſinned, Lord I have ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned, but theſe people what have they done?</hi> What you have done, your ſelves doe know, and your God doth know; therefore to your <hi>repentance,</hi> and to his <hi>indulgence</hi> I remit it.</p>
                  <p>But for my ſelfe, O that I had the <hi>Heart</hi> of this <hi>Publican,</hi> to pronounce the <hi>words</hi> of this <hi>Publican, Deus propitius eſto mihi peccatori, God bee mercifull to Mee a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yet you will ſay,<note place="margin">Appl.</note> but which is the <hi>greateſt ſinne</hi> in the catalogue of thy perſonall tranſgreſſions? I ſay, my <hi>firſt</hi> and <hi>greateſt ſinne</hi> is my <hi>ſinne</hi> of <hi>thought;</hi> the <hi>ſecond is like unto this,</hi> concerning my <hi>Calling:</hi> and upon theſe two hang all my offences.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Gods Grace</hi> (bleſſed be my <hi>God</hi> for his <hi>Grace</hi>) <hi>hath preſerved me from preſumptuous ſinnes, that they have not got the dominion over mee: Qui facit peccatum ex diabolo eſt. God Grace</hi> hath prevented mee from <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> thoſe notorious <hi>ſinnes,</hi> which make a man a ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vant to the <hi>divell.</hi> Howbeit there is another kinde of <hi>ſinne,</hi> which ſome call <hi>Limen Inferni,</hi> the very <hi>brink of Hell;</hi> this is the <hi>ſinne</hi> of <hi>thought.</hi> Now this <hi>ſinne of thought I thinke</hi> (nay I know) to be <hi>My ſinne.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Whereas every Chriſtian ſhould bee, and many a Chriſtian is, <hi>Nun quam minus ſolus quam quum ſolus,</hi> when they are <hi>moſt ſolitary,</hi> then are they <hi>beſt imploy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed,</hi> in <hi>holy invocations,</hi> and <hi>heavenly contemplations;</hi> for my <hi>ſelfe,</hi> I finde my private <hi>cogitations</hi> to bee <hi>aut
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:18407:20"/>malae, aut otioſae: im<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> mulae quia otioſae:</hi> to bee either <hi>Evill,</hi> or <hi>Idle:</hi> indeed to be <hi>Evill</hi> becauſe <hi>Idle.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>My idle evill <hi>Thoughts</hi> are like <hi>Camomile, the more they grow, the more I trample on them;</hi> and yet <hi>the more I trample on them, the more they grow.</hi> Like that <hi>Serpent Hydra,</hi> when I <hi>out off one Head of an evill Cogitation,</hi> inſtantly <hi>two</hi> other ſprowt up, nay, ſprowt out in the place of it. Like the <hi>Second Beaſt</hi> in the thirteenth of the <hi>Revelations,</hi> my <hi>Thoughts a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſe our of the earth, Earthly cogitations.</hi> And like the <hi>Firſt Beaſt</hi> in the ſame Chapter, although I give a <hi>Deadly wound</hi> to the <hi>Head</hi> of one of thoſe <hi>Beaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Thoughts,</hi> yet it will not <hi>Die</hi> notwithſtanding.</p>
                  <p>My <hi>Thoughts,</hi> like <hi>Davus</hi> in the <hi>Comedie,</hi> like <hi>Doeg</hi> in <hi>Souls Familie,</hi> and like the <hi>Materia Prim<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi> in <hi>Philoſophie, ſemper machinantur male fierum,</hi> they alwaies make ſome <hi>Miſ-rules,</hi> and meditate ſome <hi>Miſchiefe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Than <hi>Thought</hi> can hardly be thought a more <hi>Ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſsitating</hi> motive to perpetuate the <hi>Prayer</hi> of this poore <hi>Publicane</hi> in my Text, <hi>God be mercifull to Me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now I ſhew you that <hi>Saul</hi> who would <hi>Hide himſelfe,</hi> that <hi>Sin</hi> which is <hi>Higher than all my reſt, by the ſhoulders upward,</hi> my <hi>Defects</hi> in my <hi>Calling,</hi> the <hi>Miniſterie,</hi> ſo many in number, ſo mighty in na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture.</p>
                  <p>The <hi>Miniſterie.</hi> For the <hi>Matter</hi> thereof, we are converſant about the <hi>Word of God,</hi> both <hi>audible and viſible,</hi> both the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> and the heavenly <hi>Sacraments.</hi> For the <hi>Forme,</hi> we doe it <hi>authoritative,</hi>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:18407:20"/>we are <hi>Diſpencers</hi> of them. Our <hi>Efficient inſtrumen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall</hi> is the <hi>Church of God,</hi> and the <hi>Efficient principall</hi> is <hi>God Himſelfe, who did Thruſt me forth to be a la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bourer in his Harveſt,</hi> when as ſome of my moſt foo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſh friends, and ſome of my more fooliſh fancies, did whiſper me in the eare to divert me to ſome more <hi>profitable Vocation.</hi> And the <hi>end</hi> is, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>Great Reward,</hi> yea a <hi>greater</hi> than that, to <hi>ſave Soules;</hi> nay, the <hi>greateſt of all,</hi> to be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to <hi>Doe ſervice unto God,</hi> whether it be by being the <hi>ſavour of Life to the children of Obedience,</hi> or the <hi>ſavour of Death in thoſe that Periſh.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>For the <hi>Effect.</hi> At theſe <hi>extraordinary</hi> times, we hope, when we <hi>caſt our Bread upon the Waters,</hi> and deliver our <hi>Sermons</hi> amongſt a <hi>Multitude</hi> of <hi>People,</hi> who are like <hi>many Waters,</hi> that through Gods <hi>extra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinarie</hi> grace, there may be <hi>one ſoule hungring and thirſting after Righteouſneſſe,</hi> which will vouchſafe to take <hi>one morſell</hi> of that we ſet before them. If not, we hope for an <hi>ordinarie</hi> bleſſing among the <hi>Flockes</hi> over which <hi>the Holy Ghoſt hath made us Overſeers.</hi> If not ſo, but that in this time of <hi>Plentie</hi> we <hi>bring</hi> our <hi>Corn</hi> into the <hi>Market,</hi> but find it <hi>ſlighted</hi> both by <hi>Forreiners</hi> and <hi>Inhabitants,</hi> then <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Poore</hi> deſpiſed <hi>Husbandmen,</hi> we will carry it home to <hi>feed</hi> our owne <hi>Families.</hi> Nay, if <hi>Pride, Idleneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe of Bread</hi> ſhould reigne under our owne roofes, though a <hi>Miniſter</hi> cannot have <hi>Curam animarum,</hi> yet if he can have but <hi>Curam Animae:</hi> if through <hi>my Fooliſhneſſe of Preaching</hi> I have <hi>ſaved but one Soule,</hi> but mine <hi>Owne Soule:</hi> this certainly is a precious <hi>Effect</hi> of a moſt priceleſſe <hi>Vocation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="36" facs="tcp:18407:21"/>Now, that in <hi>ſuch a Calling</hi> there ſhould be any <hi>ſuch Defect,</hi> of <hi>Conſcience,</hi> not to be inſtant (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,) <hi>in ſeaſon, out of ſeaſon:</hi> of <hi>Commoditie,</hi> not to conceive this <hi>Godlineſſe</hi> to <hi>be great gaine:</hi> of <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent,</hi> ſince <hi>God</hi> hath ſaid it, he <hi>will never Forſake us:</hi> or of <hi>Courage, God is on our ſide, we need not care what Man can doe againſt us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That we ſhould but from a corner of our eye caſt but a <hi>glaunce</hi> upon the <hi>Riches</hi> of the <hi>Citie,</hi> the <hi>Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours</hi> of the <hi>Court,</hi> the <hi>Reputation</hi> of the <hi>Lawyers, Common</hi> or <hi>Civill,</hi> the <hi>Eſteeme</hi> of the <hi>Phyſicians,</hi> or the <hi>Quiet</hi> of the <hi>Gentrie.</hi> So that we ſhould not commend this while we live, as the only <hi>Treaſure to our Soules;</hi> and when we die, as the principall <hi>Lega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie, Portion, and Inheritance to our Sons.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That we ſhould not <hi>Delight</hi> to diſcharge this bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed <hi>Function with all our Heart, with all our Soule, with all our Mind, and with all our Strength;</hi> but that we ſhould leave <hi>any crannie in our Hearts</hi> either for <hi>Diſcontent</hi> at <hi>home,</hi> or for <hi>Envie abroad;</hi> either for <hi>Wiſhes</hi> of <hi>Additions to our Temporalls,</hi> or for <hi>Feare</hi> of <hi>Oppoſition to our Eccleſiaſticalls:</hi> that we ſhould not be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> &amp; <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, alwayes <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Content,</hi> and prompt, and provided to publiſh Gods truth by our preaching, pens, and proteſtation.</p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I confeſſe and profeſſe it before <hi>God, Men,</hi> and <hi>Angels;</hi> Here, <hi>This</hi> is <hi>My Sin,</hi> and herein <hi>God be mercifull to Me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="4"/> Thus theſe three words miniſter to our notice two ſtrange <hi>Extremes.</hi> more diſtant than the <hi>Antipo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des,</hi> or than the <hi>Xenith</hi> and the <hi>Nadir,</hi> than the moſt ſevered <hi>Paris</hi> of the <hi>Earth,</hi> or the two more con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trarie
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:18407:21"/>
                     <hi>Points</hi> of <hi>Heaven, God,</hi> and <hi>ſinfull Man.</hi> And the word remaining <hi>(Mercie)</hi> is the <hi>Communis ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minus,</hi> is the <hi>Knot</hi> where theſe two termes doe meet.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercy</hi> is that miraculous <hi>Medium</hi> which doth alter the <hi>Colour,</hi> yea, and the <hi>Nature</hi> of the <hi>Viſible Object. Sinfull man</hi> in himſelfe is <hi>Red,</hi> red as <hi>Skarlet;</hi> but <hi>God,</hi> looking through <hi>Mercie,</hi> apprehendeth him to be <hi>White,</hi> white as the <hi>Snow in Salmon. God</hi> in regard of <hi>Sinfull</hi> man is a <hi>Judge</hi> and <hi>Revenger;</hi> but through <hi>Mercie,</hi> even <hi>ſinfull</hi> man looketh upon him as up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on a <hi>Saviour,</hi> a <hi>Redeemer,</hi> yea, as upon an <hi>indulgent Father.</hi> This <hi>Collyrium</hi> cleared the dull ſight of this devour <hi>Publican.</hi> Being himſelfe, <hi>he did not ſo much as lift up his eyes to heaven;</hi> but through this <hi>Medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> he <hi>durſt looke God in the very face,</hi> ſaying, <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Mercifull</hi> to a <hi>Sinner! Sin</hi> is the <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> of the <hi>Soule,</hi> and <hi>Mercie</hi> is the <hi>Medicine</hi> thereof. As a <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicine,</hi> ſo <hi>Mercie</hi> is <hi>Sanativa, Praeſervativa, &amp; Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motiva:</hi> it is a <hi>Purge to Cure Sickneſſe,</hi> a <hi>Cordiall to Strengthen Weakneſſe,</hi> and an <hi>Antidote to Anticipate Relapſes.</hi> There is a <hi>Pardoning,</hi> a <hi>Preſerving,</hi> and a <hi>Preventing Mercy:</hi> a <hi>Mercy</hi> pardoning our ſinnes <hi>Paſt,</hi> preſerving us againſt ſinne <hi>Preſent,</hi> and preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting us from ſinne to <hi>Come.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 The firſt the <hi>Woman</hi> had taken <gap reason="foreign">
                           <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                        </gap> in the act of <hi>Uncleanneſſe: I condemne thee not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> goe, ſin no more.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 The ſecond God gave to <hi>Paul; My Grace is ſufficient for thee,</hi> and, <hi>my ſtrength is made perfect in thy weakneſſe.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>
                        <pb n="38" facs="tcp:18407:22"/>3. And the third, rejoyced the <hi>Heart</hi> of holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid: Bleſſed bee God, and bleſſed be thy advice, and bleſſed be thou which haſt kept me this day from aven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ging my ſelfe with my owne hand.</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>And this <hi>Publican</hi> deſired, needed, hoped all theſe three: <hi>Mercie</hi> to <hi>pardon</hi> him for the time <hi>paſt,</hi> to <hi>preſerve</hi> him for the time <hi>preſent,</hi> and to <hi>pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> him for the time to <hi>come.</hi> This threefold <hi>mercy,</hi> gave this <hi>prayer</hi> to the <hi>ſoule</hi> of the <hi>Publican;</hi> and the <hi>ſoule</hi> to this <hi>prayer</hi> of the <hi>Publican.</hi> Hence hee praied, <hi>God be mercifull to me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thoſe are <hi>lame</hi> Chriſtians, who <hi>tread</hi> not in the <hi>foot-ſteps</hi> of this <hi>Publican:</hi> Parallel the particulars.</p>
                  <p>Firſt look <hi>back-ward;</hi> Remember the miſpending of our <hi>time, meanes,</hi> and <hi>callings.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Our <hi>time</hi> was all from <hi>God.</hi> But to God what <hi>time</hi> have we returned? the <hi>ſeventh?</hi> the <hi>ſeventeenth?</hi> yea or the <hi>ſeventieth?</hi> What one here dare ſay, that in his <hi>whole life</hi> hee hath given but <hi>One whole imire yeere</hi> unto <hi>Gods ſervice?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Our <hi>meanes. God</hi> i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> the <hi>Fountaine</hi> iſſuing forth thoſe alſo. But returne we any <hi>Rivers,</hi> for the <hi>Oceans</hi> we have received? the <hi>tenth?</hi> nay the <hi>tenth</hi> of the <hi>tenth?</hi> How much, how much have we imploied on our <hi>ſelves?</hi> How little, how very little have wee ſet apart for our <hi>God?</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 Our <hi>Callings.</hi> Have we uſed them as <hi>Gods talents?</hi> to Gods <hi>glory?</hi> Have wee not uſed them as <hi>Rakes</hi> to draw <hi>riches</hi> to us? or as <hi>Stirrups</hi> to raiſe us to <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>motion?</hi> What then would become of us, if it were not for Gods <hi>pardoning mercy:</hi> if God would not be <hi>mercifull to us</hi> miſerable <hi>Sinners?</hi>
                     </item>
                  </list>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="39" facs="tcp:18407:22"/>Next let us looke <hi>inward,</hi> indeed <hi>downward,</hi> and bluſh at the infinite frailties of our beſt abilities.</p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Our <hi>Faith</hi> is <hi>ſicut Luna, nunquam Una:</hi> in many <hi>Warnes, Cloudings,</hi> and <hi>Eclipſes.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 Our <hi>Hope</hi> is like an <hi>anchor</hi> of <hi>reed,</hi> apt to bee torne up with every triviall temptation.</item>
                     <item>3 And our <hi>Charitie</hi> like the <hi>Cypreſſe</hi> tree, very <hi>tall,</hi> but bearing little <hi>fruit.</hi> Our <hi>ſoules</hi> have need of a <hi>Cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diall,</hi> of a <hi>preſerving mercy:</hi> That God would bee <hi>Mercifull to us ſinners,</hi> by his <hi>ſtrengthning Grace,</hi> and gracious aſſiſtance.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Finally, let us looke <hi>forward,</hi> yea <hi>backeward,</hi> yea <hi>inward</hi> alſo: let all men, at all times, looke all waies. And if we can, let us turne our eye from ſome <hi>preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mercie:</hi> which is the <hi>mercy of mercies.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <list>
                     <item>1 Full often ſhall wee, have wee, doe we <hi>ſwell</hi> with <hi>proſperitie;</hi> but that Gods <hi>mercy</hi> doth ſend us ſome moderate <hi>adverſitie,</hi> to <hi>prick that windie bladder,</hi> and to <hi>prevent</hi> us from <hi>ſecurity.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>2 As often are wee <hi>dejected</hi> with <hi>adverſitie;</hi> but then Gods <hi>mercie</hi> doth raiſe us with ſome <hi>proſperitie,</hi> to <hi>prevent</hi> as from impatience and <hi>blaſphemie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>3 <hi>Nature</hi> maketh us prone to <hi>ſuperſtition;</hi> but Gods <hi>mercie</hi> hath given us birth in a bleſſed Land (which <hi>is the kingdome of the Goſpell, and hath the Goſpell of the kingdome</hi>) to <hi>prevent</hi> us from <hi>Idolatrie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>4 <hi>Company</hi> allureth us many times, to beſtow <hi>Gods Day</hi> on their <hi>Societie;</hi> but Gods <hi>mercy,</hi> in giving us <hi>cuſtomarie Sabbath Sermons,</hi> doth draw us to Church for ſhame, and <hi>preventeth</hi> us from that too frequent, and publike profane <hi>impietie.</hi>
                     </item>
                     <item>5 Our people are apt enough to act the part of thoſe <hi>Boyes</hi> of <hi>Jericho,</hi> to have a <hi>bald-head,</hi> ſome
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:18407:23"/>ſcornefull <hi>nick-name,</hi> for the <hi>Prophets</hi> of the Lord: but the <hi>mercie</hi> of the <hi>Lord</hi> hath a little <hi>prevented</hi> them, and a little touched their hearts (as he did the heart of <hi>Lidia</hi>) that they doe in ſome ſort eſteeme them to be the <hi>Horſemen of Iſrael,</hi> and the <hi>Chariots</hi> of the ſame.</item>
                  </list>
                  <p>Have we not beene <hi>angry</hi> too often, too ſuddenly, too much? And this is a prologue to <hi>Murder.</hi> But bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed be that <hi>mercie,</hi> which as often <hi>prevented us. Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moderate diet, fantaſticall faſhions,</hi> too <hi>looſe ſpeeches,</hi> if Gods <hi>mercie prevented</hi> not, who dare ſay that they might not lead us to <hi>uncleanneſſe?</hi> Yee know our de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſires, cares, and indeavours to <hi>thrive our ſelves,</hi> and to <hi>raiſe</hi> our <hi>Poſterity:</hi> if we <hi>doe</hi> this <hi>without covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe,</hi> admire Gods <hi>preventing mercy,</hi> indeed beyond admiration. <hi>Corrupt</hi> nature hath framed us with <hi>broad eares, and wide mouths,</hi> with a ſtrange apt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe to <hi>ſpeake</hi> of the <hi>abſent,</hi> more than becommeth the <hi>innocent.</hi> Have we learned the leſſon of holy <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi> in any meaſure? ſo <hi>to take heed to our waies, that we offend not with our tongue?</hi> Reverence Gods <hi>preven<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting mercie,</hi> as our onely inſtructor in that ſingular vertue. And that our <hi>Boſome Aetn<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>,</hi> our <hi>continuall concupiſcence,</hi> if we can <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>quench thoſe deſires</hi> in any <hi>degree,</hi> that they <hi>Flame not forth into actuall Ambition, Covetouſneſſe,</hi> and <hi>Voluptuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe;</hi> the voice of our <hi>Praiſe</hi> and <hi>Prayer,</hi> muſt aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cribe all this to Gods <hi>preventing mercie,</hi> in the phraſe of this <hi>Publican: God is,</hi> ever hath beene, and ever may hee bee a <hi>God mercifull</hi> to us <hi>miſerable Sinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The conſideration of Gods <hi>mercy</hi> in generall, but of his <hi>preventing mercie</hi> in eſpeciall, may incline our
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:18407:23"/>hearts, to treaſure up this <hi>precious Praier,</hi> for our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>petuall practice. It were well, if like the <hi>Iſraelites,</hi> wee could write it as a <hi>ſelect Scripture,</hi> in our <hi>Phy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lacteries</hi> and verges of our garments. It were well, if like that <hi>Emperour</hi> we could paint it as a <hi>choyce ſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tence,</hi> in our windowes and <hi>Walles</hi> of our houſes. It were well, if like that <hi>Father</hi> wee could carry it as an <hi>Obvious Poeſie,</hi> on our <hi>Tables</hi> and <hi>Trenchers.</hi> All this were well: but it were farre better, if with the bleſſed <hi>Virgin,</hi> we could <hi>Lay it up in our Hearts,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Written</hi> not with <hi>ink,</hi> but with the <hi>Spirit</hi> of the <hi>living God;</hi> not in the <hi>tables</hi> of <hi>ſtone,</hi> but in the <hi>fleſhly tables</hi> of the <hi>Heart.</hi> That <hi>Nulla dies ſine linea,</hi> that <hi>every houre we may utter this Prayer; God be mercifull to Me a Sinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>God be mercifull</hi> to us! Surely God <hi>Hath Been,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Appl.</note> and <hi>Is Mercifull</hi> unto us <hi>alreadie.</hi> That we are here, now met together at this time, in this place, it is the <hi>Lords mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>It is <hi>Gods mercy,</hi> that the ſubſtance of this Text, which is writ in this verſe, was not written upon <hi>all our Houſes,</hi> as it was upon ſome of our poore <hi>Neighbours: LORD HAVE MERCIE UPON US.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>What am I, that I did not fall amongſt thoſe <hi>eight hundred</hi> which died this yeere in my owne poore Pariſh? and what are you, that you ſervive thoſe <hi>eight and twentie thouſands</hi> which were buried with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the circuit of your famous <hi>Citie?</hi> That our <hi>eight hundreds</hi> aroſe not to <hi>eight thouſands:</hi> and that your <hi>eight and twenty thouſands</hi> did not multiply to <hi>eight<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcore Thouſands:</hi> and that we were made but <hi>Cyphers</hi>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:18407:24"/>among thoſe numbers appointed to die: that the <hi>Lord ſwep us not All away</hi> with that <hi>beſome</hi> of his <hi>indignation,</hi> the <hi>Plague:</hi> that they were <hi>ſcopae diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſolutae,</hi> that we eſcaped, this was <hi>Gods mercie,</hi> Gods <hi>great mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That the <hi>Tower</hi> of <hi>Siloam</hi> fell upon <hi>eighteen,</hi> and upon <hi>no more</hi> of the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>Jeruſalem:</hi> it was <hi>Gods mercy</hi> unto them. That the <hi>Plague</hi> hath deſtroi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed <hi>ſo many</hi> of the <hi>Inhabitants</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> but <hi>no more:</hi> this is <hi>Gods mercie unto us.</hi> Yea, <hi>Gods mercy</hi> was to us, as <hi>preferment</hi> ſhould be to men of merit, <hi>Fugientem ſequitur,</hi> it did follow us when we did <hi>flee</hi> from it. <hi>Stulti Stoici cum miſericordiam quaſi vitium devita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bant:</hi> when the <hi>fooliſh people</hi> did <hi>forſake their owne mercies,</hi> and did pluck down <hi>Lord have mercy upon us,</hi> from their Doores; even then God did write o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver their Heads; <hi>Miſerebor cujus miſerebor, I will have mercy, on whom I will have mercy:</hi> and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve many from the <hi>Plague. Gods mercy, Gods mira<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous mercie.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Nay, whileſt our provoked <hi>Judge</hi> did deſtroy us with the <hi>plague,</hi> even then alſo hee ſhewed <hi>mercy</hi> in his <hi>Judgements.</hi> That in our pariſh, and in your Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, there <hi>dyed ſo many,</hi> it was <hi>too many,</hi> had not God deſigned it to bee ſo; but that there <hi>dyed no more,</hi> this was <hi>citra condignum, leſſe</hi> than wee did <hi>deſerve, Gods mercy:</hi> and that I and you were <hi>Titiones ab in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cendio, Brands ſnatched out of that fire,</hi> that <hi>wee dyed not of the plague,</hi> this was <hi>ſupra condignum,</hi> more than we <hi>did deſerve, Gods gracious mercie.</hi> Carnall conſultations, it may be, may conclude, that ſo many <hi>children died of the plague,</hi> this was a <hi>cruell affliction:</hi>
                     <pb n="43" facs="tcp:18407:24"/>But I ſay, <hi>Deus fecit nihil inaniter, nihil inhumaniter,</hi> that theſe <hi>judgements</hi> were not without <hi>wiſdome,</hi> they were not <hi>without mercies.</hi> That <hi>Infants</hi> were deſtroyed, carnall men may call it <hi>cruelty,</hi> but it was <hi>crudelitas parcens,</hi> in verity very <hi>mercy.</hi> Although they did <hi>not know their right hand from their left,</hi> yet <hi>God</hi> (it may be) did <hi>know</hi> that they would <hi>patrizare, imitate</hi> the <hi>ſiniſter dealings</hi> of their naughty <hi>Parents,</hi> and therefore to withhold them from a ſinfull <hi>life</hi> by a timely <hi>death;</hi> this was <hi>Gods mercy:</hi> and wee who have <hi>eſcaped the plague,</hi> if we continue in our ſinnes, it is <hi>miſericordia puniens,</hi> to incurre <hi>greater judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments,</hi> if we be not prevented by <hi>Gods mercy.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But now, if the Lord would be pleaſed to ſay a <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſummatum eſt to our Croſſe,</hi> to ſay of the <hi>plague, It is fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed,</hi> that our inhabitants might ſafely and ſecurely <hi>return to their houſes, follow their trades, and frequent their Churches, in the feare of God, without feare of one another:</hi> that we might no more be <hi>deſtroyed by the plague, devoured by poverty, afflicted for our friends, affrighted in our mindes,</hi> and (which is moſt miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble) <hi>hindered from comming to Church;</hi> this would bee the <hi>mercy,</hi> the <hi>tender mercy of our God, whereby from on high he hath viſited us,</hi> and delivered us from that heavie <hi>viſitation.</hi> Then, as the laſt yeere <hi>in the plague,</hi> the <hi>heart</hi> of every <hi>good Chriſtian</hi> was like <hi>Ari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtotle booke, raſatabula,</hi> a <hi>Faire folio,</hi> wherein the <hi>let<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters</hi> of this <hi>text</hi> were <hi>written in text letters, God bee mercifull to mee a ſinner:</hi> ſo this yeere, being freed <hi>from the plague,</hi> we ſhould be <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, all of us ſhould be <hi>one heart,</hi> to be <hi>one booke,</hi> that <hi>book</hi> of <hi>Ezekiel, ſcriptus intus &amp; foris, written within and
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:18407:25"/>without,</hi> like <hi>Pſalme</hi> 136. every line, <hi>For his mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy endureth for ever.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now that <hi>God may ceaſe plaguing, and that we may ceaſe ſinning, God be mercifull to us All for Evermore, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Finally, to make my <hi>Exordium</hi> my <hi>Concluſion,</hi> I may re-enforce this exhortation from this preſent occaſion of <hi>hearing</hi> and <hi>ſpeaking.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In <hi>hearing,</hi> if you have offended either in regard of your <hi>attention</hi> to the <hi>ſpeaking,</hi> or of your <hi>intenſion</hi> to the <hi>practiſing</hi> of Gods word, give mee leave to bee your poore <hi>Oratour: God be mercifull to you ſinners.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>If in <hi>ſpeaking</hi> your judgement doth <hi>apprehend</hi> or <hi>reprehend</hi> any <hi>errours</hi> in my diſcourſe, I beſeech you to <hi>intercede</hi> for mee to our great <hi>interceſſour;</hi> that Chriſts <hi>mercy</hi> may <hi>pardon</hi> me what I have <hi>done, pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vent</hi> me what I <hi>ſhall doe,</hi> and <hi>preſerve</hi> me in all my <hi>do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings</hi> of this nature.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>O pray</hi> for <hi>Mee</hi> that I may <hi>pray</hi> for my ſelfe, in all my <hi>actions,</hi> but in my <hi>Sermons</hi> eſpecially. <hi>God be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull to me a ſinner.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18407:25" rendition="simple:additions"/>
                  <p>PASCHA CHRISTIANUM; <hi>THE</hi> CHRISTIAN PASSEOVER.</p>
                  <p>A Sermon appointed for the SPITTLE, but preached at St. <hi>Pauls</hi> on Wedneſday in Eaſter Weeke, 1637.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>BY</hi> JOHN LYNCH, Parſon of <hi>Herietſham</hi> in <hi>Kent,</hi> and Chaplain unto the R. Reverend Father in God the Lord Biſhop of SARUM.</p>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>Coloſſ. 2.17.</bibl> 
                     <hi>The body is</hi> CHRIST.</q>
                  <q>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>Auguſt. contra Adiman. cap. 16.</hi>
                     </bibl> Non Signa &amp; umbrae ſalutem dederunt, ſed ea quae his ſignificabantur.</q>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDOM,</hi> Printed by ROBERT YOUNG, for <hi>Humfrey Blunden,</hi> 1637.</p>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18407:26"/>
                  <pb n="47" facs="tcp:18407:26"/>
                  <head>PASCHA CHRISTIANUM, THE CHRISTIAN PASSEOVER.</head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>1 COR. 5.7.8.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>
                        <hi>7</hi> Chriſt our Paſseover is ſacrificed for us: <hi>8</hi> Let us therefore keep the Feaſt <hi>(or the Holy-day)</hi> &amp;c.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He ſubject matter (if you note it) of this my text, here, is an Apoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>licall indiction (you ſhall finde) of a Feaſt; together with a ſpecificati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on both of the cauſe why we muſt, as alſo a particular direction tou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching the manner how.</p>
                  <p>The indiction wee have in theſe words, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Epulemur:</hi> that is, as it is in the text and margent of
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:18407:27"/>our Engliſh Verſion, <hi>Let us keepe the Holy-day, Let us keepe the Feaſt.</hi> Where I pray take notice by the way, how that this our Eaſter feaſt is not like that ſame hereſie of the <hi>Acephali,</hi> a certaine blinde cuſtome, brought in amongſt us no man living can tell by whom: neither like thoſe <hi>Feriae domeſticae</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the Romans, is it of private inſtitution, of which kinde were thoſe of the <hi>Cornelian</hi> family, ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken up onely by ſome few: no, it is <hi>Feſtum publicum</hi> (you ſee) <hi>&amp; ſtativum,</hi> a feaſt that is founded upon the Word of God; and therefore S. <hi>Auguſtine</hi> telleth us in a certaine Epiſtle of his, viz. in his 119. <hi>ad Jan.</hi> how that by the expreſſe authoritie of divine Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture it is, that yeerely about this time we doe keep a feaſt.</p>
                  <p>Yea, but why now doe wee keepe a feaſt (you will ſay)? This my Text here will tell you why: <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtus Paſcha noſtrum immolatus eſt pro nobis, Chriſt our Paſſeover</hi> was now <hi>ſacrificed for us.</hi> And all theſe cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtances being duely weighed by us, have we juſt cauſe to keepe a feaſt now?</p>
                  <p>Yea, I trow; yea, and ſo to keepe it too, not as it ſhall ſeeme beſt unto our corrupt fancies, as they of <hi>Syracuſe</hi> in <hi>Livie</hi> kept the feſtivals of their <hi>Diana,</hi> for three whole daies together lewdly addicting themſelves unto nought but drunkenneſſe and all ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe; as if for our parts ſo the feaſt be kept by us, we need not to paſſe (wee thinke) for the manner how: No, <hi>ſancta ſanctè</hi> and therefore, the feaſt we keepe now being the feaſt of Paſſeover, in ſuch ſort onely are we to keepe it, as with the nature of a Paſſeover ſhall be moſt ſutable.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="49" facs="tcp:18407:27"/>Would you know how? Why not with leaven then (as you may read in <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.) <hi>non in fermento veteri,</hi> not with that old ſowre bread, which we uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally fed upon whileſt we were in <hi>Egypt;</hi> no, <hi>Haud eſt conveniens Paſchati iste panis:</hi> and therefore if wee will keepe this feaſt here, according to the preſcribed rites thereof, wee muſt utterly exterminate from us all leaven: during the whole time of this feſtivitie of ours, we muſt not ſo much as harbour leaven in our houſes; much leſſe then (if we will keepe this feaſt a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>right) may we knead and mould it up in our bread.</p>
                  <p>Yea, but if not with leavened, with what bread then is it St. <hi>Paul</hi> his will that we doe keep the feaſt? for with ſome bread or other we muſt needs keepe it (I am ſure) if his meaning in earneſt be that we doe keep it at all.</p>
                  <p>The truth is, a thing ſo neceſſary is bread to the ſubſtance of every feaſt, as that to imagine a feaſt to have no bread in it, is to imagine a feaſt to bee no feaſt. This St. <hi>Paul</hi> knew well enough, being him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe an Hebrew; he knew well enough, how that <hi>ab eſu panis Hebraei totum convivium denotârunt,</hi> how that the Hebrew idiome it was under the tearme <hi>[Bread]</hi> to comprehend uſually the whole banquet. This he knew, I ſay, and becauſe he knew it, though he bars us one ſort of bread, yet he allowes another; though hee reſtraines us from bread that hath any leaven in it, yet unleavened bread he allowes our fill. What ſay I? doth he allow it us doe I ſay? nay, to ſpeake truth, he doth injoine it us: for this word <hi>(Let)</hi> here (you muſt know) in our Engliſh Verſion is not barely permiſſive, but imperative, and ſtrict<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:18407:28"/>bind us it doth, as to keep the feaſt, ſo though not thus to keep it, yet thus; though not <hi>in fermento,</hi> yet <hi>in azymis,</hi> though not with leavened bread, yet with unleavened.</p>
                  <p>Yea, but what then? Shall we untombe the Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogue (you will ſay?) Shall we <hi>Deum colere per eſcas?</hi> And thoſe very ceremonies, which for ſo ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny hundred of yeeres have lien buried, and are quite putrefied, is it St. <hi>Paul</hi> his will (may we thinke) in this my Text here, that wee ſhould now rake them up a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine, and bring them in uſe?</p>
                  <p>Farre be it from us to have the leaſt thought, that Saint <hi>Paul</hi> ſhould play here the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that hee ſhould prevaricate, ſay and unſay; or that hee ſhould build anew what hee erſt deſtroied: that hee ſhould build anew here at Corinth, what hee deſtroied (wee read) at Coloſſi: or that hee ſhould teach one thing here unto this people, and quite another thing there unto that. You muſt know therefore how that by this leavened and unleavened bread here ſpoken of, Saint <hi>Paul</hi> meaneth not the leavened or unleavened bread of paſte: no, himſelfe hath taught us how that Gods Kingdome is not <hi>Eſca &amp; Potus;</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 14.17.</note> himſelfe hath taught us how that it is not what wee eate that commendeth a man to God:<note place="margin">1 Cor. 8.8.</note> neither if wee eate ſuch ſweet bread are wee ought the better for it (can we ſay) neither if we eate ſuch leavened bread are we ought the worſe. It is the corruption (ſaith <hi>Iſodore Hiſpalenfis</hi>) of the old man that is the leavened bread that is here ſpoken againſt. Againe, it is the converſation (ſaith hee) of the new man that is the ſweet bread that is here called for: <hi>Let us keep the
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:18407:28"/>feaſt, not with leavened bread, i.e.</hi> not with malice (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) and wickedneſſe: Againe, <hi>Let us keep the feaſt with ſweet bread, i.e.</hi> with ſincerity (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) and truth.</p>
                  <p>As the Text conſiſteth of two Verſes, ſo doe the Verſes branch themſelves into two parts, <hi>viz.</hi> into <hi>Beneficium</hi> and <hi>Officium,</hi> into a doctrine of faith, and a rule of life: into <hi>Beneficium</hi> or <hi>Credendum,</hi> a thing done for us on Good-Friday; and into <hi>Officium</hi> or <hi>Agendum,</hi> a thing to bee done by us now at Eaſter; yea not at Eaſter onely, but every day, during the whole ſeven daies of our life. The <hi>Beneficium</hi> wee have in theſe words: <hi>Paſcha noſtrum, &amp;c.</hi> The <hi>Offici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>um</hi> in theſe: <hi>Itaque epulemur.</hi> The thing done for us we have in the ſeventh Verſe, <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed:</hi> the thing to be done by us in the eighth, <hi>Let us therefore keep the feaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>In the <hi>Beneficium,</hi> which I call the doctrine, the <hi>Credendum</hi> or thing done, there are foure things which doe voluntarily offer themſelves in ſeverall to be obſerved, and all they too (if wee well conſider them) of ſuch ſingular moment and importance, as that even in ſeverall they may afford us matter e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nough, every one of them to keep a feaſt for. Here of the firſt is <hi>Paſchanoſtrum,</hi> that even wee Chriſtians have alſo a Paſſeover. The ſecond is <hi>Chriſtus,</hi> that our Paſſeover is Chriſt. The third is <hi>Sacrificatus eſt,</hi> that Chriſt is ſacrificed. The fourth and laſt is <hi>Prono<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bis,</hi> that hee is ſacrificed for us. Of theſe in order, and firſt of <hi>Paſcha noſtrum,</hi> that even wee Chriſtians have alſo a Paſſeover; wee that are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed by faith, as well as they that are <hi>Abrahams</hi> ſeed by
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:18407:29"/>fleſh: we of the new Covenant <hi>Our's,</hi> as well as they of the old Covenant <hi>Their's.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <milestone type="tcpmilestone" unit="unspecified" n="1"/> Yea, but a Paſſeover! What is a Paſſeover (you will ſay?) A rite it is well worth the cleering; and the true meaning whereof (if you will but looke in <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus, cap.</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 26.) it is Gods command (you ſhall find) that every Iſraelite ſo punctually ſhould under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand, as that if a childe (they ſay) were but once a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to eate ſo much bread as an olive, and were but of ſtrength once holding his father by the hand to goe from Jeruſalem gates unto the Temple, the father of that childe was bound to cauſe him to goe up that hee might there catechize him in this ceremonie. Where by the way, I pray tell mee, did God ſo ſtrictly bind the Jewes to inſtruct and edifie their children in the grounds and principles of religion; and is it a matter (may we thinke) that he left freely unto the choice and liberty of us Chriſtians, whether wee for our parts in theſe things will informe our children now or not? How commeth it to paſſe elſe (I would faine know) that ſome amongſt us, who are paſt ſucklings (I am ſure) yea or weanlings either, yea or ſtriplings either, being in truth many of them (we ſee) men growne, and therefore able (we may think) to eate more bread than comes to the quantity of an olive, and to goe further without a fathers hand than from Jeruſalems gates unto the Temple, than from the ſtreet unto the Church (I meane) than from their owne houſes unto Gods, how commeth it to paſſe (I ſay) that ſome amongſt us, who are now altogether (I am ſure) paſt children (unleſſe you will make ſuch children as the Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> doth,<note place="margin">Iſaiah 63.20.</note> children well
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:18407:29"/>nigh an hundred yeeres old) are yet more groſſely ignorant in moſt Chriſtian principles, than are even the moſt ignorantly ignorant amongſt the Roma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſts? But of this <hi>Obiter,</hi> and but by the by onely (as we ſay) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to our ſhame, to the end, that if poſſible, I might in theſe things provoke us of the Church of England unto emulation. To anſwer at length therefore unto the queſtion, touching the ſenſe and meaning of a Paſſeover.</p>
                  <p>The word <hi>Paſcha</hi> here in the originall is by birth an Hebrew (you muſt know) not a Greeke; neither (as ſome Monkes have ſung) doth it derive its pedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gree from <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to ſuffer: but <hi>ſicut perhibent qui hoc ſciunt</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) as men skilfull in that language have delivered, <hi>Ab eo dicitur quod tranſitur,</hi> it is deduced in Hebrew from the word <hi>Paſach,</hi> which is as much (you muſt know) in our native En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh, as to fare, leap, or to paſs over: &amp; therfore ſome have thought how that even from this very root not onely <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> hath ſprung amongſt the Greekes, but even amongſt the Latines alſo <hi>Paſſus,</hi> and here in our own country dialect a Paſe. Now the <hi>tranſitus</hi> or paſſage here alluded unto by Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> is that which in the 12. chapter of the booke of <hi>Exodus</hi> wee doe find de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed to the very full: where the deſtroying Angel by Gods appointment being to paſſe quite through the land of Egypt, and to ſmite impartially all the firſt-borne in the land, even from man unto beaſt (e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven from the firſt-borne of <hi>Pharaoh</hi> that ſate upon his throne, unto the firſt-borne of the captive that was in the dungeon) he yet ſpared (we reade) Gods owne people, hee in mercy paſſed over them, God
<pb n="54" facs="tcp:18407:30"/>having appointed them to this purpoſe with the bloud of a certaine Lambe to all-beſprinkle both the two ſide-poſts, and the upper doore-poſt of their houſes, that the Exterminator ſeeing the bloud thereon, might not paſſe in thither to deſtroy them. The remembrance of this deſtruction, thus paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing over them, were the children of Iſrael every yeer in moſt ſolemne manner to celebrate, both by the killing of a certaine Lambe, ſelected by them to this purpoſe, as alſo by performing duly certaine other rites preſcribed unto them by God. This Lamb thus ſlaine by them in memory of what had once paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed them, did the Jewiſh people by a Metonymie call <hi>Paſcha ſuum,</hi> their Paſſeover, and the ſlaying and the eating of this Lambe, the ſlaying and eating of their Paſſeover. <hi>Thou ſhalt ſacrifice the Paſſeover at even</hi> (ſaith God, <hi>Deut.</hi> 16. <hi>ver.</hi> 6.) <hi>Where wilt thou</hi> (ſay the Diſciple, <hi>Matth.</hi> 14.) <hi>that wee goe and pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pare that thou mayeſt eate the Paſſeover?</hi> The Paſſeo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver! that is, the Lambe, whereby the Angels paſſing over them was commemorated; it being no unuſuall thing amongſt ſundry other kinds of ſacramentall predication, to ſpeake that of the thing ſignified, which is true moſt properly of the ſigne only, and to aſcribe that againe unto the ſigne, which is due onely in truth unto the thing ſignified: and all this by rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon altogether of that ſpirituall union and conjuncti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on which in every ſacrament of either Covenant is betwixt the <hi>Relatum</hi> (as they call it) and the <hi>Corre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latum,</hi> betwixt the corporall ſubſtance and the ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall, betwixt the outward element, and the inward grace.</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="55" facs="tcp:18407:30"/>Well, you have ſeen by this time (I ſuppoſe) what a Paſſeover is, what in it ſelfe, what in its ſigne, what <hi>in rei veritate,</hi> what <hi>in ſignificante myſterio;</hi> what in the truth of the thing done, what in figure alſo of that ſame truth. In it ſelfe, it was the paſſage (you have ſeen) of a deſtroying Angell over the Iſraelites; in it's ſigne it was a ſacrifice offered in remembrance of that ſame paſſage: in the truth of the thing done, Iſraels firſt-borne you ſee were preſerved; in figure of that ſame truth, a certaine Lamb, you ſee, was ſlain. Yea, but in the meane while, where is <hi>noſtrum</hi> (you will ſay?) Where is that ſame Paſſeover which I ſaid was Ours? For all this while have we been only in Iſrael, you know: and what is Iſraels, I am ſure, is nought to us.</p>
                  <p>True, it is not (I muſt confeſſe:) but yet for all this have but patience (I beſeech you) for a little time, and I nothing doubt but with Gods aſſiſtance to repay with intereſt, what erſt I promiſed, and to make it cleare unto you how that, as well as Iſrael, even we Chriſtians alſo have a Paſſeover, a paſſage over from as great an evill, a paſſage over to as great a good. For proofe hereof, I pray tell me what think you (I beſeech you) of our ſoule? Is not that a thing we muſt needs grant every whit as deere unto us as our firſt borne? Yea, a thing in truth for whoſe ſalvation, for whoſe ſafe paſſage (I meane) from hence to Heaven, there is no man (I thinke) ſo devoid of reaſon, that will not give both firſt borne and all hee hath too. Againe, what think you (I beſeech you) of Gods vengeance continually hovering over us, for our ſinnes, and every houre, every moment ready
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:18407:31"/>to powre us downe to hell? Is not that a thing as much to bee dreaded by us, as that deſtroying Angell was by the Iſraelites: yea and by ſo much the more too, by how much wee are to feare eternall death, more than temporall? But now when by reaſon of <hi>Adams</hi> ſinne we were all liable to condemnation, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pecting hourely when Gods juſtice ſhould have ceazed upon our ſoules, that God in mercy was then pleaſed not to deſtroy us with the Egyptians: that is (as S. <hi>Paul</hi> phraſeth it) not to condemn us with the world, but to paſſe over us, to ſpare us (as he did his own children ſome times the Iſraelites) not ſuffering the Exterminator to have any power at all upon us; that thus it was, what is more plaine (I beſeech you) throughout the whole body of the New Teſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment? Where read wee not (if you have obſerved it) in many places of our being delivered from <hi>wrath?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Theſſ. 1.10.</note> Of our being freed from the <hi>Law?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Rom. 8.2. Gal. 3.13. Epheſ. 2.5.</note> Of our being re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemed from the <hi>Curſe?</hi> Of being ſaved by <hi>Grace?</hi> And in the fift of St. <hi>John</hi> the 24. <hi>verſ.</hi> (where wee have both the <hi>terminos</hi> of this happy paſſage of ours) reade we not expreſly how that each true beleever is <hi>already paſſed from death to life?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well then, that a Paſſeover we have, that is moſt certaine (you ſee) even we Chriſtians, as well as the Jewes: yea and that ſuch a Paſſeover in truth (if wee well examine it) as wherewith the Jewiſh Paſſeover muſt not compare: No, neither in reſpects of that evill which in either Paſſeover was avoyded, the evill in theirs being only a bodily danger, wheras it was a ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rituall danger (you ſee) that wee eſcaped in ours: nor yet in reſpect of that good which in either
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:18407:31"/>Paſſeover was effected, the good in theirs being on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly a temporall deliverance; whereas it was an eternall deliverance, you ſee, that was wrought in ours. What will you ſay now unto the meanes ordained by God in either Paſſeover for the effecting of this good, for the avoiding of this evill, for the working of this deliverance, for the eſcaping of this danger? Even in this reſpect too is not their Paſſeover far in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour (alas) to ours? even as farre as the earth is in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour unto the heavens? even as farre as the creature is inferiour to the Creator? Yes: for whereas the meanes in theirs was only <hi>agnus,</hi> as ſaith Saint <hi>Am<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>broſe, irrationabilis naturae;</hi> behold in ours it was <hi>ag<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nus divinae potentiae:</hi> whereas the meanes in theirs was only a lamb that was taken by them out of the fould; behold in ours it was that Lambe that deſcended for us downe from heaven, even that very Lamb which both S. <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeakes of and S. <hi>John</hi> the <hi>Baptiſt</hi> points at, namely <hi>Chriſt; Paſcha noſtrum Chriſtus eſt,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 1.19.</note> our Paſſeover,</hi> ſaith my text, <hi>is Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 And the truth is, if wee well conſider with our ſelves what was to be done for us in our Paſſeover, what the ſtate we were to paſſe from, what the ſtate wee were to paſſe unto, wee muſt needs grant how that in all reaſon none could have been our Paſſeover, ſave onely Chriſt alone; none the meanes of our paſſage from the ſtate of wrath to the ſtate of grace; none the meanes of our paſſage from the ſtate of death to the ſtate of glory, ſave onely that Lambe, <hi>qui tollit peccata mundi,</hi> even that Lamb of God,<note place="margin">Joh. 1.36.</note>
                     <hi>qui in ſinu Patris eſt;</hi> that moſt holy immaculate Lambe <hi>Chriſt.</hi> For alas, alas, in the caſe wee were in, could
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:18407:32"/>any other lamb have ſerved the turne, think you? could a lamb out of the ſtock have beene a ſufficient ranſome for a mans ſoule? for that which is of more worth than all the lambs in the whole world are? yea, in truth than the whole World it ſelfe is, or a whole world of worlds beſides? Why, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, (ſaith <hi>Proclus</hi> of Conſtantinople) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: the redempti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of a ſoule is a greater purchaſe, than either the wealthieſt Saint could have compaſſed, or the migh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tieſt Angell; how much leſſe then could a common lamb, trow you, have a conſiderable recompenſe, and counterprice, I ſay not for all the ſoules in this or that onely particular Kingdome, but even for all the ſoules of all the people in all the Kingdomes under Heaven? But now ſuch a Lambe it was that wee wanted; ſuch a Lambe that we ſtood in need of, even a Lambe by whoſe meanes and merit the deſtroying Angell might bee made paſſe over, not the ſoules onely of ſome few Iſraelites, in our little Angle only of the Land of Egypt; but over all the ſoules of all mankinde, that either are or have beene ſince the world began. Why, and bleſſed be God (and we have cauſe to feaſt for it I think) ſuch a Paſchal Lambe it is that we now have, God in mercy having ſo provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded for us, that even his onely Son, you ſee, ſhould be our Lambe; for <hi>Paſcha noſtrum Chriſtus eſt, our Paſſeover,</hi> ſaith my text, <hi>is Chriſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt (I ſay) and in very deed ſuch a true Paſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chal Lamb is Chriſt, ſuch a perfect Paſſeover our Paſſeover, ſuch a compleat Paſſeover ours, as that to ours the Jewiſh Paſſeover was but as the ſhadow
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:18407:32"/>unto the ſubſtance, the Jewiſh Lambe to ours but as the type unto the truth. For proofe hereof, doe but ſee the Parallels, I beſeech you, betwixt their Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over and ours, betwixt <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as they call it, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, betwixt our crucifigible Paſſeover, and their legall one: and I pray tell me what think you? was there ought typified can we ſay in theirs, which in every reſpect, if we ſearch the Goſpel, was not fully verified (wee ſhall finde) in ours?
<list>
                        <item>Firſt, their Lambe was one of the flocke, wee read; in like man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner ſo was ours, even <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, (ſaith <hi>Euſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bius Caeſarienſis</hi>) one that was <hi>made of a woman</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) that was <hi>true man.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Secondly,<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Gal.</hi> 4 4.</note> Secondly, their Lambe was <hi>without blemiſh,</hi> wee read;<note place="margin">
                              <hi>Exod.</hi> 12.5.</note> in like manner ſo was ours, even <gap reason="foreign">
                              <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                           </gap>, (ſaith <hi>Proclus</hi>) one that knew no ſinne, ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi> that had no guile.</item>
                        <item>Third<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, their Lambe was to bee offered, we read; in like manner ſo was ours, <hi>Oblatus eſt quia ipſe voluit,</hi> ſaith the Prophet; <hi>through the eternall Spirit,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Paul,</hi>
                           <note place="margin">
                              <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note>
                           <hi>hee offered himſelfe.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>Fourthly, and laſt of all, their Lambe, we read, was to be ſacrificed; in like manner ſo was ours, <hi>Chriſtus Paſcha noſtrum immolatus eſt, Chriſt our Paſſeover,</hi> ſaith my Text, <hi>is ſacrificed.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The word in the Originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which is ren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dred by divers diverſly: M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Beza</hi> reading it, <hi>ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catus eſt, Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed,</hi> whereas in the Vulgar Latine we finde it, <hi>immolatus eſt, Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſlaine.</hi> To ſpeake properly, it is the word <hi>ſacrificed</hi> that in my judgement doth here fit us beſt; that importing unto us not onely the ſlaying of a thing, but alſo the ſlaying of a thing offered; without either of which, in true proprietie of ſpeech,
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:18407:33"/>Chriſt could never have bin a ſacrifice, and therefore conſequently never <hi>Paſcha noſtrum,</hi> never in all reaſon <hi>our Paſſeover.</hi> This is evident by that difference which hath been obſerved by the learned, betwixt what is offered, what is ſacrificed, and what onely upon ſome common ordinary occaſion is ſlain: becauſe whereas a thing may be offered (they tell us) that is not ſlaine, as the firſt-borne were amongſt the Iſraelites; and ſlaine that is not ſacrificed, as the calfe was by the Witch of <hi>Endor:</hi> yet truely ſacrificed they ſay a thing cannot be, unleſſe both offered it be, yea and ſlaine too, either analogically or really, either in pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portion or in truth. Chriſt was both, to ſhew in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry reſpect the truth and veritie of his ſacrifice, <hi>&amp; ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latus eſt, &amp; immolatus,</hi> Chriſt our Paſſeover, I ſay, was both. In <hi>Iſai.</hi> 53.3. there the Prophet tells us that Chriſt was offered: in <hi>Dan.</hi> 9.26. there the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet tells us that Chriſt was ſlain: again, in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. there the Apoſtle tells us that Chriſt was offered: in <hi>Rev.</hi> 5.12. there the Apoſtle tels us that Chriſt was ſlaine. <hi>Oblatus eſt,</hi> he was offered, ſay Divines, <hi>in vita,</hi> in his life: <hi>Occiſus eſt,</hi> he was ſlaine, ſay they, <hi>in cruce,</hi> upon the croſſe. <hi>Oblatus eſt,</hi> hee was offered that his ſlaughter might be a ſacrifice: <hi>Occiſus eſt,</hi> he was ſlaine that his ſacrifice might be complete. One thing I am ſure of, ſo ſanctified was Chriſt his ſlaughter by his being offered, and on the other ſide againe, ſo accompliſhed was Chriſt his ſacrifice by his being ſlaine, as that not without cauſe it is, if we well conſider it, that St. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith not in this my Text here, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Chriſt our Paſſeover is <hi>offered,</hi> or <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Chriſt our Paſſover is <hi>ſlain;</hi>
                     <pb n="61" facs="tcp:18407:33"/>no, but to make it plaine unto us how that <hi>ſlaine</hi> hee was, not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, upon any common uſuall oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſion, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, in honour only of our God (which the learned obſerve to be the maine and only difference between <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>:) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, therefore, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith he, Chriſt our Paſſeover is <hi>ſacrificed.</hi> Yea but to ſacrifice is a Church-worke, you will ſay, not to be done but by ſome Prieſt onely; it would not bee amiſſe therefore to make enquiry here by what Prieſt it was that Chriſt was ſacrificed.</p>
                  <p>Surely by none other Prieſt, ſave only by himſelfe alone; it was himſelfe onely that here gave himſelfe to bee a ſacrifice unto God now:<note place="margin">
                        <hi>Eph.</hi> 5.2. <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.14.</note>
                     <hi>Tradidit hostiam ſemetipſum,</hi> ſaith Saint <hi>Paul, Chriſt did offer up him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Ipſe ſemetipſum?</hi> did Chriſt ſacrifice himſelfe? why, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (as I have ſhewed you) what ever is ſacrificed is deſtroyed; and did Chriſt deſtroy himſelfe, you will ſay? did he <hi>ſemetipſum in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terficere,</hi> ſlay himſelfe?</p>
                  <p>For anſwer: Though preciſely neceſſary it be un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to every ſacrifice that the thing offered be deſtroy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, yet it is no way materiall at all by whom de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtroyed it bee, whether by him that offereth it, or by ſome other, provided alwayes that the partie of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fering it, doe willingly yeeld thereunto his conſent. But now that Chriſt conſented to his owne death, at leaſt wiſe that hee did not hinder it, neither <hi>potentiae obicem opponendo,</hi> nor <hi>objectum actui ſubducendo,</hi> this is ſo plaine, as that to doubt thereof is to doubt whether there bee a Sunne or no at noone-day. For proofe hereof, in <hi>Joh.</hi> 10. doth hee not <hi>lay downe his
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:18407:34"/>life</hi> (he tells us) <hi>of himſelfe?</hi> yea, ſaith he not plainly, that no man taketh it from him whether hee will or no, but that freely, voluntarily, of his owne accord hee doth lay it downe of himſelfe? Yea. Hence is it that through the eternall Spirit he is ſaid to offer up himſelfe. Neither wonder hereat, as at a thing un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>likely, that in one and the ſame action, the ſame per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, at the ſame time, ſhould bee both ſacrifice anc Prieſt too; for I will tell you more than this (and it is matter of wonder indeed) when Chriſt our Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over was now ſacrificed, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> ſaith <hi>Epiphanius,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that he might ſhew from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth how that all other ſacrifices were for evermore to be aboliſhed, and that together with his, all other, with all appendices of theirs, were to expire their laſt. <hi>Idem &amp; ipſe Pontifex,</hi> ſaith <hi>Origen, idem ponatur &amp; hoſtia:</hi> both the ſacrifice was the Prieſt, faith <hi>Epi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phanius,</hi> and the Prieſt the Lambe, and the Lamb the Temple, and the Temple the Altar, and the Altar God, and God Man: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Chriſt being made all in all things, and all purpoſely for us, <hi>ſacrificatus eſt pro nobis, Chriſt is ſacrificed,</hi> ſaith my Text, <hi>for us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well then, that wee have a Paſſeover, you have ſeen (as I ſuppoſe) and that this Paſſeover of ours is Chriſt: you have ſeen alſo how or when it was that Chriſt here was Our Paſſeover, <hi>viz.</hi> not as hee was ſlaine without being offered; nor yet as hee was offe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red without being ſlaine: no, but as hee was both ſlaine and offered too, and ſo ſacrificed: <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeover</hi> (ſaith my Text) <hi>is ſacrificed.</hi> The laſt cir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cumſtance that now preſenteth it ſelfe in this firſt part
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:18407:34"/>of my Text to be entreated of, is the <hi>finis cui,</hi> the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon for whoſe ſake it was that Chriſt was ſacrificed; <hi>Sacrificatus eſt pro nobis, Chriſt was ſacrificed</hi> (ſaith my Text) <hi>for us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For us!</hi> Not for himſelfe then: no, there was no cauſe of death (God wot) in him: <hi>Ipſe non meruit ſi non pro pietate mori,</hi> even his very Judge himſelfe being his witneſſe, there was nothing worthy of death to be found in him. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (ſaith <hi>The<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>odoret</hi> in the perſon of Chriſt) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: hee that owed not a death, tooke death now upon himſelfe, and hee ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jected himſelfe unto death here, over whom death in truth had not any right at all. And to ſpeake ſooth, well for us was it that Chriſt ſuffered not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe; well for us, yea very well that he was not ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed for himſelfe. For if the way of that old Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pent had been ever found upon this rocke,<note place="margin">Prov. 30.19.</note> if this our Lambe had had any ſpot in him, and ſo had deſerved death in himſelfe, could hee ever then have been a fit Paſſeover, to have now been ſacrificed (as hee was) for us? No, <hi>Si ipſe indebitam mortem non ſuſciperet,</hi> (ſaith <hi>Gregorie</hi>) <hi>nunquam nos à debita morte liberaret:</hi> if Chriſt (I may ſay) in any reſpect had bin ſacrificed for himſelfe, impoſſible then had it been that in any reſpect he ſhould have thus ſatified (as hee did) for us: but now ſo it is, that in this my Text here, <hi>Chriſt was ſacrificed</hi> (we reade) <hi>for Us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For Us!</hi> Not for Angels then: no, as not for him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe, ſo not for them neither; their nature he aſſumed not, their perſon hee ſuſtained not, hee for them was not ſacrificed, they by him were not delivered. It
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:18407:35"/>was for Us, for <hi>us men</hi> (ſaith our Creed) that the Son of God came downe from heaven, that he was incar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate by the holy Ghoſt of the Virgin <hi>Mary,</hi> that he was made man: for <hi>us men,</hi> for <hi>us</hi> it was that he was made lower than the Angels, <hi>quod expertus infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma, quod paſſus indigna, &amp; quod demum per mortem crucis ad ſua reverſus;</hi> and that at the laſt he was thus ſacrificed according to this Scripture. The truth is, had this my Text here been either penn'd or ſpoken unto us by ſome Angel, why then queſtionleſſe as well for Angels as for <hi>Us</hi> might wee have ſaid that Chriſt was ſacrificed: but now the words (you know) are Saint <hi>Pauls,</hi> and Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (you know) was a man, why then for <hi>us men</hi> it was that Chriſt was ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificed (you ſee) for <hi>us men,</hi> I ſay, for <hi>us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Yea, but Saint <hi>Paul</hi> (you will ſay) was a Jew, and if Chriſt was ſacrificed for Jewes onely, very little (God knowes) will be the benefit that will ariſe from hence to <hi>us.</hi> True, he was ſo indeed, himſelfe hath told us, how that hee was an Hebrew of the He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes: but here is the comfort yet, and without this, ſmall heart ſhould wee have to keep the feaſt now; here is the comfort (I ſay) that this Epiſtle of his, whereof this my Text here is a part &amp; portion, is not <hi>beati Pauli ad Hebraeos,</hi> the Epiſtle of S. <hi>Paul</hi> the Apoſtle unto the Hebrewes; no, but <hi>ad Corinthios prima,</hi> his firſt Epiſtle unto the Corinthians. Now the City of Corinth ſtood in Greece (you muſt know) above ſeven hundred miles from Judea, and therefore queſtionleſſe the people wrote to here were meerly Gentiles, no Jewes. Why, and ſo they were indeed, and becauſe they were ſo, we may
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:18407:35"/>from hence gather therefore to our comfort, how that for us Gentiles it was that Chriſt was ſacrificed, for us Gentiles, for us.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>For us!</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> !<note place="margin">Rom. 11.</note> O the depth of the riches of the wiſedome and goodneſſe of our God! how unſcarch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>able are his judgements? how his waies paſt finding out? Could it ever have been beleeved that Chriſt ſhould have been thus ſacrificed (as he was) for us? for us ſinners of the Gentiles? for us that were farre off? for us that were without God in the world, that the Son of God ſhould be thus ſlain for us? Indeed, had it bin for the Jews only that Chriſt had died here, the wonder queſtionleſſe had not been ſo great, for they were Gods inheritance, Gods choſen, the ſeed of <hi>Abraham</hi> Gods friend; and if for a friend a man may chance to die ſometimes, why not ſometimes then for a friends ſeed too. But now as for us, wee were not only <hi>abalienati à Deo,</hi> not only <hi>quoad ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tum externum,</hi> ſtrangers; but we were alſo (we muſt remember) <hi>hoſtes, quoad diſsidium internum,</hi> enemies: yea, &amp; that as well in an active as in a paſſive ſenſe, as well directly as by interpretation, as well for that we rebelliouſly hated Gods rule over us, as for that we were in all things contrary unto his will: and is it not moſt ſtrange and admirable (in this caſe we were in) that Chriſt ſhould be ſacrificed yet for us? the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent for the guilty? the home-borne for ſtrangers? the only Son for enemies? Chriſt for us? Yet ſo it was, and that now it was ſo, it was no more than was fore-told, no more than in <hi>Numb.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 10.11. God himſelfe had ſignified that ſo it ſhould be. For be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides that firſt Paſſeover there in the firſt moneth,
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:18407:36"/>reade we not alſo of a ſecond Paſſeover (if you mark it) in the ſecond moneth? of a Paſſeover allowed by God to be ſlaine purpoſely for thoſe perſons, who during the celebration of the firſt Paſſeover were in a journey a farre off)? Yes. But now, if you will but ſuffer S. <hi>Paul</hi> to unvaile <hi>Moſes</hi> his face, if you will but expound the Law there by the Goſpel, <hi>Num.</hi> 9. <hi>ver.</hi> 10. by <hi>Epheſ.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. you ſhall then find how that not without a myſterie it is, that the Hebrew of this word <hi>far off</hi> is obſerved by the learned for ſome ſpeciall conſideration to have extraordinary prickes over it; becauſe by that ſecond Paſſeover there per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted by God to thoſe in a journey farre off, God did prefigure unto us Chriſt here ſacrificed (you ſee) for us, even for us Gentiles in the fleſh, ſtrangers, for us who at that time were farre off, both from the kindred of the Jewiſh nation, and from the Cove<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nants alſo of the promiſe, <hi>Sacrificatus eſt pro nobis, Chriſt is ſacrificed</hi> (ſaith my Text) <hi>for us.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Well then Chriſt died not (you have ſeen) for himſelfe here, nor yet for Angels; no, nor yet onely for Jewes neither: for Saint <hi>Paul</hi> writing (you ſee) unto Gentiles, ſaith, that <hi>Chriſt is ſacrificed for us. For us</hi> he ſaith; not for ſome few of us, under ſuch a Romane Prelate onely, or of ſuch a faction: for us within the verges onely of the Romiſh Hierarchy, or for us of the Congregation onely in New England: No, <hi>ſanguis Chriſti pretium eſt</hi> (ſaith St. <hi>Auguſtine</hi>) the Lambe here ſacrificed (you ſee) is Chriſt; and therefore at too high a rate do they value themſelves, and the bloud of Chriſt doe they prize too low, <hi>qui dicum aut illud tam parvum eſſe, ut ſolos Afros eme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit;
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:18407:36"/>aut ſe tam magnos pro quibus ſolis illud ſit datum:</hi> who being themſelves (God he knowes) but a ſorry handfull of men, if they compare themſelves with the whole world, doe yet think that this common Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over of ours ſhould bee ſlaine incommunicably for none but them alone. In <hi>Hebr.</hi> 2. <hi>ver.</hi> 9. Chriſt ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſted death (we reade) for every man: in 2. <hi>Corinth.</hi> 5. <hi>ver.</hi> 14. hee died Saint <hi>Paul</hi> tells us for <hi>all:</hi> ſo that when in this my text here we do reade of Chriſt our Paſſeover, how that he was ſacrificed for us, it is in effect (you muſt know) but the very ſame with that in <hi>Rom.</hi> 8. <hi>ver.</hi> 32. where God delivered up (we reade) his owne Son, <hi>pro nobis omnibus,</hi> for us all. Howbeit, I would not that you ſhould here miſtake mee, as if the benefit of Chriſt his paſſion (I thought) ſhould redound to all men, and as if becauſe in <hi>Heb.</hi> 2. Chriſt taſted death for every man, I might therefore hold, that every man ſhould reap the fruit of it unto ſalva<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion. No, however it was that <hi>ſufficienter</hi> (as wee ſay) and in reſpect of the dignity of the price paid, Chriſt was ſacrificed, we may ſay very wel, for every one of us in the whole world: for, <hi>Tanti quid valet</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Auguſtine?</hi>) <hi>Quid, niſi totus orbis? Quid, niſi omnes gentes?</hi> what one worldly thing, except the whole world it ſelfe, could be worth the bloud-ſhedding of the Son of God? yet becauſe the Jewiſh Paſſeover was never kill'd (if you have obſerv'd it) but for ſuch onely as were made count of (as in <hi>Exo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dus</hi> 12. <hi>ver.</hi> 4. you may reade, if it pleaſe you, more at large:) for this cauſe therefore (I ſay) onely for them amongſt us was Chriſt ſlaine <hi>efficienter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Eſtiu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </hi>) to purpoſe: I meane for them only <hi>ſimpliciter</hi>
                     <pb n="68" facs="tcp:18407:37"/>(ſaith <hi>Topporus</hi>) for them onely with effect, whom God having choſen from before all eternity to bee Sons (as we may call them) of the ſociety, ſhall now eate this Lambe in their ſeverall families, ſhall apply Chriſt unto themſelves by faith. So then the reaſon why all are not ſaved is not want of merit in Chriſt, but of faith and grace in them that periſh. That thus it was, what is more plaine (I beſeech you) than that in <hi>Galat.</hi> 3. <hi>ver.</hi> 27. where reade we not how that the promiſe of the faith of Jeſus, is given to them only that beleeve? Yes: and therefore, <hi>Si non credis</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Ambroſe</hi>) <hi>non tibi paſſus eſt Chriſtus:</hi> never dreame thou (O man) that Chriſt was ſacrificed for thee, in caſe it be ſo that thou doeſt not beleeve. The truth is, did Saint <hi>Paul</hi> write here unto an infidell people, not converted, ſome ground then might pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fane miſcreants have, to hope that Chriſt was ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficed here for them: but the endorſement (if you marke it) of this Epiſtle runs, not unto all at Corinth without exception; no, but <hi>Eccleſiae Dei quae eſt Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rinthi,</hi> unto them that call there on the name of Chriſt: now, <hi>Quo modo invocabunt in quem non cre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diderunt?</hi> how poſſibly can men invoke him in whom they have not as yet beleeved? Why then for Us be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leevers it was that Chriſt was ſacrificed (you ſee) for Us beleevers, I ſay, for Us.</p>
                  <p>For Us (I ſay) and for ſuch of us two waies may wee ſay that Chriſt was ſacrificed: for us, for our good; and for us, in our ſtead: for us, for our be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hoofe; and for us, in our behalfe. Firſt, for our good: for we muſt not thinke that Chriſt our Paſſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over was ſlaine in vaine here; that the Sonne of God
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:18407:37"/>did dye <hi>gratis</hi> (as we ſay) that the ſoveraigne foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taine of Chriſt his bloud was let out to run at waſte: wee muſt not thinke that this boxe of ointment, farre more precious than that of Spikenard elſewhere, was broken, ſpilt, and powred forth here <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, to no purpoſe. The good queſtionleſſe is moſt infi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nite that doth redound unto us from Chriſt his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice; yea ſo infinite, as that here in this life wee cannot perfectly conceive it, becauſe (alas) here in this life wee doe not perfectly receive it; the greateſt part of what we enjoy, being the leaſt part of what wee expect: the greateſt part of what wee have <hi>in re,</hi> the leaſt part of what we have <hi>in ſpe.</hi> In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, wee may here meditate perhaps on ſome few particulars of what Chriſt hath gained for us by this his ſacrifice, but the exact knowledge, as well as the full fruition of ſuch benefits, being reſerv'd eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally for the life to come, beyond the faculty it is of our beſt Arithmetick to recount the ſumme of them, to compute them all.</p>
                  <p>One thing I am ſure of, the ſole benefit that doth now accrue unto us by Chriſt his ſacrifice, is not onely, as ſome fond miſcreants have dreamed, our confirmation in the Goſpell: no, if this were all, I would gladly know then in what one particular a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove the reſt, the death of Chriſt here doth more ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantage us than the death might have done of ſome other man? Doth not S. <hi>Paul</hi> tell us of himſelfe, how that what he ſuffered was for Gods choſen ſake, the Elect? that is (as it is <hi>Col.</hi> 1.24) for Chriſt his bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die ſake the Church? Well, but how for the Elect? how for the Church it would be knowne? Mary (as
<pb n="70" facs="tcp:18407:38"/>my Lord of <hi>Sarum</hi> cleeres it in that moſt excellent expoſition of his) <hi>non pro illis redimendis, non expi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>andis;</hi> not that he might ſatisfie for their ſinnes, nor (<gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, St. <hi>Paul</hi> had not wherewith to pay his owne ſcores, much leſſe then would his ſtocke hold out to defray the debts of other men) <hi>ſed pro illis confirmandis &amp; adificandis in doctrina Evangelica,</hi> but that by his ſufferings he might confirme and ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſh them in the truth and certainty of what he had preached; and that by this means they being ſtreng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thened in the faith and verity of the Goſpel, <hi>ſalutem conſequantur quae est in Chriſto,</hi> they might obtaine that ſalvation which is in Chriſt.</p>
                  <p>But now did St. <hi>Paul</hi> doe this by his death,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 2.10.</note> and did Chriſt may we thinke no more by his? did the Diſciple doe this by his death, and did the Lord, may we thinke, no more by his? nay, in truth did Chriſt here no more for us now by his death, than what by his miracles (if we doe but well bethinke our ſelves) he had done formerly (we ſhall finde) in his life time? and what very well hee might have done for us, though he had never taſted death at all? Why ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, I beſeech you, that after a long time ſpent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt us here in this world, in all pietie, innocency, and demonſtration of the Spirit, our bleſſed Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our at laſt, like the Prophet <hi>Eliah</hi> elſewhere, ſhould have beene charioted up into heaven without death, and from heaven ſhould have given a <hi>ſpecimen</hi> of his power and majeſtie unto us on earth here: might not even this alone have been enough, we may think, to have eſtabliſhed us in the Goſpel? this alone have beene abundantly enough to have confirmed and
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:18407:38"/>ſtrengthened us in the truth? Yes, I trow. Why then it is cleere, I thinke, how ever ſome heretickes have broached the contrary, that the good benefit &amp; emolument which doth redound unto us by Chriſt his ſacrifice, muſt ſurely in reaſon bee ſomewhat elſe needs, beſides our confirmation in what h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>e had taught.</p>
                  <p>Why and ſomewhat elſe alſo muſt it needs be, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides our inſtitution in holineſſe, and beſides our in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction by his example, in obedience, patience, and brotherly love. For, as St. <hi>Bernard</hi> ſweetly, <hi>Quid prodeſt,</hi> ſaith hee, <hi>quod nos inſtituit, ſi non reſtituit?</hi> wherein are we profited by Chriſt his inſtruction, if wee bee not alſo reſcued by him from deſtruction? Indeed Chriſt his croſſe (I muſt confeſſe) was our co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pie, Chriſt his paſſion our patterne; and therefore St. <hi>Peter</hi> tells us how that Chriſt did ſuffer for us,<note place="margin">1 Pet. 2.21.</note> lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving us <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an Example, <hi>ut nos veſtigia ipſius inſequeremur,</hi> that wee might tread in his ſteppes,<note place="margin">Phil. 2.5.</note> both incheerfully ſubmitting our ſelves unto Gods appointments, and in enduring patiently all wrongs, as alſo (which St. <hi>John</hi> pointeth at) in effectually lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving one another, even unto the death.<note place="margin">1 John. 3.16.</note> Well, but if Chriſt his paſſion doth no way benefit us at all, but by way of patterne onely and enſample, what then ſhall we ſay of infants? very hard ſurely muſt it goe with them needs, little fruit, little profit will there from Chriſt his death here ariſe to them: for can they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forme themſelves unto Chriſt his death, who have never heard as yet of Chriſt his life? or can they imi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tate, may wee thinke, their Saviours vertues, who have never imitated as yet their firſt parents ſinne?
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:18407:39"/>In all likelihood, <hi>pro qualitate vulneris allata eſt medi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cina;</hi> in all probabilitie, by the nature of the wound it is, that we can give the beſt gheſſe at the plaiſter. But now ſure I am ſome way elſe it was that <hi>Adam</hi> damnified us by his tranſgreſſion <hi>quàm ex ſola oſten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſione peccati,</hi> than only by opening a gap before us unto all lewdneſſe, and therefore queſtionleſſe ſome way elſe it was that Chriſt did benefit us now by his paſſion <hi>quàm ex ſola oſtenſione virtutum,</hi> than onely by chalking out a way before us unto all good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſe.</p>
                  <p>Why and ſo it was indeed: for the truth is Chriſt our Paſſeover (we may ſay) was ſacrificed for the remiſſion of our ſins, for our reconciliation with the Father, and, which followeth neceſſarily upon theſe two, for our redemption from hell. Whence elſe is it (I would faine know) that Chriſt his bloud in holy ſcripture, is ſtiled our ranſome, our attonement and the propitiation for our ſinnes? Is is not to make it plaine unto us, how that Chriſt his death here was as well expiatorie as exemplarie? and that Chriſt our Paſſeover was now ſlaine (we muſt know) as well <hi>ut daret juſtitiam,</hi> as <hi>ut doceret; as well ut infunderet charitatem,</hi> as <hi>ut oſtenderet? pro nobis redimendis,</hi> or (as it is in one of our Church her collects if you have obſerved it) that he might be a ſacrifice for ſinne,<note place="margin">2. Sunday after Eaſter.</note> as well as <hi>pro nobis inſtituendis,</hi> that he might be an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſample unto us of godly life?</p>
                  <p>But now if any ſhall queſtion us how Chriſt his death here could be the expiation of our ſinnes, and not rather intruth (being ſo execrable a ſacriledge as it was) a further aggravation of our guilt<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> it cannot
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:18407:39"/>bee improbable, ſince God was ſo highly offended with our firſt parents, and in them with the whole world, only for the eating of that forbidden fruit; that he hath farre greater cauſe (we muſt think) in all likelihood to bee much more enraged now againſt mankind for this ſo horrid, this ſo inhumane a mur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther acted upon the perſon of his only Sonne? For anſwer hereunto, know thus much, that Chriſt his death here, we ſay, was our attonement, not as out of malice and moſt unjuſtly it was procured by the Jewes, but as moſt obediently and in meere love it was taken upon him by himſelfe, Chriſt his charitie being of more force, we are ſure, to acquire and pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe for us Gods favour, than the ſpite &amp; rancour of the whole world could be to incenſe againſt us Gods wrath. To this purpoſe what ſaith S. <hi>Bernard</hi> in his 119. <hi>Epiſt.</hi> againſt <hi>Abailardus?</hi> Mary, <hi>Non mors</hi> (ſaith he) <hi>ſed voluntas placuit ſponte morientis:</hi> it was not ſimply death that did here ſo pleaſe God, but the will of him that ſo freely died, and that by death did both unſting death, and work ſalvation, and reſtore righteouſneſſe, and ranſack hell, &amp; enrich heaven, and vanquiſh principalities, and ſubdue powers, <hi>&amp; paci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficantis omnia quae in coelo ſunt &amp; quae in terra,</hi> and that did gather together in one all things both which are in heaven and which are in earth.</p>
                  <p>By all this it is moſt cleere and evident, as I ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe, that Chriſt was ſacrificed here for our good; yea for our good, not as ſome hell-bred hereticks have vented, of edification only and inſtruction, but of remiſſion alſo, and of reconciliation, and of redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion from hell. Yea but what then? is this all (you
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:18407:40"/>will ſay?) No marry is it not, you muſt know; this is not all yet: for what thinke you, I pray, of that in <hi>Virgil? Unum pro multis dabitur caput?</hi> Is it not a phraſe, I beſeech you, of the ſame force with <hi>unum multorum loco dabitur caput?</hi> What againe of that in <hi>Terence,</hi> I will marry thee for him? Is it not as much in every reſpect as if he had ſaid in other words, I will marrie thee in ſtead of him? In the 9. to the <hi>Rom.</hi> St. <hi>Paul</hi> wiſheth, that for his brethren he were cur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed: for his brethren doth he ſay? <hi>pro fratribus?</hi> that is, <hi>fratrum loco,</hi> in his brethrens place. Againe in the 2. to the <hi>Corinth.</hi> S. <hi>Paul</hi> tells us, how that for Chriſt wee are ambaſſadours: for Chriſt doth hee ſay? <hi>pro Chriſto?</hi> that is, <hi>Chriſti vice,</hi> in Chriſt his ſtead. But the truth is, if in this my text here Chriſt were not ſacrificed for us now in this ſenſe, how commeth it to paſſe then that by one of the Fathers he is ſaid <hi>noſtro nomine ſuſcipere ſupplicia?</hi> how, that by an other he is ſaid <hi>noſtra pro nobis luere debita?</hi> yea how commeth it to paſſe then that he is ſtiled <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the pledge and hoſtage for our ſoules? Doth not all this make plaine unto us what himſelfe hath taught us in S. <hi>Matthewes</hi> Goſpel, <hi>viz.</hi> that he did <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>; ſtake his ſoule downe in the roomth of ours, and ſo by conſequent that Chriſt was ſacrificed, we may ſay very well for us? for us? that is, <hi>vice noſtrâ,</hi> by way of commutation in our ſtead.</p>
                  <p>But now, that to be ſacrificed in our ſtead, is more than to be ſacrificed for our good, this is plaine, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe whereas hee that dieth for our good, may yet not die perhaps in our ſtead; on the other ſide he that
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:18407:40"/>dieth in our ſtead, cannot but die alſo for our good, we may be ſure we have even 'the whole army of noble Martyrs bearing witneſſe with us unto this truth, who all in their ſeverall orders having died for our good, yet amongſt them all, was there any one of them that ever died wee can ſay in our ſtead? No, <hi>acceperunt juſti, non dederunt coronas:</hi> how precious ſo ever all their deaths were in the ſight of their Creator, yet for all that (ſaith <hi>Leo</hi> in his 12. ſermon upon the paſſion) <hi>nullius inſontis occiſio propitiatio fuit mundi:</hi> the very beſt of them all could never ſay, how that he died in the behalf of the beleeving world. <hi>Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gulares in ſingulis mortes fuerunt,</hi> each man of them in particular died in particular to himſelfe alone. How rich ſo ever they all were in the gifts &amp; graces of the Spirit, yet <hi>hand alterius quiſquam debitum ſuo funere ſolvit,</hi> yet for all that could not any one of them un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dertake the ranſome of his enthralled brother. It was onely Chriſt (ſaith one) amongſt the ſonnes of men, in whom all of us wee may ſay did ſuffer; in whom all of us we may ſay were crucified, in whom all of us wee may ſay did die; Chriſt onely, Chriſt in whom all of us wee may ſay were ſlaine, and of whom therefore we may ſay very well how that he was ſacrificed here for us: for us? in our ſteed, as well as for us, for our good; for us, in our behalfe, as well as for us, for our behoofe.</p>
                  <p>Yea but why Chriſt thus for us (you will ſay?) why not we rather for our ſelves? <hi>Cum ſis ipſe no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cens moritur cur victima pro te?</hi> ſince wee men were they that had offended, why ſhould Chriſt an inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent thus die for us?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="76" facs="tcp:18407:41"/>Why? why not? If God had ſo determined, why not? <hi>Cum aliunde reatus, cur non aliunde juſtitia?</hi> ſince by another it was that we were ingaged, why by another alſo may we not be enlarged? <hi>An juſtitia juſti ſuper eum erit</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Bernard</hi>) <hi>&amp; impietas impii non erit ſuper eum?</hi> ſhall the righteouſneſſe of the righteous be upon him alone; and ſhall the wic<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kedneſſe of the wicked be not onely upon him, but upon us too? It was by <hi>Adam</hi> (you know) that wee were made ſinners, and why by Chriſt therefore may wee not be made righteous? It was by <hi>Adam</hi> (you know) that we were all addicted, and why by Chriſt therefore may wee not be all enfranchiſed? You will ſay, that <hi>Adam</hi> perhaps was our father: and what? was not Chriſt (I beſeech you) our brother? or is it equall (doe you thinke) that that ſonne who beareth the burden of his fathers ſin, ſhould yet be debarred from what ever benefit might accrue unto him from his brothers righteouſnes? Aſſure your ſelves, there is as great an efficacy in Chriſt his bloud, as in <hi>Adams</hi> ſeed; in Chriſt his bloud to cleanſe us, as in <hi>Adams</hi> ſeed to ſtaine us; in Chriſt his bloud for our purgati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as in <hi>Adams</hi> ſeed for our pollution. Indeed, were there betwixt Chriſt and us no manner relation at all, ſomewhat improbable then might it ſeem unto humane reaſon, that by meanes here of Chriſt his ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crifice, the wrath of God ſhould bee made to paſſe from us. But now, beſides the neerneſſe of Chriſt his conjunction unto us, <hi>naturâ, regno, vadimonio</hi> (hee being not only our brother, but even our king too; not only our king, but alſo our pledge:) beſides this (I ſay) what ſaith the Scripture (I beſeech you?)
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:18407:41"/>Mary, we are all in Chriſt (ſaith S. <hi>Paul</hi>) one body: ſo that there is as ſtraight an union betwixt us and Chriſt (you ſee) as betwixt the members and the head. But now it being ſo common a thing in the body naturall to puniſh one member for another; for inſtance, to brand the forehead for the tongues la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſhneſſe, and for the theft which the hand hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitted to ſcourge the back: why ſhould it ſeem un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable unto us, that in the body myſticall Chriſt our head ſhould die for us here? eſpecially too, Chriſt being not only willing (we are ſure) thus for our ſakes to undergoe death, not onely able by his owne ſtrength powerfully to raiſe up himſelfe againe from death, but by death alſo to overcome death, to purchaſe a life for us which ſhall never end in death, and, to the endleſſe praiſe of Gods boundleſſe glory, to ſave us from dying who muſt have died for ever elſe?</p>
                  <p>Well, you have ſeen at length (I ſuppoſe) what Chriſt hath done: What! yea, and for whom too. What he hath done, doe I ſay? what he ſuffered ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther; for, <hi>ſacrificatus eſt</hi> (you ſee) hee was ſacrificed, and needs muſt he ſuffer (I trow) even to deſtruction, whoſoever he is that ſhall be ſacrificed. Why, and to make it plaine unto us that Chriſt did ſo, ſome tranſlations read it therefore, He was ſlaine: <hi>Chriſtus Paſcha noſtrum immolatus eſt,</hi> Chriſt our Paſſeover (ſay they) is ſlaine. Hee was ſlaine (I ſay) and that not for himſelf (I ſhewed you) innocent Lamb that he was, not for himſelfe: no, nor yet for Angels, no, nor yet only for Jewes neither; but for Jewes and Gen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiles together: for Us, for Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> for Corinthi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:18407:42"/>for Circumciſed, for Uncircumciſed, for He<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brewes, for Greekes, <hi>Chriſt is ſacrificed</hi> (ſaith my Text) <hi>for us.</hi> For us, yea even for all of us, <hi>ſub con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditione</hi> (as wee ſay) <hi>&amp; in cauſa:</hi> for albeit in Chriſt none but the Elect were redeemed, yet was the whole world redeemed (ſaith my Lord of Sarum) by Chriſt: but for Us of the faithfull, Gods children, <hi>ſimpliciter</hi> (I told you) <hi>&amp; cum effectu:</hi> for <hi>us,</hi> by way of edification, <hi>noſtro commodo,</hi> for our good: for <hi>us,</hi> by way of expiation, <hi>noſtro loco,</hi> in our ſtead: for <hi>us, per viam confirmationis,</hi> for our profit and behoofe: for <hi>us, per viam ſurrogationis,</hi> in our perſon and be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>halfe. Let us paſſe now from what was done on Chriſt his part, unto what remaineth to bee done on ours; from the <hi>Beneficium</hi> unto the <hi>Officium,</hi> from the dogmaticall part of my Text unto the practicall, from the doctrine of faith, the <hi>Credendum,</hi> Chriſt his bounty to us upon Good-Friday, unto the rule of life, the <hi>Agendum,</hi> our duty to him now at Eaſter; yea let mee tell you againe not at Eaſter only, but during the whole courſe here of this our life.</p>
                  <p>One thing I am ſure of (however D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Kelliſon</hi> would beare the world in hand that wee teach the contrary) never the doctrine was it for ought I know, never the dreame (as yet) of any Church Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtant, that becauſe Chriſt on his part hath done ſo much for us, we from henceforth therefore need doe nought on ours. No, even <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, wee have all been taught (I hope) how that Chriſt was as well a Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phet as a Prieſt,<note place="margin">2 Tim. 3.15.</note> as well <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as well a Prophet to teach us our future duties,<note place="margin">Heb. 5.1.</note> as a Prieſt to ſatisfie for
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:18407:42"/>our paſſed debts: Even this my Text here doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince thus much, where the Apoſtle having taught us (you ſee) how that Chriſt was ſacrificed, yea and that he was ſacrificed too our Paſſeover, to the end that the wrath of God might be made to paſſe from us; doth he now leave it (can we ſay) unto our ſelves alone, to make what uſe we liſt of this ſo heavenly a doctrine which he hath delivered? doth he referre it wholly now unto our owne diſcretions only to paſſe by this ſo infinite mercy of God in what ſort wee pleaſe? No, that hee doth not: for as in the ſeventh Verſe he hath ſhewed us what concerning this point we are to beleeve, ſo now in the eight Verſe doth hee alſo informe (you ſee) how in conſideration hereof we are to live: as before in the preceding part of my Text by way of doctrine hee hath taught us what in love to us Chriſt did ſuffer, ſo now in that which followeth doth hee by way of uſe teach us what in thankfulneſſe unto Chriſt we muſt doe: <hi>viz.</hi> that in a gratefull acknowledgement of this his ſo un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable favour towards us, wee muſt from hence<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forth ſolemnly keep a feaſt: <hi>Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed, let us therefore</hi> (ſaith Saint <hi>Paul</hi>) <hi>keep the feaſt.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The word in the originall is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, which as well bids an holy-day (you muſt know) as indicts a feaſt, and every whit as properly by <hi>Tremelius</hi> is rendered <hi>feſtum celebremus,</hi> let us keep the holy-day, as by the vulgar Latine and ſome others <hi>epulemur,</hi> let us keep the feaſt. Our laſt Engliſh verſion reades it both waies, and not but upon very good grounds too doth it ſo reade it, it not being unknowne unto us
<pb n="80" facs="tcp:18407:43"/>how that both theſe waies men did ſolemnize a Paſſeover of old amongſt the Jewes: <hi>viz. Et feſtum celebrando, &amp; epulando,</hi> both by making a holy-day, and by keeping a feaſt too. Why, and in the name of God both theſe waies let us Chriſtians celebrate now this our Paſſeover; becauſe Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed, let us therefore keep an holy-day: becauſe Chriſt our Paſſeover is ſacrificed, let us therefore alſo keep a feaſt.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, <hi>feſtum celebremus,</hi> let us keep an holy-day, &amp; that by obſerving carefully an holy reſt, as from ſin every day, for never upon any day may we reſt in that (Chriſt for us being not therefore ſlaine now, that we from henceforth might live in ſinne) ſo upon all theſe and the like ſolemne holy-daies from all workes alſo of ſervile labour, from all worldly workes of what kind ſoever they be, which without notorious detri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment cannot be well forborne. Beſides what we may learne in this point even from very Heathens, whoſe ſeverall holy-daies (we find) they did count polluted, if after notice once given thereof <hi>per praeconem,</hi> a man upon any ſuch day was found at his worke: be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides this (I ſay) I pray tell mee,<note place="margin">B. Ely, Sab. pag. <hi>222.</hi>
                     </note> doth not a learned Prelate of ours, in a late elabourate Treatiſe of his, a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt ſundry other Kings lawes to this purpoſe, produce a law enacted by our owne <hi>Alured,</hi> that a freeman, if he wrought <hi>in quavis festa die,</hi> hee was either to be diveſted of this liberty, or to bee ſoundly fined for it; a ſervant either <hi>corium perdere,</hi> either to loſe his skin, or to redeem it with his coine? And no marvell truly, for even Gods owne law it is in <hi>Levi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticus</hi> 23. it is Gods owne law there (I ſay) that bid
<pb n="81" facs="tcp:18407:43"/>adieu we ſhould unto all worldly affaires upon all ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly-daies, that upon all holy-dayes (as the very name may prompt us to doe) wee ſhould forbeare to min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle our ſelves with what belongs to earth.</p>
                  <p>Not that it is Gods will that we ſhould now be i<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle (we may thinke) or paſſe the Holy-day away in doing nothing. No, <hi>qui nihil agit malè agit,</hi> he that doth nought muſt needs doe naught, we may bee ſure. Even very heathen people have ſeene thus much, though they had the light onely, God knowes, of blinde nature: and therefore amongſt the antient Romans the goddeſſe, it ſeemes, had no Temple al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed her within the City, but abroad elſewhere without the Wals, in ſome extreme parts of the Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>urbs; intimating unto us hereby, how that idleneſſe is a vice not tolerable in any State, as being indeed the undoubted mother of all ungodlineſſe and ſinne. But what now? will God ſuffer, doe you thinke, upon an holy-day, what is not to be endured, we may be ſure, upon any day? or is it an idle reſt, doe you thinke, that hee alwayes requireth at our hands, when upon ſuch daies as theſe are he interdicteth labour? wherein then, I wonder, would this our reſt differ even from the very reſt of our <hi>jumenta?</hi> from our oxe his reſt at the ſtall, and from our horſes reſt in the ſtable? for ſure I am, as well as wee, even they are to reſt al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo from all travell. It is recorded by <hi>Cato</hi> concer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning one of the <hi>Scipio's,</hi> how that he was never leſſe alone (he ſhould ſay) than when alone: and, <hi>Nun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quam minus otioſus quam cum otioſus,</hi> never leſſe idle than when he was idle. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, (ſaith a Divine, whom St. <hi>Baſil</hi> ſpeaks of) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, I know
<pb n="82" facs="tcp:18407:44"/>not what others may doe, but ſure am I, ſaith he, that I am never more buſied, than when I doe reſt: why, and never more buſied let us at any time bee, than when God doth call us, as here, to keep an holy-day; never more exerciſed, though neither in ſinfull nor ſecular affaires, yet in all ſuch workes as doe concerne the day.</p>
                  <p>Now what are they? Sure I am, not to madde and gad it up and downe the ſtreets, to ſir and ſmoake it in Tobacco ſhops, to roare and revell it in Tavernes, (and as it were in contempt of that deſtroying An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gel (whoſe ſword as yet, you fee, is not quite ſhea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thed) to lay purpoſely aſide all honeſt labour, that we may the more greedily proſtitute our ſelves unto all leud exceſſe? No, there are both lawes Imperiall, (I am ſure) and Eccleſiaſticall, ſtrictly reſtraining men from theſe exorbitancies; and that eſpecially too up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on all ſuch dayes, as for order and policie ſake we doe call Holy. And no marvell truly, for, <hi>Haeccine ſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lennes dies decent,</hi> ſaith <hi>Tertullran, quae alios dies non decent?</hi> or have we no other way, may we thinke, to make an holy-day, than by making our ſelves there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on the more unholy? Indeed, were they <hi>Liberalia</hi> which we doe now celebrate, were they daies dedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cated to the god of Riot, unto drunken <hi>Bacchus</hi> I meane, on whoſe ſeverall Feſtivals men might both ſpeake and doe, it ſeemes, what ever they liſted; then wonder I could not if that we did keepe theſe dayes now with farre more looſeneſſe than I hope we doe. But now, beſides that he is a ſober God whom wee are to worſhip now (as the Athenians ſaid ſometimes of their <hi>Minerva</hi>) a God who holds not libertie, I
<pb n="83" facs="tcp:18407:44"/>am ſure, to be piety, or occaſion of rioting to be reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion; neither ever did teach us, as yet, when we are to keep an holy-day, to expreſſe our publike joy by our publike ſhame. Beſides this, I ſay, I pray be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinke your ſelves, is not the feaſt we keepe now the feaſt of Paſſeover? Yes. But <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith Saint <hi>Gregory,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, the word <hi>Paſcha,</hi> ſaith hee, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ports a paſſing, as of that deſtroying Angel from o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the Iſraelites, ſo of the Iſraelites themſelves alſo from out of Egypt: why in the name of God then, if indeed your purpoſe be to keepe a true Paſchall holy-day now, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, yea and that too in ſuch a faſhi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, as whereby Gods deſtroying Angel may bee made to paſſe at length from us, why let us paſſe then with all diligence from what ever courſes heretofore we learned in Egypt, unto ſuch workes onely and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligious exerciſes, as ſhall beſt beſeeme (wee know) Gods own choſen Iſraelites, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, from workes of ſinne unto workes of grace, <hi>à rebus inferioribus ad ſuperiora,</hi> from workes of vanitie un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to workes of piety: and (that we may doe <hi>opiu diei in die ſuo,</hi> in it owne day the worke of the day) from the baſe drudgerie workes of the fleſh and divell, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to ſuch as are true holy-day works indeed.</p>
                  <p>Would you know what theſe workes are? Why, doe but uncaſe the word (I beſeech you) the Latine <hi>feriae</hi> (I meane) into its firſt ſwadling clothes, and you ſhall then finde, how that a right holy-day work is either <hi>ferire victimas,</hi> or <hi>ferre dona,</hi> you ſhall then finde how that a true holy-day worke, is either to ſlay our beaſts for ſacrifice, or to bring hither our gifts. One thing I am ſure of, both theſe works did
<pb n="84" facs="tcp:18407:45"/>the Jewiſh people heretofore upon their holy-daies, as unto men verſed any whit in ſacred ſtorie it is moſt evident and cleere. Why, and in the name of God (if we will keep the holy-day aright) both theſe works alſo let us doe on ours now: becauſe S. <hi>Paul</hi> his will is that wee ſhould keepe an holy-day, let us ſlay our beaſts therefore now for ſacrifice; becauſe Saint <hi>Paul</hi> his will it is that we ſhould keepe an holy-day, let us bring hither therefore now our gifts too.</p>
                  <p>Firſt let us <hi>ferire victimas,</hi> ſlay our beaſts for ſacri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fice: not thoſe beaſts wee doe read of in the law; no, I doe doubt very much how willing many of us would be to part in theſe dayes with ſuch beaſts as thoſe were; neither if we all were willing hath every one of us (can I thinke) any ſuch beaſts now to part with; neither if wee all had them, doth God now (I am ſure) require any ſuch beaſts at our hands. What ſay I? doth hee not require them, doe I ſay? nay, to ſpeake ſooth, hee doth now reject them; for <hi>ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crificia &amp; victimas noluiſti</hi> (ſaith <hi>David</hi>) as for all le<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gall ſacrifices (ſaith St. <hi>Paul</hi>) God will none of them now.<note place="margin">Pſal. 40.6. Heb. 10.5.</note> Indeed a time once there was, I muſt confeſſe, when God required ſuch beaſts (not for that he him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe then had the leaſt need of them; <hi>for the beaſts of the forreſt are mine all of them</hi> (ſaith God) <hi>and ſo are the cattell too upon a thouſand hills;</hi> and therefore, as S. <hi>Juſtine Martyr</hi> rightly, <hi>we can never think that any thing can bee wanting unto him who is Lord of all things:</hi>) why but yet at that very time was the ſlay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſacrificing of ſuch beaſts, only a ceremonie, no ſtanding law; only a ceremonie, I ſay, which had only <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as the name gives, no ſtanding
<pb n="85" facs="tcp:18407:45"/>law which was to reach unto us.</p>
                  <p>No? Was it not ſo, will ſome ſay? Why, what are thoſe beaſts then, we would know, that muſt be ſlain by us now (you tell us) upon this our holy-day?</p>
                  <p>Surely not the beaſts of our heards (you muſt un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtand) no, but the beaſts rather in our hearts, our unreaſonable affections, our brutiſh luſts, theſe e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpecially are the beaſts which wee muſt now downe with: theſe beaſts if we ſhall ſtill ſtable in us, though ſlay whole Hecatombs wee ſhould of thoſe other beaſts, yet when all comes to all, ſhall wee but keep a beaſtly holy-day (I dare ſay) a day no way pleaſing unto him that was now ſlaine for us. Theſe beaſts therefore let us now to pot with, though they bee never ſo deare unto us, let not our hand ſpare them: no, whether the hot petulant goat of carnall luſt it be, or the raſh head-ſtrong ram of unadviſed anger, yea or that proud unruly beaſt either (which I am afraid to meddle with almoſt, ſo generally foſtered is he (I ſee) both in towne and country, there being hardly that family amongſt us in the whole king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome where wee ſhall not heare him muttering and murmuring at ſome time or other either againſt Church or State:) would you that I ſhould name him unto you? Why, if I ſhall not offend then in ſo doing, it is that ſtiff-neck'd Bull (I meane) of—Diſcontent.</p>
                  <p>Now all theſe beaſts being thus ſlaine by us (as oh if it were Gods will that in truth they were) let us not by and by ſet up our reſt here, as if the whole worke now (wee thought) of the day were done: no, he that here gave himſelfe (yee ſee) to bee ſlaine our Paſſeover, doth expect oblations (wee muſt thinke)
<pb n="86" facs="tcp:18407:46"/>as well as ſacrifices, and lookes that in celebrating unto him this our holy-day, wee ſhould as well bring our gifts hither, as here ſlay our beaſts. One thing I am ſure of, as upon other feſtivals, ſo in par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular on this of ſweet bread, Gods expreſſe or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der it was,<note place="margin">Deut. 16.16.</note> that there ſhould not any man appeare before him with an empty hand. The people ſhall offer thee (ſaith the Prophet) in the 110. <hi>Pſalme</hi> (ſpeaking of theſe very times now under the Goſpel) <hi>oblationes voluntarias,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Ver. 3.</note> free-will offerings, <hi>in die vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis tuae,</hi> in the day of thy power; or (as <hi>Rivet</hi> and ſome others will have it) <hi>in die exercitus tui,</hi> in the day of thine army. But now in the whole compaſſe of the yeere, are there any daies, the daies ſo proper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly (we may ſay) of Chriſt his power, yea and <hi>dies exercitus</hi> too, <hi>&amp; copiarum ejus,</hi> the daies, in truth, of his hoſts and armies, as are theſe very daies, when in the like places to this, the ſelected bands of Chriſt his Church doe troop together thus, ſolemnly to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>memorate that moſt ſtupendious act of Chriſt his power, in moſt powerfully raiſing up himſelfe from the dead? In any caſe then let us not faile to manifeſt our ſelves a moſt willing people unto Chriſt now up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on theſe daies; upon theſe daies (I ſay) theſe ſolemn holy-daies, theſe daies of Chriſt his army, theſe daies of Chriſt his power. And that as by bringing hither unto him that <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that which of all other gifts is indeed the beſt, the hallowed oblation of a good in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tention, offered upon the unſtained altar of an honeſt heart (for the ſacrifice of God is the heart (ſaith <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vid</hi>) and what ever gift wee ſhall bring him without the heart, it will but prove ominous at length &amp; pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>digious,
<pb n="87" facs="tcp:18407:46"/>as did that heartleſſe ſacrifice ſometimes of King <hi>Pyrrhus;</hi>) ſo becauſe the intentions of the heart are ſeldome reall (wee may be ſure) where they doe not expreſſe themſelves (when time ſerves) by the outward act; even by the word of the mouth when it hath meanes and opportunity ſo to doe, yea and when it hath meanes and opportunity ſo to doe, by the hand too: (for, for mine owne part I have ever held (I muſt tell you) their reaſons to be as brainleſſe, as their religion is heartleſſe (I feare) who in excuſe of their unbended knees, and unbared heads in Divine Service, doe alledge Gods acceptance onely of the heart:) for this cauſe therefore (I ſay) together with the incenſe of our hearts, let us bring hither the calves alſo of our lips, lauding and praiſing Gods name in this great celebrity of ours, as for that we do yet live, here to aſſemble our ſelves, when ſo many (you ſee) on either hand of us have this yeere bin ſwept away; ſo for that we can aſſemble our ſelves here to magni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fie him for his infinite mercies towards us in Chriſt Jeſus, ſlaine of purpoſe that hee might be a Paſchal ſacrifice (you ſee) for Us, who never had one before, even for Us. This unvalued mercy of his, let us ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ceaſe to ſet forth, never at any time forget to ſpeake of, eſpecially not at this time, when to this very purpoſe (you ſee) we are to keep the holy-day, that as the word <hi>feriae</hi> imports, wee might <hi>fari,</hi> here ſpeake of theſe things unto God his praiſe. Yea, but what then? Will it ſerve the turne (will ſome ſay) if we doe bring hither unto God our lips only? or may we put God off (may we thinke) with a bare lip-gift alone, as the King of Cowlam (they ſay) doth his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>god?</p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="88" facs="tcp:18407:47"/>Beloved, <hi>Nequam verbum eſt</hi> (as hee in <hi>Plautus</hi> ſaith well) <hi>bene vult, niſi qui bene facit;</hi> and therefore becauſe hee that accepts the will for the deed when nought but the will can be had, doth yet expect the hand with the lips, when men may give the hand; for this cauſe therefore (I ſay) let as many of you as God hath given hands unto as well as lips, preſent God now, as with the calves of your lips, ſo with the very beſt &amp; choiceſt fruits alſo of your hands: imparting liberally <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and according every man unto what hath been lent you by God, ſomewhat <hi>Aris Dei,</hi> unto the repairing and beautifying (I meane) of decayed Churches, Chriſt his manſions; ſomewhat <hi>Charis Dei,</hi> unto the reliefe and ſuccour (I meane) of diſtreſſed Chriſtians, Chriſt his mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers; and that as for his ſake, by whoſe onely merit it is that we are already paſſed from wrath to grace, ſo for his ſervice too, by whoſe only power it will be that wee ſhall hereafter paſſe from death to glory, there <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> (that I may ſpeake in <hi>Damaſcens</hi> phraſe) <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, there to keep with Chriſt an everlaſting holy-day, throughout all eternitie in the heavens; whither he bring us all who hath dear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly bought us all, even Jeſus Chriſt the righteous: to whom, with the Father and the Holy Ghoſt, be aſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed (as moſt due is) all honour, and glory, and praiſe, and power, and dominion, from this time forth and for evermore. <hi>Amen, Amen.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
         <text xml:lang="eng">
            <front>
               <div type="title_page">
                  <pb facs="tcp:18407:47"/>
                  <p>A SERMON, PREACHED IN <hi>S. PAULS</hi> CHURCH IN LONDON, BY <hi>JOHN SQUIER</hi> PRIEST, Vicar of Saint <hi>Leonard</hi> Shordich, in MIDDLESEX.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed by ROBERT YOUNG, for <hi>Humfrey Blunden,</hi> 1637.</p>
               </div>
               <div type="dedication">
                  <pb n="90" facs="tcp:18407:48"/>
                  <head>To the moſt worthy paire of moſt religious perſons, Sir <hi>Alexander Saint-John,</hi> and his vertuous Lady.</head>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>His <hi>Text</hi> and <hi>Sermon</hi> doth <hi>exhort</hi> to <hi>good workes.</hi> It is my riches, that even in my poore Pariſh there are ſome, who <hi>preach</hi> this <hi>exhortation</hi> better by their <hi>practice,</hi> than I enforce it by my <hi>preaching:</hi> of whom (be it ſpoken without either diſparaging them, or flatte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring you) yee are the chiefe. This hath been long <hi>prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in my thought,</hi> and now my <hi>thought</hi> is <hi>printed:</hi> I account it a maine branch of my happy content, that I have two ſuch choſen people, ſo zealous of <hi>good works,</hi> living under my miniſtery. And that you may long live <hi>So,</hi> and <hi>There,</hi> by the increaſe of Gods <hi>Grace,</hi> and to the increaſe of Gods <hi>Glory,</hi> is the perpetuall prayer of him, who is</p>
                  <closer>
                     <signed>Yours in our Jeſus, JOHN SQUIER.</signed>
                  </closer>
               </div>
            </front>
            <body>
               <div type="sermon">
                  <pb n="91" facs="tcp:18407:48"/>
                  <head>A SERMON PREACHED IN St. PAULS CHURCH IN <hi>LONDON.</hi>
                  </head>
                  <epigraph>
                     <bibl>
                        <hi>MATTH. 5.16.</hi>
                     </bibl>
                     <q>Let your light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee your good workes, and glorifie your Father which is in heaven.</q>
                  </epigraph>
                  <p>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>Hat <hi>Citie</hi> of <hi>Antioch, Acts.</hi> 11.26. doth in ſome ſort reſemble this <hi>Text:</hi> from this <hi>place</hi> are the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vants of our Saviour <hi>firſt</hi> and prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cipally <hi>called Chriſtians.</hi> For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever as there was in <hi>Logicke,</hi> al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>though there bee in <hi>Theologicke,</hi> a continuall contention betwixt the <hi>Realls</hi> and <hi>Nomi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalls;</hi> yet doe I <hi>really</hi> ſide with, and <hi>ex animo</hi> ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe
<pb n="92" facs="tcp:18407:49"/>to the former. Our <hi>talkative Chriſtians,</hi> who are like the <hi>Nightingale, Vox &amp; praeterea nihil,</hi> no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing but <hi>voice,</hi> I deeme them and doome them fit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter for the <hi>cage</hi> than the <hi>Church, ſing they never ſo melodiouſly.</hi> But I hope and pray that we may learne Chriſt otherwiſe from this <hi>text.</hi> This <hi>text</hi> is <hi>Chriſt</hi> his <hi>Inſtitution</hi> of a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> which conſiſteth <hi>in do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing</hi> the <hi>deeds</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity.</hi> The <hi>deeds</hi> of <hi>Chriſtia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity</hi> are here deſcribed by the <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Forme</hi> thereof. The <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> is here called
<list>
                        <item>1. <hi>literally, Good workes:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. <hi>metaphorically, Light.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> The <hi>Forme</hi> of <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> followeth, in following the <hi>metaphor,</hi> and that in three particulars: <hi>Good workes</hi> muſt <hi>ſhine,</hi> they muſt be <hi>ſeene,</hi> and they muſt be <hi>ſhowne.</hi>
                     <list>
                        <item>1. <hi>Good workes</hi> being termed <hi>light,</hi> wee know that <hi>light, lucerna</hi> is of <hi>light eſteeme</hi> if it be not <hi>lighted:</hi> my Text ſaith therefore that <hi>good workes</hi> muſt <hi>ſhine:</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>2. a <hi>light</hi> that is <hi>lighted,</hi> and doth <hi>ſhine,</hi> yet it may bee kept in a <hi>cloſet,</hi> or <hi>put under a buſhell:</hi> the <hi>Ubi</hi> or proper place of the <hi>candle</hi> is a <hi>candle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſticke;</hi> it followeth therefore, our <hi>good workes</hi> muſt ſhine <hi>before men, that they may ſee them.</hi>
                        </item>
                        <item>3. Though a <hi>candle</hi> doe <hi>ſhine before men, and men doe ſee it,</hi> yet if it bee ſo <hi>placed,</hi> that a man cannot ſee to <hi>write,</hi> or <hi>read,</hi> or <hi>worke</hi> that which doth <hi>principally</hi> concerne him, he is deprived of the <hi>principall benefit</hi> thereof: wherefore the remnant of my Text ſheweth that a Chriſtian muſt apply this <hi>Candle of his ſoule</hi> to the <hi>eye</hi> of his <hi>ſoule,</hi> that he may <hi>ſee</hi> to doe the grand <hi>worke</hi> of his <hi>ſoule, to Honour his God; that they may glorifie his Father which is in heaven.</hi>
                        </item>
                     </list> Thus doth <hi>Chriſt</hi> inſtruct every one to be a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> how to doe <hi>Bonum,</hi> and
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18407:49"/>that <hi>benè,</hi> thereby to become <hi>bonus. Our light</hi> muſt <hi>ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good workes, and glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi> Now that <hi>God</hi> give us <hi>His grace,</hi> that wee may give him <hi>That glory.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Undertaking this heavenly worke of heavenly <hi>e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dification,</hi> conſider wee firſt the <hi>Materials</hi> thereof, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>your good workes.</hi> If <hi>Chriſtianity</hi> bee not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, that <hi>Chriſtian</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, an Idlesby in that building: becauſe meere <hi>knowledge</hi> is to greater <hi>dam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation, Luk.</hi> 12.47. and meere <hi>knowledge</hi> is in the <hi>damned,</hi> in the <hi>divell, Luk.</hi> 4.10. <hi>Omnes Grae cinorunt quid ſit honeſtum, ſoli Lacedaemonii faciunt quod eſt honeſtum: All Chriſtians Know, true Chriſtians Doe Chriſtianity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>fruit</hi> doth ſhew the <hi>tree, Luk.</hi> 6.44. a <hi>good man</hi> like the <hi>good tree Pſal.</hi> 1. doth bring forth his <hi>fruit in due ſeaſon;</hi> like the <hi>tree of life, Rev.</hi> 22. <hi>in many ſea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons:</hi> yea like the <hi>tree in Alcinous</hi> his <hi>orchard,</hi> in <hi>eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry ſeaſon. Aarons rod</hi> did not <hi>onely bloome.</hi> Philoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phy ſaith <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>felicity</hi> is <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>operation,</hi> not <hi>ſpeculation:</hi> and the <hi>Moraliſts,</hi> that their <hi>Art</hi> is not <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, but <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, not an <hi>affection</hi> but an <hi>action.</hi> Nature frameth men with <hi>ten fingers</hi> to <hi>one tongue:</hi> but wee invert it, <hi>Oraque centum,</hi> like <hi>Stentor,</hi> wee <hi>open our mouths wide,</hi> when wee ſhould <hi>open our hands wide, Deut.</hi> 15.11. But ſurely they are <hi>no excellent ſervants</hi> who will <hi>onely weare the Livery;</hi> therefore, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Chriſt</hi> ſaith, <hi>Chriſtians</hi> muſt <hi>doe</hi> the workes of <hi>Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtianity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Such as are <hi>Chriſtians</hi> muſt <hi>doe the works of Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>anity: and good Chriſtians good workes.</hi> What? <hi>abſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lutely
<pb n="93" facs="tcp:18407:50"/>good workes?</hi> No, I abſolutely deny that. <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: <hi>Sanctum non eſt quod geritur ſanctum, niſi ſanctè quod ſanctum eſt peragitur: Dew attendit tum actum, tum affectum,</hi> ſaith St. <hi>Cy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prian.</hi> Where there are <hi>good works</hi> in <hi>perfection,</hi> there muſt be both a <hi>perfect action externall,</hi> and <hi>perfect af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection internall.</hi> But <hi>quis idoneus ad haec?</hi> liveth the man that dareth ſay he can diſcharge it? Alas, alas, we have <hi>many commiſsions, more omiſsions:</hi> In the moſt <hi>vigilant Chriſtian, Gregories</hi> two wormes will eat out the <hi>core</hi> and <hi>cor</hi> of his moſt <hi>hearitie action: ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perbia aut deſidia,</hi> either <hi>ſloath</hi> in them, or <hi>pride</hi> of them, will conſtraine the beſt Chriſtian to ponder the <hi>terminus diminuens,</hi> remaining: <hi>opera bona Noſtra,</hi> they are <hi>Our good workes,</hi> and therefore <hi>blemiſhed</hi> in their <hi>goodneſse.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Chriſt doth, and Chriſtians may call their <hi>workes, good workes:</hi> for they are wrought <hi>out</hi> of a <hi>good mat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> the holy <hi>Scriptures,</hi> 1 <hi>Sam.</hi> 15.22. <hi>by a good effi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cient,</hi> the holy <hi>Spirit, Joh.</hi> 15.5. and <hi>to a good end,</hi> to hallow Gods holy <hi>name,</hi> in my <hi>text</hi> for this day, and in our <hi>prayer</hi> for every day. <hi>Primitively,</hi> our <hi>workes</hi> are <hi>pure,</hi> are cleere in the <hi>fountaine;</hi> but <hi>derivatively</hi> muddie and <hi>dirtie</hi> in the <hi>channell</hi> and <hi>kennell</hi> of our performance. If once they be <hi>Our workes,</hi> Our God doth know it, and hath ſaid it, <hi>All our righteouſneſſe is but as filthy ragges, Iſai.</hi> 64.6. This is enough to <hi>vilifie</hi> our beſt <hi>actions,</hi> and to <hi>humble</hi> our beſt <hi>affecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons,</hi> that they are called <hi>bona opera Noſtra, Our good workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Paſſing the <hi>dignitie,</hi> proceed we to the <hi>neceſsity</hi> of our <hi>good workes,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Let your light ſhine. Chriſt
<pb n="95" facs="tcp:18407:50"/>is Imperative,</hi> and <hi>Christians</hi> are <hi>Optative,</hi> that they may be <hi>Potentiall,</hi> and <hi>Indicative, manifeſtly</hi> and <hi>pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erfully</hi> to ſtop the <hi>mouths</hi> of ignorant malitious peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, by <hi>our good workes,</hi> and godly con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation, 1 <hi>Pet.</hi> 2.15. I will not cramme your atten<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion with that <hi>Crambe,</hi> thoſe common Scriptures for <hi>good workes,</hi> obvious to our <hi>Children</hi> and <hi>Catechiſts,</hi> to our <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> to our very Novices in Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion: onely I will appeale to all your memories, that all the Patriarchs, Prophets, Apoſtles, Diſciples, Martyrs, Fathers, Confeſſors, and ſound Profeſſors, did ever ſtrive to <hi>practiſe</hi> that <hi>opus ſidei,</hi> that <hi>worke of faith,</hi> 1 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 1.3. and to <hi>walke</hi> in that <hi>narrow</hi> way to heaven, which is paved with <hi>good workes.</hi> For my part, I am through, that thoſe who goe not in this <hi>via,</hi> ſhall never attaine that <hi>patria.</hi> Though <hi>Ben<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nard ſaw not A'll,</hi> yet hee <hi>ſaw enough in this point,</hi> and they are <hi>blinde Bayards,</hi> who be ſo <hi>bold</hi> as to gain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſay it. I am tranſported with this point, and as it were tranſlated by this point, into a <hi>pilgrimage</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards <hi>heaven:</hi> like that of <hi>Jacob</hi> to <hi>Padan Aram, Gen.</hi> 28. me thinketh I have a <hi>viſion</hi> of a <hi>ladder rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching to heaven,</hi> and a <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>multitude</hi> of the <hi>ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fects of good workes,</hi> as <hi>Angels aſcending and deſcen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding,</hi> as <hi>meſſengers</hi> to tell us, that we ſhall climbe the <hi>ladder, where God ſtandeth at the top thereof.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 At the <hi>foot, below</hi> the foot of that <hi>ladder, lieth Man:</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, yea, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. Before <hi>Hell</hi> was, we were prevented from <hi>Hell,</hi> and <hi>elected</hi> into <hi>Heaven</hi> in <hi>Chriſt Jeſus.</hi> The <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <hi>Charter</hi> of our enfranchiſment is in <hi>Gods Predeſtination:</hi> the <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap> or <hi>counterpane</hi> thereof, is in <hi>our owne Converſation.</hi> By
<pb n="96" facs="tcp:18407:51"/>
                     <hi>doing good workes,</hi> we may and muſt <hi>make our election ſure,</hi> 2 <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10.</p>
                  <p n="2">2 In the <hi>fall</hi> of <hi>Adam, we, all Adamites, fell into Hell. Titiones ab incendio,</hi> out of which <hi>fire</hi> we are ſnatched by our bleſſed <hi>Redeemer: our good workes</hi> are the <hi>fruits</hi> and <hi>ſignes</hi> of that our bleſſed <hi>redemp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</hi> For if we <hi>be the children of Abraham,</hi> we will <hi>doe</hi> the <hi>deeds of Abraham, Joh.</hi> 8.39.</p>
                  <p n="3">3 As we were <hi>Titiones ab incendio,</hi> ſo that wee be not <hi>Titiones ad incendium:</hi> that wee doe not <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lapſe</hi> to our <hi>ruine;</hi> but that we are <hi>aſſured</hi> that we are <hi>juſtified,</hi> and ſhalbe <hi>glorified.</hi> The <hi>evidence</hi> of this <hi>aſſurance</hi> is given by the <hi>Spirit Cauſativè,</hi> by way of <hi>operation:</hi> but it ariſeth alſo from <hi>our workes, effectivè,</hi> by way of <hi>declaration.</hi> If <hi>wee keepe Gods Commandements, we dwell in him, and hee in us: and herehy we know that hee abideth in us,</hi> 1 <hi>Joh.</hi> 3.24.</p>
                  <p n="4">4 That we are <hi>elected, redeemed, juſtified,</hi> yea and <hi>Glorified</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, according to the <hi>firſt fruits,</hi> and gracious <hi>fore feeling</hi> thereof. Wee muſt render our <hi>regale vectigal:</hi> our <hi>thankfulneſſe</hi> muſt bee our <hi>tribute</hi> to <hi>God,</hi> for that wee are made <hi>Citizens</hi> and <hi>Subjects</hi> of his <hi>Kingdome.</hi> And our <hi>thanks</hi> muſt be by our <hi>deeds,</hi> we muſt <hi>gratias agere; gratias dicere</hi> is no phraſe. Like <hi>Cinaetus</hi> to his King, we muſt ſay, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>. When <hi>we have done what wee can, wee are but unprofitable ſervants, Luke</hi> 17.10: Though we ſhall be <hi>unprofitable,</hi> yet muſt we not be <hi>unthankfull ſervants:</hi> and by our <hi>good workes</hi> wee muſt <hi>declare</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="5">5 True <hi>thankfulneſſe for our benefits,</hi> doth alwaies produce true <hi>love</hi> to our <hi>benefactour.</hi> Now this <hi>love</hi>
                     <pb n="97" facs="tcp:18407:51"/>muſt not be <hi>Gyges,</hi> to walke <hi>inconſpicuous;</hi> nor an <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dombezech,</hi> to have no <hi>Fingers;</hi> nor like <hi>Logick,</hi> may it be <hi>clutcht-fiſted,</hi> but like <hi>Rhetorike,</hi> it muſt be <hi>open handed. Love</hi> doth dwell at the <hi>ſigne</hi> of the <hi>open hand,</hi> and the <hi>motto</hi> is <hi>bona opera veſtra, Your good workes.</hi> If <hi>we love Chriſt, we will keepe his commande<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments, Joh.</hi> 14 21.</p>
                  <p n="6">No ſervant to <hi>Love: Love</hi> there fore is <hi>Obe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient;</hi> and <hi>Obedience</hi> is the <hi>foundation</hi> of my Text. I am <hi>Obedient</hi> to my Creator, ſaith every <hi>Creature: Tu loquere, ut te videam. Shew it by thy works,</hi> ſaith Chriſt to us <hi>Chriſtians;</hi> and we Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans ſhould anſwer our Chriſt, as the Iſraelites did <hi>Moſes, All that the Lord hath ſpoken will wee doe, Exod.</hi> 19.8.</p>
                  <p n="7">7 But our <hi>conſciences, mille teſtes,</hi> a great <hi>cloud of witneſſes,</hi> complaine <hi>to Us, of Us,</hi> that wee have not returned thoſe <hi>thanks,</hi> nor imbraced that <hi>love,</hi> nor expreſſed that <hi>obedience</hi> to our bleſſed Creator. It ſtandeth us then in hand to <hi>repent</hi> us of thoſe notori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous Omiſſions. But what is <hi>repentance?</hi> onely <hi>mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tification,</hi> and <hi>vivification;</hi> a <hi>putting off the old man,</hi> and <hi>a putting on the new man, Epheſ.</hi> 4.22. &amp; 24. that is, the eſchewing of <hi>evill workes,</hi> and the inſuing of <hi>good workes.</hi> We ſay we <hi>repent,</hi> how doe we ſhew it? It is poſſible, that all our <hi>geſtures, poſtures, ſighs, prayers,</hi> and <hi>profeſsion,</hi> may be but <hi>Domeſtici teſtes, partiall falſe witneſſes,</hi> or vaine-glorious <hi>Pſeudo-Mar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tyrs. Deus teſtis;</hi> that we doe truely <hi>repent</hi> (if wee be not rotten hypocrites) our <hi>good workes</hi> before God and man will <hi>witneſſe</hi> it.</p>
                  <p n="8">8 Next, no <hi>repentance!</hi> no <hi>faith.</hi> Theſe <hi>twinnes,</hi> like thoſe of <hi>Hippocrates,</hi> will thrive or pine to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether.
<pb n="98" facs="tcp:18407:52"/>Theſe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>Day ſtarres,</hi> will riſe and ſet in the ſame minute. Like <hi>Ruth</hi> and <hi>Naomi,</hi> they will <hi>live and die together.</hi> A carnall <hi>neglect</hi> of <hi>good workes</hi> will kill them both. But for <hi>faith!</hi> a <hi>wording</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſour (as the Harlot uſed her Infant, 1 <hi>King.</hi> 3.16) doth <hi>ſmother</hi> it, and take away the <hi>breath</hi> of it. For as the <hi>bodie</hi> without <hi>breath</hi> is <hi>dead,</hi> ſo <hi>faith</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out <hi>works</hi> is <hi>dead</hi> alſo, <hi>James</hi> 2.26.</p>
                  <p n="9">9 If our <hi>faith faile,</hi> it is fit that we ſhould fall to our <hi>prayers: Lord increaſe our faith, Luk.</hi> 17.5. <hi>Our prayers</hi> are <hi>heavie,</hi> like <hi>Moſes hand:</hi> wee cannot <hi>hold them up</hi> againſt braving <hi>Amalek,</hi> againſt our bold temptations: our <hi>goods workes</hi> are <hi>Hur</hi> and <hi>Aaron</hi> to ſupport them. <hi>Our prayers</hi> are <hi>Sagittae Salutis,</hi> 2 <hi>King.</hi> 13.17. the <hi>arrowes</hi> of <hi>ſalvation: goods works,</hi> are our <hi>Eliſha,</hi> to teach us to <hi>ſhoote. Good workes</hi> are the <hi>feathers</hi> to thoſe <hi>arrowes,</hi> which make them <hi>flie as high as heaven;</hi> and, like <hi>Jonathans Bow, never to turn back emptie,</hi> but ever to bring a bleſſing with them. A voice was heard from Heaven, ſaying, <hi>Thy prayers and thine almes are come up for a memoriall before God, Act.</hi> 10.4.</p>
                  <p n="10">10 Yea <hi>good works</hi> are not onely <hi>helps of prayers,</hi> but they are <hi>prayers</hi> alſo. I conceive <hi>prayers</hi> to bee <hi>vocall ſacrifices,</hi> and <hi>ſacrifices</hi> to bee <hi>reall prayers.</hi> Now <hi>good works are ſacrifices:</hi> therefore <hi>prayers.</hi> I diſpute not the diſtinctions, whether <hi>good workes</hi> be <hi>ſacrificia propitiatoria,</hi> ſacrifices to aſſwage Gods vengeance for our tranſgreſsions; by our <hi>pietie</hi> for our <hi>ſacriledge,</hi> or by our <hi>charitie</hi> for our <hi>avarice:</hi> whether <hi>goods works</hi> bee <hi>ſacrificia impetrantia,</hi> to beg a bleſsing upon our King and kingdome, upon our families and perſons: or whether they be onely
<pb n="99" facs="tcp:18407:52"/>
                     <hi>ſacri ficia Euchariſtica,</hi> the tribute of our <hi>thankfulnes.</hi> But this I know; <hi>our good workes</hi> are <hi>ſacrifices,</hi> true <hi>ſacrifices, ſacrifices wherewith God is pleaſed,</hi> yea <hi>well pleaſed.</hi> For S. <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>To do good and to com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>municate forget not, for with ſuch ſacrifices is God well pleaſed, Heb.</hi> 13.16.</p>
                  <p n="11">11 Hereunto will I be bold to annex a <hi>tranſcendent goodneſſe of good workes.</hi> I muſt ſpeake it truely, you muſt heare it cautelouſly. <hi>Good workes doe purge us from our ſins.</hi> I tranſgreſſe little from the phraſe, no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing from the ſenſe of S. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.22. <hi>We purifie our ſelves in obeying the truth.</hi> Indeed this property of <hi>purging ſinnes, properly,</hi> by way of <hi>redemption,</hi> is peculiar to the prerogative of <hi>Chriſt:</hi> the <hi>blood of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt doth cleanſe us from all our ſins,</hi> ſaith S. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1. <hi>Joh.</hi> 1.7. but <hi>inſtrumentally,</hi> and by way of <hi>mortifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation,</hi> and repreſsing our concupiſcence: as it is men<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tioned by S. <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Col.</hi> 3.5. we may aſcribe this <hi>good worke</hi> to <hi>good workes. By mercy and truth iniquitie is purged, Pro.</hi> 16.6. I will therefore preſume to the beſt man under this roofe, under heaven, to come neer and ſay, <hi>Father, goe to Jordan, waſh and be cleane. Cleanſe your ſelves by good workes,</hi> and a godly converſation.</p>
                  <p n="12">12 We are Gods <hi>ſervants;</hi> do our fraile appetites in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vite us be <hi>hirelings?</hi> will <hi>mercinarie</hi> motives make us to <hi>be good?</hi> to <hi>do good?</hi> our <hi>good works</hi> ſhall produce a <hi>good reward,</hi> a double <hi>reward,</hi> yea a treble, <hi>tempo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall, ſpirituall and eternall,</hi> 1 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. Doe not cen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, nor ſuſpect this doctrine for <hi>Popiſh</hi> and imply<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>merites:</hi> no, out of my judgement, not affection, I abhorre all <hi>Popery,</hi> and of all <hi>Popery</hi> I abhorre this <hi>Hereſie,</hi> that proud preſumptuous point of <hi>Merits.</hi> But that <hi>good workes</hi> ſhall have their <hi>remard<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> it is
<pb n="100" facs="tcp:18407:53"/>Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> doctrine, <hi>Hebr.</hi> 11.6. and wee have Saint <hi>Pauls</hi> diſtinction to cleere it from <hi>Popery, Rom.</hi> 4.4. our <hi>reward ſhall be of Grace,</hi> not of <hi>Debt,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, ſaith S. <hi>Baſil:</hi> and S. <hi>Ambroſe</hi> ſeemeth to ſpeake the ſame ſentence in Latine, <hi>Donum liberalitatis, non ſtipendium vir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tutis;</hi> a <hi>reward</hi> proceeding from the <hi>benignity</hi> of the <hi>rewarder,</hi> not from the <hi>dignity</hi> of the <hi>rewarded:</hi> hee can be no way <hi>meritorious. I have heard that power belongeth unto God, and that thou, Lord, art mercifull: for thou rewardeſt every man according to his worke, Pſal.</hi> 62.12.</p>
                  <p n="13">13 Moreover, the <hi>good workes</hi> of <hi>good Chriſtians,</hi> ſhall have a <hi>reward</hi> according to the <hi>proportion</hi> of their <hi>goodneſſe. He which ſoweth ſparingly, ſhall reap ſparingly: and hee which ſoweth bountifully, ſhall reap bountifully<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 2. Cor. 9.6. They that be wiſe, ſhall ſhine as the brightneſſe of the firmament; but they that turne many to righteouſneſſe, as the ſtarres for ever and ever, Dan.</hi> 12.3. The <hi>patient Innocents</hi> which ſtart not, and ſhrinke not at the groundleſſe and endleſſe bark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of black-mouth'd <hi>ſlaunderers; They</hi> are <hi>bleſſed,</hi> and commanded joyfully to expect the <hi>augmentation</hi> of their <hi>bleſsings.</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, a <hi>reward,</hi> even a <hi>great reward</hi> in the <hi>Kingdome of Heaven, Math.</hi> 5.11.12.</p>
                  <p n="14">14 Theſe many points are ſo many ſtems, ſpring<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing from one ſtalke, <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>: the <hi>love of our ſelves, to our ſelves.</hi> There remaine two maine motives; whereof the one is <hi>comparable</hi> to any of theſe, the other <hi>ſuperlative</hi> to all of theſe: <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, and <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, our <hi>love</hi> to our <hi>brethren</hi> on earth, and our <hi>love</hi> to our <hi>Father</hi> in heaven; to <hi>edifie them,</hi> and to <hi>glorifie him,</hi> both in the Text. To <hi>draw men to Chriſt</hi> is <hi>Gods</hi> rov<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all
<pb n="101" facs="tcp:18407:53"/>
                     <hi>Prerogative, John</hi> 6.44. therefore to <hi>communicate</hi> this to <hi>Us,</hi> muſt be a rare <hi>priviledge</hi> for ſuch mortall miſerable creatures. But <hi>exempla trahunt mores, ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>emplary good workes</hi> are an <hi>adamant,</hi> very <hi>attractive,</hi> and <hi>they</hi> are <hi>(not iron)</hi> of a heavie diſpoſition, who will not follow them. <hi>Good workes</hi> doe <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, <hi>draw men,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, they make <hi>nolentem volentem,</hi> ſuch as are <hi>backward</hi> to religion, to become <hi>forward</hi> in religion: Thus <hi>homo generat hominem, one good worke</hi> doth produce another. <hi>Good workes</hi> are <hi>neceſſary</hi> to bee done by <hi>good men,</hi> that by their <hi>example</hi> they may <hi>edifie</hi> their <hi>brethren.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="15">15 Theſe many fore-named <hi>motives to,</hi> and <hi>effects of good workes,</hi> are as ſo many <hi>ſtarres,</hi> which impart <hi>light to us,</hi> and exerciſe their <hi>influence</hi> on us, to make our <hi>ſoules vegetative,</hi> to grow from grace to grace, to be fertile and fruitfull in <hi>good workes.</hi> Or like <hi>thoſe ſtarres,</hi> the <hi>ſeptem Triones,</hi> they are brave <hi>directions</hi> to us towards our <hi>haven,</hi> our <hi>heaven:</hi> and happy are thoſe holy Chriſtians, who can ſteere thither through an <hi>ocean</hi> of good actions.</p>
                  <p>And this laſt, our <hi>exemplary piety,</hi> and <hi>charity</hi> to <hi>edifie</hi> our <hi>brethren,</hi> like the <hi>ſtarre</hi> of the <hi>Epiphanie,</hi> it doth as it were <hi>ſtand over the houſe,</hi> and directly di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rect us to this <hi>command</hi> of <hi>Chriſt,</hi> as that <hi>ſtarre</hi> did thoſe <hi>Magi</hi> to the <hi>perſon</hi> of <hi>Chriſt.</hi> Or <hi>ſicut inter ſtel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>las Luna minores,</hi> like the <hi>Moone, it ſhineth brightly,</hi> that we may <hi>ſee the way to heaven,</hi> in this <hi>night</hi> of our <hi>ignorance,</hi> and imperfect underſtanding. And, as the <hi>Aſtrologers</hi> teach of the <hi>Moone,</hi> it doth <hi>rule the head,</hi> and imploieth the <hi>braines</hi> in holy meditations, to compaſſe an holy converſation.</p>
                  <p>But the <hi>motive behind is before</hi> them <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ll in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#PDCC" extent="1 span">
                        <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="102" facs="tcp:18407:54"/>incitement: like the <hi>Sunne,</hi> it doth <hi>obſcure</hi> all theſe in a glorious <hi>luſtre.</hi> It doth impart <hi>light</hi> and <hi>life</hi> to all who are called <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> to <hi>walke worthy</hi> of their <hi>Vocations,</hi> ſince by our <hi>good workes</hi> wee ſhall <hi>glorifie</hi> our <hi>good God,</hi> that we ſhall <hi>doe good workes</hi> in the ſight of the <hi>Devill, Job</hi> 1.8. and in deſpight of <hi>di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>velliſh men,</hi> 
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, as <hi>Theophylact</hi> ſpeaketh, that our very <hi>enemies</hi> ſhall <hi>approve</hi> us with their <hi>hearts,</hi> though they <hi>reprove</hi> us with their <hi>tongues.</hi> Had I the tongues of men and Angels, I could ſay no more to urge the <hi>neceſsity of good workes,</hi> than what is here ſaid in this Text, in this part of my Text: <hi>Let our light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good workes, and glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>I will ſhut up this <hi>Sermon,</hi> drawing this <hi>one Do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctrine</hi> into a <hi>double</hi> uſefull <hi>Application:</hi> firſt, by way of <hi>apologie, for our Religion,</hi> ſecondly, by way of <hi>An<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tilogie, againſt our Religion.</hi> In the one, I will <hi>pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe</hi> the <hi>Doctrine</hi> of our <hi>Church</hi> to be <hi>admirable;</hi> in the other, I will <hi>confeſſe</hi> the <hi>practice</hi> of our <hi>profeſſors</hi> not to be <hi>anſwerable.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">1 Have I here any <hi>Auditors,</hi> who are <hi>Papiſts,</hi> or <hi>Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſhly affected?</hi> If prejudice and partiality have not <hi>ſtopped both the eares</hi> of ſuch perſons, I crave but <hi>one corner</hi> to receive the <hi>true report</hi> of their <hi>falſe reports</hi> and forged <hi>calumnies,</hi> wherewith they charge our <hi>Church Reformed.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The Proteſtants doe <hi>neglect good workes,</hi> becauſe they doe not hold them <hi>neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> ſaith the <hi>Jeſuit</hi> who did occaſion that rare Treatiſe ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, <hi>The way to the Church, ſect.</hi> 40. <hi>Nil niſi Fidem requirunt. Leſsius</hi> ſaith, the <hi>Proteſtants require no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing
<pb n="103" facs="tcp:18407:54"/>but faith, de Antichriſto, pag.</hi> 250. <hi>Suarez</hi> more fully and foulely too: <hi>Quocunque modo vivunt, per ſolam fidem gloriam ſibi promittunt; &amp; neque Mandatorum obſervationem, neque Poenitentiam eſſe neceſſariam praedicant:</hi> the <hi>Proteſtants</hi> preach (ſaith the <hi>Jeſuite, Apolog.</hi> 5.10. <hi>nu.</hi> 11.) <hi>that it is no matter how men live, promiſing glory by faith alone,</hi> accounting both the <hi>keeping</hi> of the <hi>Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mandements</hi> &amp; <hi>Repentance Unneceſſary. Legem ad Salutem nequaquam eſſe neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſariam, impiè dicere non ſunt veriti,</hi> their <hi>Trent</hi> Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme ſaith, <hi>pag.</hi> 339. we are not affraid to ſay impi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ouſly, <hi>That the Law of God is not neceſſary to Salvati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> The ſame ſmoake ariſeth from a <hi>cloud</hi> of like <hi>wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes, Campian, Dowly, Malvenda, Ferus, Stella, &amp;c.</hi> againſt which loud lewd <hi>Lie,</hi> we appeale to our <hi>God,</hi> to our <hi>Conſciences,</hi> to our <hi>Bookes,</hi> to our <hi>Sermons,</hi> to this <hi>Sermon,</hi> to our <hi>Hearers,</hi> to our very <hi>Children</hi> in their <hi>Catechiſmes,</hi> who were never taught one ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble of ſuch a damnable doctrine.</p>
                  <p>But the beſt is, <hi>Bellarmine</hi> doth bluſh at theſe bold <hi>calumnies; Diſertis verbis docent opera eſſe ad Salu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tem neceſſaria: non quidem neceſsitate Efficientiae, ſed Praeſentiae, de Juſtificat.</hi> 4. The <hi>Proteſtants</hi> (ſaith he) doe <hi>plainly teach, that good workes are neceſſary to Salvation,</hi> not in the act of <hi>Juſtification,</hi> but in the worke of <hi>Sanctification,</hi> without which there can be no <hi>Salvation.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Indeed we <hi>doe not,</hi> indeed we <hi>dare not</hi> avouch with that <hi>Jeſuite</hi> of <hi>Rome,</hi> that at the laſt day wee expect <hi>Juſtum Judicem,</hi> a <hi>Juſt Judge,</hi> not <hi>miſericordem Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trem,</hi> not a <hi>mercifull Father.</hi> Nor with thoſe <hi>Prieſts</hi> of <hi>Rhemes,</hi> that <hi>Heaven</hi> is the <hi>value, worth,</hi> and <hi>price</hi>
                     <pb n="104" facs="tcp:18407:55"/>of our <hi>workes.</hi> For my part I profeſſe, I can <hi>ſwallow</hi> no <hi>Pills,</hi> be they never ſo <hi>artificially gilded.</hi> No <hi>Me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits</hi> will downe with mee, though wrapt up in the quaint phraſe of curious <hi>Campian, Opera tincta ſan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guine Chriſti:</hi> or with the neat diſtinctions of <hi>Condig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, Congruity, &amp;c.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>But if it can be proved, that the <hi>Proteſtant Church</hi> doth hold <hi>dogmatically,</hi> that <hi>good workes are not ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſary to Salvation,</hi> I will turne Papiſt. Againe, if we make it plaine, that they charge us with theſe pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pable, groſſe, ſhamefull and ſhameleſſe <hi>lyes,</hi> onely to ſtrengthen their deſperate reſolution in this damna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble point of <hi>Merits;</hi> mee thinketh an ingenuous Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſt ſhould almoſt be perſwaded <hi>to turne Proteſtant:</hi> only S. <hi>Paul</hi> hath told us, and fore-told of them; there is a generation, <hi>who will not receive the love of the Truth: and therefore God hath ſent on them ſtrong deluſion, that they might beleeve a lye,</hi> 2. <hi>Theſ.</hi> 2.10, 11.</p>
                  <p>Concerning the remnant, a <hi>long Preface</hi> would bee requiſite to mediate for that <hi>ſhort concluſion.</hi> For my <hi>Miſtreſſe Experience</hi> hath taught mee (her <hi>wiſe Scho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar</hi>) that it is <hi>more offenſive</hi> for a <hi>Preacher</hi> to <hi>reprove ſinne,</hi> than for an <hi>Hearer</hi> to <hi>commit it.</hi> I hope there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore and pray, that in this Congregation there bee none of <hi>Malchas</hi> his <hi>kinſmen,</hi> who have <hi>loſt their right eares;</hi> nor none of <hi>Theophraſtus</hi> his <hi>Scholars,</hi> who uſed none but their <hi>left hands,</hi> that whatſoever I <hi>reach</hi> them with a <hi>right hand,</hi> yea and <hi>heart</hi> too, they <hi>receive</hi> it with a <hi>ſiniſter interpretation.</hi> Beloved, I begge an <hi>intelligent</hi> and <hi>charitable</hi> attention. I will <hi>ſpeak</hi> in <hi>verity,</hi> in Gods holy name doe you <hi>heare</hi> in <hi>charity.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="105" facs="tcp:18407:55"/>
                     <hi>Good workes! Good God,</hi> where are thoſe <hi>good men</hi> who doe performe them? ſome few onely excepted.</p>
                  <p n="1">1 The <hi>idleneſſe</hi> of the poore, dejected, unrewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded, unregarded <hi>Mercenaries;</hi> the lofty, lordly de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portment of others more plentifully maintained. The <hi>baſe flattering</hi> of <hi>great ones,</hi> and that <hi>more than moſt baſeſt flattery of the baſe ones,</hi> the <hi>multitude,</hi> to the fomenting of faction, ſchiſme, and diſobedience. Are theſe the <hi>good workes</hi> of our <hi>Clergie?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2 The <hi>ſlow foot</hi> to the <hi>houſe</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>ſtiffe knee</hi> to the <hi>worſhip</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>ſhut hand</hi> to the <hi>members</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> the <hi>evill eye</hi> againſt the <hi>miniſters</hi> of <hi>God,</hi> and (as it is feared) the <hi>ſchiſmaticall heart</hi> in the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>God.</hi> Are theſe the <hi>good workes</hi> of your <hi>Laity?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">3 The hyperexceſſive <hi>prodigality</hi> upon <hi>hawkes, horſes, hounds, drinking, dancing</hi> and <hi>dicing,</hi> and that incredible <hi>parſimonie</hi> towards the <hi>poore,</hi> the <hi>country, Church,</hi> nay their <hi>God.</hi> Are theſe the <hi>good workes</hi> of the <hi>Countrey?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4 The <hi>lying</hi> in <hi>ſhops, ſwearing</hi> in <hi>markets, equivo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cating</hi> in <hi>ſelling, ingratitude,</hi> nay <hi>perſidiouſneſſe</hi> in <hi>borrowing, uſury,</hi> nay <hi>extortion</hi> in <hi>lending;</hi> and that <hi>avarice</hi> is become an <hi>ubiquitary Inmate</hi> in this fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mous <hi>metropolis.</hi> Are theſe the <hi>good workes</hi> of this <hi>City?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="5">5 The <hi>incouraging</hi> and <hi>inſtructing</hi> of <hi>malitious</hi> quarrelſome <hi>Clients,</hi> the <hi>protecting</hi> and <hi>priviledging</hi> of <hi>debtors</hi> and <hi>malefactors;</hi> their <hi>antipathy</hi> to the <hi>Church-government,</hi> becauſe of the <hi>Churches anti ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> and the ſpinning out of <hi>Law-Suits</hi> with <hi>long</hi> and <hi>coſtly</hi> proceedings, oft times to the <hi>undoing</hi> of <hi>Plaintife</hi> and <hi>Defendant</hi> too. Certainly ſuch <hi>Law<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yers</hi>
                     <pb n="106" facs="tcp:18407:56"/>are <hi>no Papiſts,</hi> for they meane <hi>not to merit hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> by ſuch <hi>good workes.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="6">6 That a <hi>Gallant</hi> may not <hi>heare the lye,</hi> but that his <hi>ſword</hi> muſt <hi>right it,</hi> and <hi>write it</hi> in the <hi>blood</hi> of his reproacher, or <hi>loſe</hi> his owne in aſſaying it. That a <hi>Gallantreſſe</hi> may not <hi>ſee</hi> that <hi>woman,</hi> but that her <hi>foot</hi> or <hi>heart</hi> muſt preſſe <hi>before</hi> her: onely to <hi>Church</hi> and <hi>Heaven</hi> ſhee will give <hi>precedence</hi> to any. That <hi>Hee</hi> doth torment the <hi>Taylour, Shee</hi> the <hi>Sempſter,</hi> both the <hi>Divell with inventing faſhions:</hi> that both ſpend more time in <hi>cutting, curling, powdring,</hi> and <hi>plaiting</hi> their <hi>haire,</hi> than they doe in <hi>praying</hi> either in <hi>publike</hi> or in <hi>private;</hi> and that they make themſelves <hi>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters</hi> by their <hi>miſhapen attire:</hi> I can hardly contrive theſe <hi>good works</hi> within the compaſſe of my <hi>text,</hi> and of the <hi>holy Scriptures.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="7">7 That <hi>worke</hi> of our <hi>Nation</hi> is <hi>no good worke;</hi> that which maketh our <hi>Kingdome</hi> a ſcorne to our foes, a ſorrow to our friends, a ſhame to our ſelves: That <hi>Noli me tangere,</hi> and <hi>Noli me nominare</hi> too; <hi>I dare not name it.</hi> But Chriſt doth <hi>name it,</hi> and <hi>curſe it too, Luk.</hi> 11.17. <hi>That worke</hi> will bring <hi>this land</hi> to a ſpee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy <hi>confuſion,</hi> if <hi>God</hi> doth not <hi>ſhield</hi> it by his <hi>mercifull protection, and miraculous prevention.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="8">8 But the <hi>Antipodes to all good workes,</hi> is that <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minary of all bad works;</hi> that <hi>worke</hi>—which here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tofore hath beene <hi>hated</hi> of the <hi>Heathen,</hi> now <hi>practi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed, patroniſed,</hi> yea <hi>purchaſed</hi> by <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> by <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtants: Sacriledge</hi> and <hi>Church-robbing.</hi> What? be a <hi>thiefe</hi> to my <hi>God? Maſter is it I?</hi> every one will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pologize for himſelfe in the phraſe of that <hi>innocent Apoſtle.</hi> I would to God <hi>there were no coine in my cot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tage,
<pb n="107" facs="tcp:18407:56"/>no bread in my cupboard, no bookes in my Study, no breath in my body,</hi> conditionally there were <hi>no ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crilegious Church-robbers</hi> in this <hi>Kingdome.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>The <hi>ſtones</hi> in their <hi>walls,</hi> the <hi>ſheaves</hi> in their <hi>barnes,</hi> and the <hi>loaves</hi> on their <hi>tables,</hi> will cry <hi>ſacriledge</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt many a man of worth in our nation.</p>
                  <p>This <hi>goodly,</hi> but <hi>drouping Edifice,</hi> if it ſhould <hi>drop downe;</hi> and <hi>bury us,</hi> either <hi>talking</hi> in the <hi>Church,</hi> or <hi>praying</hi> in the <hi>Quire,</hi> we ſhould be no <hi>Martyrs,</hi> who eſteem <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, all <hi>coſt loſt,</hi> which might be beſtow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on ſo <hi>religious a reparation;</hi> nay, ſo <hi>neceſſary a prevention.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>That ſo many perſons in too many Pariſhes are in want of <hi>ſpirituall bread</hi> under their <hi>temporall Tith-takers:</hi> wee need not <hi>glory</hi> in our <hi>merits,</hi> that wee ſuſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend our aſſiſtance from thoſe <hi>ſilly ſoules.</hi> The <hi>people may periſh where prophecy faileth.</hi> Beloved, there is a <hi>poſitive,</hi> and there is a <hi>privative ſacriledge. Cain</hi> was <hi>profane,</hi> though peradventure <hi>ſeventy times ſhort</hi> of <hi>Lamech</hi> in <hi>profaneneſſe.</hi> To <hi>withdraw</hi> what the <hi>Church hath,</hi> and <hi>to withhold</hi> what the <hi>Church</hi> doth <hi>need:</hi> the later is <hi>ſacriledge</hi> as <hi>well,</hi> though <hi>not as much</hi> as the former.</p>
                  <p>There is one, and but one <hi>ſalve</hi> for this <hi>ſore,</hi> the <hi>re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption of Impropriations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Let not <hi>Impropriatours</hi> ſtart, I plead not for im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſibilities; not that they ſhould <hi>give</hi> them, but that wee ſhould <hi>buy</hi> them: That <hi>every man ſhould lay by him in ſtore as God hath proſpered him,</hi> till that his <hi>private charity</hi> might find <hi>opportunity,</hi> and (if God hath ſuch a bleſſing in ſtore for us) be enabled by <hi>pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>like authority,</hi> to concurre in the <hi>buying</hi> in of <hi>Impro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priations.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <pb n="108" facs="tcp:18407:57"/>If <hi>Authority</hi> would <hi>open that Treaſury</hi> for <hi>Gods houſe,</hi> the <hi>rich</hi> men would <hi>caſt in their gifts,</hi> and <hi>the widowes</hi> would caſt in thither their <hi>mites</hi> alſo. And the <hi>bleſsing</hi> of <hi>Jeroboam</hi> be upon that <hi>hand,</hi> which would be <hi>clutched</hi> in ſuch a <hi>contribution.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This would be the <hi>accompliſhment</hi> of this <hi>text,</hi> in one <hi>ſuperlative</hi> particular. If wee ſhould <hi>light that torch</hi> which <hi>Popery</hi> hath <hi>extinguiſhed: Then, would our light ſo ſhine before men, that they would ſee That good worke, and glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi> Yea, for this preſent my meditations apprehend ſuch a <hi>good worke</hi> to be our <hi>beſt Orator,</hi> to <hi>begge</hi> a <hi>bleſsing</hi> upon our <hi>kingdome;</hi> upon the <hi>Epitome</hi> thereof, the <hi>Honourable high Court of Parliament;</hi> upon the <hi>Head</hi> thereof, his <hi>Roiall Majeſty.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>As therefore we <hi>love</hi> our <hi>King,</hi> as we <hi>love</hi> our <hi>King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome,</hi> as we <hi>love</hi> our <hi>Church,</hi> as we <hi>love</hi> our <hi>Soules:</hi> ſo in this point, <hi>Let our light ſo ſhine before men, that they may ſee our good workes, and glorifie our Father which is in heaven.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Frange Domine panem quidem tuum, manibus meis:</hi> I have <hi>delivered thy Meſſage, to thy people;</hi> I have ſpoken to their <hi>Eares, Lord Jeſus ſpeake unto their Hearts.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
                  <pb facs="tcp:18407:57"/>
               </div>
            </body>
         </text>
      </group>
   </text>
</TEI>
